<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/about.xml">
  <properties>
    <title>Data access with the Spring framework</title>
    <abstract>
       Data access with the Spring framework
    </abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <title>Data access with the Spring framework</title>
    <header>
Data Access with the Spring Framework

(featuring Castor JDO examples)

Werner Guttmann

June 2005
    </header>
    
    <p>This article is copy of the article <a href="">article</a> written by
       <a href="">Juergen Hoeller</a> a few months ago to showcase the
       integration of Hbernate with Spring. I have replaced Hibernate-specific 
       references with Castor JDO ones, but tried to maintain the structure
       of the original document wherever possible. It's almost unnecessary to 
       mention that all credits go to the original author.</p>

    <section name="Preface: Spring Benefits for Castor Users">
		
		<p>Spring's lightweight bean container offers IoC-style wiring up of business objects, DAOs, and 
		   resources like JDBC DataSources and Castor JDO JDOManager instances. Such an XML-defined 
		   application context is a powerful alternative to manually managed singletons or factories that 
		   parse their configuration from custom properties files. As non-intrusiveness is a central 
		   goal, such Spring-configured application beans do not need to depend on Spring interfaces 
		   or classes but get configured via their bean properties. This concept can be applied in any 
		   environment, be it a J2EE web app, a desktop app, or even an applet.</p>

		<p>In the context of Castor JDO, Spring's generic transaction management for DAOs is of particular 
		   interest. The goal is to separate data access and transaction demarcation aspects to allow for 
		   reusable transactional business objects that are not tied to any specific data access or 
		   transaction strategy. Demarcation can either happen programmatically via TransactionTemplate, 
		   or declaratively via the AOP TransactionInterceptor. Both native Castor JDO / JDBC transactions 
		   and JTA are supported as strategies out-of-the-box. This is a viable alternative to local 
		   Stateless Session Beans.</p>

		<p>Spring's CastorTemplate offers a simple way to implement Castor JDO-based DAOs without caring 
		   about handling Database instances or participating in transactions. No need for try-catch 
		   blocks, no need for transaction checks. A simple Castor JDO access method can be a one-liner! 
		   Combining heterogeneous DAOs works seamlessly, both in terms of DAO interfaces and participating 
		   in transactions. For example, certain DAOs can be implemented on plain JDBC, preferably via 
		   Spring's JdbcTemplate to avoid manual exception handling.</p>

		<p>You can use a lot of Spring's features respectively classes in a library style, as everything 
		   is designed as a set of reusable JavaBeans. Don't be discouraged by the fact that Spring 
		   can serve as full application framework too! The application context concept is an additional 
		   benefit, not a requirement for using other Spring features. In any case, you're invited to 
		   review and leverage the Spring approach, no matter to what extent, before deciding to take the effort 
		   and risk of building such infrastructure in-house.</p>
		
	</section>
	
	<section name="Introduction: Resource Management">

		<p>Typical business applications are often cluttered with repetitive resource management code. 
		   Many projects try to invent own solutions for this issue, sometimes sacrificing proper handling 
		   of failures for programming convenience. Spring advocates strikingly simple solutions for 
		   proper resource handling: Inversion of control via templating, i.e. infrastructure classes 
		   with callback interfaces, or applying AOP interceptors. The infrastructure cares for proper 
		   resource handling, and for appropriate conversion of specific API exceptions to an unchecked 
		   infrastructure exception hierarchy.</p>

		<p>Spring introduces a DAO exception hierarchy, applicable to any data access strategy. For direct 
		   JDBC, the JdbcTemplate class cares for connection handling, and for proper conversion of 
		   SQLException to the DataAccessException hierarchy, including translation of database-specific 
		   SQL error codes to meaningful exception classes. It supports both JTA and JDBC transactions, 
		   via respective Spring transaction managers. Spring also offers Castor JDO, Hibernate and JDO support, 
		   consisting of a CastorTemplate / HibernateTemplate / JdoTemplate analogous to JdbcTemplate, a 
		   CastorInterceptor / HibernateInterceptor / JdoInterceptor, and a Castor JDO / Hibernate / JDO 
		   transaction manager.</p>

		<p>The major goal is to allow for clear application layering, with any data access and transaction 
		   technology, and for loose coupling of application objects. No more business object 
		   dependencies on the data access or transaction strategy, no more hard-coded resource lookups, 
		   no more hard-to-replace singletons, no more custom service registries. One simple and 
		   consistent approach to wiring up application objects, keeping them as reusable and free 
		   from container dependencies as possible.</p>

		<p>All the individual data access features are usable on their own but integrate nicely with 
		   Spring's application context concept, providing XML-based configuration and cross-referencing 
		   of plain JavaBean instances that don't need to be Spring-aware. In a typical Spring app, 
		   many important objects are JavaBeans: data access templates, data access objects (that use the 
		   templates), transaction managers, business objects (that use the data access objects and 
		   transaction managers), web view resolvers, web controllers (that use the business objects),
		   etc.</p>

	</section>
	
	<section name="Resource Definitions in an Application Context">

		<p>To avoid tying application objects to hard-coded resource lookups, Spring allows to define 
		   resources like <!--  a JDBC DataSource or --> a Castor JDOManager as beans in an application context. 
		   Application objects that need to access resources just receive references to such pre-defined 
		   instances via bean references (the DAO definition in the next section illustrates this). The 
		   following excerpt from an XML application context definition shows how to set up <!-- a JDBC 
		   DataSource and --> a Castor JDOManager <!-- on top of it -->:</p>

<!-- 
<source>
&lt;bean id="myDataSource" class="org.springframework.jndi.JndiObjectFactoryBean&gt;
  &lt;property name="jndiName"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;jdbc/myds&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>
 -->
<source>
&lt;bean id="jdoManager" class="org.castor.spring.orm.LocalCastorFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="databaseName" value="test" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="configLocation" value="classpath:jdo-conf.xml" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>

		<p>The JDO configuration file for <tt>hSQL</tt> looks as follows:</p>
		
<source>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" ?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE jdo-conf PUBLIC "-//EXOLAB/Castor JDO Configuration DTD Version 1.0//EN" "http://castor.org/jdo-conf.dtd"&gt;
&lt;jdo-conf&gt;
  &lt;database name="hsqldb" engine="hsql"&gt;
    &lt;driver class-name="org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver" url="jdbc:hsqldb:hsql://localhost:9002/dbname"&gt;
      &lt;param name="user" value="sa"/&gt;
      &lt;param name="password" value=""/&gt;
    &lt;/driver&gt;
    &lt;mapping href="mapping.xml"/&gt;
  &lt;/database&gt;
  &lt;transaction-demarcation mode="local"/&gt;
&lt;/jdo-conf&gt;
</source>
<!-- 
		<p>Note that switching from a JNDI-located DataSource to a locally defined one like a 
		   Jakarta Commons DBCP BasicDataSource is just a matter of configuration:</p>

<source>
&lt;bean id="myDataSource" class="org.apache.commons.dbcp.BasicDataSource" destroy-method="close"&gt;
  &lt;property name="driverClassName"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;com.mysql.jdbc.Driver&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="url"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;jdbc:mysql://localhost:3306/test&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="username"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;test&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="password"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;test&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;	
</source>
-->
		<p>You can also use a JNDI-located JDOManager, but that's typically not necessary outside an 
		   EJB context (see the "container resources vs local resources" section for a discussion).</p>

	</section>
	
	<section name="Inversion of Control: Template and Callback">

		<p>The basic programming model for templating looks as follows, for methods that can be part of any 
		   custom data access object or business object. There are no restrictions on the implementation of 
		   the surrounding object at all, it just needs to provide a Castor JDOManager. It can get the latter 
		   from anywhere, but preferably as bean reference from a Spring application context - via a 
		   simple setJDOMaanger bean property setter. The following snippets show a DAO definition in a 
		
		   Spring application context, referencing the above defined JDOManager, and an example for a DAO 
		   method implementation.</p>


<source>
&lt;bean id="myProductDao" class="product.ProductDaoImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="JDOManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myJdoManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>

<source>
public class ProductDaoImpl implements ProductDao {

  private JDOManager jdoManager;

  public void setJDOManager(JDOManager jdoManager) {
    this.jdoManager = jdoManager;
  }

  public Product loadProduct(final int id) {
    CastorTemplate template = new CastorTemplate(this.jdoManager);
    return (Product) template.execute(
        new CastorCallback() {
          public Object doInCastor(Database database) throws PersistenceException {
            return (Product) database.load(Product.class, new Integer (id));
          }
        });
  }
}
</source>

		<p>A callback implementation can effectively be used for any Castor JDO data access. CastorTemplate 
		   will care for proper Database opening and closing in any case, and for automatically participating 
		   in transactions. The template instances are thread-safe and reusable, they can thus be kept as 
		   instance variables of the surrounding class.</p>

		<p>For simple single step actions like a single find, load, saveOrUpdate, or delete call,
		   CastorTemplate offers alternative convenience methods that can replace such one line 
		   callback implementations. Furthermore, Spring provides a convenient CastorDaoSupport base class 
		   that provides a setJDOManager method for receiving a JDOManager, and getJDOManager and 
		   getCastorTemplate for use by subclasses. In combination, this allows for very simple DAO 
		   implementations for typical requirements:</p>

<source>
public class ProductDaoImpl extends CastorDaoSupport implements ProductDao {

  public List loadProduct(final int id) {
    return getCastorTemplate().load(Product.class, new Integer (id));
  }
}
</source>

	</section>
	
	<section name="Applying an AOP Interceptor Instead of a Template">

		<p>An alternative to using a CastorTemplate is Spring's AOP CastorInterceptor, replacing the 
		   callback implementation with straight Castort JDO code within a delegating try/catch block, 
		   and a respective interceptor configuration in the application context. The following snippets 
		   show respective DAO, interceptor, and proxy definitions in a Spring application context, and 
		   an example for a DAO method implementation.</p>

<source>
&lt;bean id="myCastorInterceptor" class="org.castor.spring.orm.CastorInterceptor"&gt;
  &lt;property name="JDOManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myJdoManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductDaoTarget" class="product.ProductDaoImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="JDOManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myJdoManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductDao" class="org.springframework.aop.framework.ProxyFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="proxyInterfaces"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;product.ProductDao&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="interceptorNames"&gt;
    &lt;list&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;myCastorInterceptor&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;myProductDaoTarget&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;/list&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>

<source>
public class ProductDaoImpl extends CastorDaoSupport implements ProductDao {

  public List loadProduct(final int id) throws MyException {
    Database database = JDOManagerUtils.getDatabase(getJDOManager(), false);
    try {
      Product product = database.load(Product.class, new Integer (1));
      if (product == null) {
        throw new MyException("No Product instance found with id " + id);
      }
      return product;
    }
    catch (PersistenceException ex) {
      throw JDOManagerUtils.convertJdoAccessException(ex);
    }
  }
}
</source>

		<p>This method will only work with a CastorInterceptor for it, caring for opening a thread-bound 
		   Database before and closing it after the method call. The "false" flag on getDatabase makes sure 
		   that the Database must already exist; else JDOManagerUtils would create a new one if none 
		   found. If there is already a DatabaseHolder bound to the thread, e.g. by a 
		   CastoreTransactionManager transaction, JDOManagerUtils automatically takes part in it in any 
		   case. CastorTemplate uses JDOManagerUtils underneath - it's all the same infrastructure.</p>

		<p>The major advantage of CastorInterceptor is that it allows any checked application exception 
		   to be thrown within the data access code, while CastorTemplate is restricted to unchecked 
		   exceptions within the callback. Note that one can offen defer the respective checks and 
		   throwing of application exceptions to after the callback, though. The interceptor's major 
		   drawback is that it requires special setup in the context. CastorTemplate's convenience 
		   methods offers simpler means for many scenarios.</p>

	</section>
	
	<section name="Programmatic Transaction Demarcation">

		<p>On top of such lower-level data access services, transactions can be demarcated in a higher level 
		   of the application, spanning any number of operations. There are no restrictions on the 
		   implementation of the surrounding business object here too, it just needs a Spring 
		   PlatformTransactionManager. Again, the latter can come from anywhere, but preferably as 
		   bean reference via a setTransactionManager method - just like the productDAO should be set via 
		   a setProductDao method. The following snippets show a transaction manager and a business object 
		   definition in a Spring application context, and an example for a business method 
		   implementation.</p>


<source>
&lt;bean id="myTransactionManager" class="org.castor.spring.orm.CastorTransactionManager"&gt;
  &lt;property name="JDOManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myJdoManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductService" class="product.ProductServiceImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="transactionManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myTransactionManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="productDao"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myProductDao"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>

<source>
public class ProductServiceImpl implements ProductService {

  private PlatformTransactionManager transactionManager;
  private ProductDao productDao;

  public void setTransactionManager(PlatformTransactionManager transactionManager) {
    this.transactionManager = transactionManager;
  }

  public void setProductDao(ProductDao productDao) {
    this.productDao = productDao;
  }

  public void loadProductAndModifyName(final int id, final String name) {
    TransactionTemplate transactionTemplate = new TransactionTemplate(this.transactionManager);
    transactionTemplate.setPropagationBehavior(TransactionDefinition.PROPAGATION_REQUIRED);
    transactionTemplate.execute(new TransactionCallbackWithoutResult() {
      public void doInTransactionWithoutResult(TransactionStatus status) {
        Product product = productDAO.loadProduct(id);
		product.setName(name);
        ...
      }
    });
  }
}
</source>

	</section>
	
	<section name="Declarative Transaction Demarcation">
		
		<p>Alternatively, one can use Spring's AOP TransactionInterceptor, replacing the transaction 
		   demarcation code with an interceptor configuration in the application context. This allows 
		   to keep business objects free from repetitive transaction demarcation code in each business 
		   method. Furthermore, transaction semantics like propagation behavior and isolation level can 
		   be changed in a configuration file and do not affect the business object implementations.</p>

<source>
&lt;bean id="myTransactionManager" class="org.castor.spring.orm.CastorTransactionManager"&gt;
  &lt;property name="JDOManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myJdoManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myTransactionInterceptor" class="org.springframework.transaction.interceptor.TransactionInterceptor"&gt;
  &lt;property name="transactionManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myTransactionManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="transactionAttributeSource"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      product.ProductService.loadProductAndModifyName*=PROPAGATION_REQUIRED
   &lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductServiceTarget" class="product.ProductServiceImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="productDao"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myProductDao"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductService" class="org.springframework.aop.framework.ProxyFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="proxyInterfaces"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;product.ProductService&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="interceptorNames"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;myTransactionInterceptor,myProductServiceTarget&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>

<source>
public class ProductServiceImpl implements ProductService {

  private ProductDao productDao;

  public void setProductDao(ProductDao productDao) {
    this.productDao = productDao;
  }

  public void loadProductAndModifyName(final int id, final String name) {
    Product product = productDAO.loadProduct(id);
	product.setName(name);
    ...
  }
}
</source>

		<p>Like with CastorInterceptor, TransactionInterceptor allows any checked application exception 
		   to be thrown with the callback code, while TransactionTemplate is restricted to unchecked 
		   exceptions within the callback. TransactionTemplate will trigger a rollback in case of an 
		   unchecked application exception, or if the transaction has been marked rollback-only by the 
		   application (via TransactionStatus). TransactionInterceptor behaves the same way by default 
		   but allows configurable rollback policies per method.</p>

		<p>A convenient alternative way of setting up declarative transactions is TransactionProxyFactoryBean, 
		   particularly if there are no other AOP interceptors involved. TransactionProxyFactoryBean combines 
		   the proxy definition itself with transaction configuration for a particular target bean. This 
		   reduces the configuration effort to one target bean plus one proxy bean. Furthermore, you do 
		   not need to specify which interfaces or classes the transactional methods are defined in.</p>

<source>
&lt;bean id="myTransactionManager" class="org.castor.spring.orm.CastorTransactionManager"&gt;
  &lt;property name="JDOManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myJdoManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductServiceTarget" class="product.ProductServiceImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="productDao"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myProductDao"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductService" class="org.springframework.transaction.interceptor.TransactionProxyFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="transactionManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myTransactionManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="target"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myProductServiceTarget"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="transactionAttributes"&gt;
    &lt;props&gt;
      &lt;prop key="loadProductAndModifyName*"&gt;PROPAGATION_REQUIRED&lt;/prop&gt;
    &lt;/props&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>

	</section>
	
	<section name="Transaction Management Strategies">

		<p>Both TransactionTemplate and TransactionInterceptor delegate the 
           actual transaction handling to a PlatformTransactionManager instance, which 
           can be a CastorTransactionManager (for a single Castor JDOManager) or a 
           JtaTransactionManager (delegating to the JTA subsystem of the container) for 
           Castor JDO applications. You could even use a custom PlatformTransactionManager 
		   implementation.</p>

		<p>So switching from native Castor JDO transaction management to JTA, i.e. 
           when facing distributed transaction requirements for certain deployments 
           of your application, is just a matter of configuration. Simply replace the 
           Castor transaction manager with Spring's JTA transaction implementation. Both 
           transaction demarcation and data access code will work without changes, as 
           they just use the generic transaction management APIs.</p>

		<p>For distributed transactions across multiple Castor session factories, simply 
           combine JtaTransactionManager as transaction strategy with multiple 
           LocalCastorFactoryBean definitions. Each of your DAOs then gets one specific 
           JDOManager reference passed into its respective bean property. If all 
           underlying JDBC data sources are transactional container ones, a 
           business object can demarcate transactions across any number of DAOs and 
		   any number of JDOManager instances without special regard, as long as using 
		   JtaTransactionManager as strategy.</p>

<source>
	&lt;bean id="myDataSource1" class="org.springframework.jndi.JndiObjectFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="jndiName"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;jdbc/myds1&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myDataSource2" class="org.springframework.jndi.JndiObjectFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="jndiName"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;jdbc/myds2&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="jdoManager1" class="org.castor.spring.orm.LocalCastorFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="jdoProperties"&gt;
    &lt;props&gt;
      &lt;prop key="databaseName"&gt;test1&lt;/prop&gt;
      &lt;prop key="configLocation"&gt;src/spring/jdo-conf1.xml&lt;/prop&gt;
    &lt;/props&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="jdoManager2" class="org.castor.spring.orm.LocalCastorFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="jdoProperties"&gt;
    &lt;props&gt;
      &lt;prop key="databaseName"&gt;test2&lt;/prop&gt;
      &lt;prop key="configLocation"&gt;src/spring/jdo-conf2.xml&lt;/prop&gt;
    &lt;/props&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myTransactionManager" 
         class="org.springframework.transaction.jta.JtaTransactionManager"/&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductDao" class="product.ProductDaoImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="JDOManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="jdoManager1"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myInventoryDao" class="product.InventoryDaoImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="JDOManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="jdoManager2"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductServiceTarget" class="product.ProductServiceImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="productDao"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myProductDao"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="inventoryDao"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myInventoryDao"/&gt;
   &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="myProductService" 
         class="org.springframework.transaction.interceptor.TransactionProxyFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="transactionManager"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myTransactionManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="target"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myProductServiceTarget"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="transactionAttributes"&gt;
    &lt;props&gt;
      &lt;prop key="increasePrice*"&gt;PROPAGATION_REQUIRE&lt;&lt;/prop&gt;
      &lt;prop key="someOtherBusinessMethod"&gt;PROPAGATION_MANDATORY&lt;/prop&gt;
    &lt;/props&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>

		<p>Both CastorTransactionManager and JtaTransactionManager allow for proper JVM-level cache 
		   handling with Castor JDO - without container-specific transaction manager lookup or 
		   JCA connector (as long as not using EJB to initiate transactions). Additionally, 
		   CastorTransactionManager can export the JDBC Connection used by Castor JDO to plain 
		   JDBC access code. This allows for high level transaction demarcation with mixed 
		   Castor JDO/JDBC data access completely without JTA, as long as just accessing 
		   one database!</p>
           
        <p>Even when not running within an EJB container, it is still possible to 
           use a stand-alone transaction manager that supports coordination of distributed
           transactions with Spring (and thus Castor JDO) such as JOTM. To allow the
           use of JOTM in such a scenario, you simply have to replace above definition
           of <tt>myTransactionManager</tt> with the following one:</p>

<source>
&lt;bean id="jotm" class="org.springframework.transaction.jta.JotmFactoryBean"/&gt;

&lt;bean id="myTransactionManager" 
       class="org.springframework.transaction.jta.JtaTransactionManager"&gt;
   &lt;property name="userTransaction" ref="jotm"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>
		
	</section>
	
	<section name="Using Spring-managed Application Beans">

		<p>A Spring application context definition can be loaded with a variety of context 
		   implementations, from FileSystemXmlApplicationContext and 
           ClassPathXmlApplicationContext to XmlWebApplicationContext. This allows for 
           reuse of Spring-managed data access and business objects 
		   in all kinds of environments. By default, a web app will have its root context 
		   defined in "WEB-INF/applicationContext.xml".</p>

		<p>In any Spring app, an application context defined in an XML file wires up 
           all the application beans that are involved, from the Hibernate session 
           factory to custom data access and  business objects (like the beans above). Most 
           of them do not have to be aware of being managed by the Spring container, not 
           even when collaborating with other beans, as they simply follow JavaBeans 
           conventions. A bean property can either represent a value parameter or 
		   a collaborating bean. The following bean definition could be part of a 
           Spring web MVC context  that accesses business beans in a root application context.</p>

<source>
&lt;bean id="myProductList" class="product.ProductListController"&gt;
  &lt;property name="productService"&gt;
    &lt;ref bean="myProductService"/&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
</source>

		<p>Spring web controllers are provided with all business or data access objects they need via 
		   bean references, so there typically isn't any need to do manual bean lookups in the 
		   application context. But when using Spring-managed beans with Struts, or within an EJB 
		   implementation or even an applet, one is always able to look up a bean manually. Therefore, 
		   Spring beans can be leveraged virtually anywhere. One just needs a reference to the 
		   application context, be it via a servlet context attribute in the web case, or a manually 
		   created instance from a file or class path resource.</p>

<source>
ApplicationContext context = WebApplicationContextUtils.getWebApplicationContext(servletContext);
ProductService productService = (ProductService) context.getBean("myProductService");
</source>

<source>
ApplicationContext context = new FileSystemXmlApplicationContext("C:/myContext.xml");
ProductService productService = (ProductService) context.getBean("myProductService");
</source>

<source>
ApplicationContext context = new ClassPathXmlApplicationContext("myContext.xml");
ProductService productService = (ProductService) context.getBean("myProductService");
</source>

	</section>


	<section name="Skeletons and Samples">

		<p>For a commented and detailed sample configuration of a J2EE web app with Spring 
		   and Castor, have a look at the "webapp-typical" skeleton, included in the Spring 
		   Framework distribution. It outlines various data source and transaction manager 
		   configuration options that are suitable for JDBC and Castor JDO apps. It also shows 
		   how to configure AOP interceptors, focusing on the transaction interceptor.</p>

		<p>As of release 1.0 M2, the Petclinic sample in the Spring distribution offers 
           alternative DAO implementations and application context configurations for JDBC 
           and Castor. Petclinic can therefore serve as working sample app that illustrates 
           the use of Castor in a Spring web app. It also leverages declarative transaction 
           demarcation with different transaction strategies.</p>

    </section>

  </body>
</document>