<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/download.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Download</title>
    <header>
      <p>For FTP access use <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/</url></p>
      <ul><b>Lastest Released Version: Castor $VERSION$</b>
        <li>The Castor JAR (XML, JDO, DAX)<br/>
            <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_$VERSION$/castor-$VERSION$.jar</url>
            <br/>&#xA0;</li>
        <li>The Castor JAR (XML only)<br/>
            <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_$VERSION$/castor-$VERSION$-xml.jar</url>
            <br/>&#xA0;</li>
        <li>The Castor JARs, docs, DTDs, command line tools and examples<br/>
            <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_$VERSION$/castor-$VERSION$.tgz</url><br/>
            <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_$VERSION$/castor-$VERSION$.zip</url>
            <br/>&#xA0;</li>
        <li>Full documentation including all JavaDocs and specs (big)<br/>
            <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_$VERSION$/castor-$VERSION$-doc.tgz</url><br/>
            <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_$VERSION$/castor-$VERSION$-doc.zip</url>
            <br/>&#xA0;</li>
        <li>Full CVS snapshot: all sources, docs, libraries (big)<br/>
            <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_$VERSION$/castor-$VERSION$-src.tgz</url><br/>
            <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_$VERSION$/castor-$VERSION$-src.zip</url>
            <br/>&#xA0;</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Notes:</p>

      <p>
         For Latest CVS version use our CVS server
         (<a href="cvs.xml">CVS Information</a>) or
         for those of you behind a firewall with the CVS port non-accessible, feel free to
         use the daily-snapshot here:
        <url>ftp://ftp.exolab.org/pub/castor/castor_daily_snapshot.tgz</url>
      </p>

      <p><small>The tarball and zips includes all the JARs required by Castor, the
         docs and API JavaDocs. To fully install Castor, simply extract all the JARs
         into your classpath.</small></p>

      <p><small>The CVS snapshot includes additional JARs required to build Castor.
         It is self sufficient and does not require any external components, except
         for javac.</small></p>

      <p><small>The documentation set includes JavaDocs for the API and JavaDocs
         for the full source code, including class usage. A small documentation
         set without the full source JavaDocs is available in the tarball and
         zips.</small></p>

      <p><small>All the JARs included with Castor and used for building Castor
         are available for distribution free of charge, subject to the respective
         license agreements.</small></p>

      <p><small>All implementation JARs (i.e. non APIs) are available under an
         open source license and available from our FTP server.
         Open source licenses in use include Apache (ASF), Exolab, Mozilla (MPL),
         and public domain. All licenses are fully compatible with each other.</small></p>

    </header>
  </body>
</document>



