<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/examples.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Running The Examples</title>

    <section title="Running The Examples">

      <p>
      In order to run the examples located in <tt>src/examples</tt>, there are
      number of steps that must first take place. these steps are outlined below:

      <ol type="1">
          <li>Download the Castor source via either <a href="download.html">FTP</a>
          or <a href="cvs.html">CVS</a>. If the source has been downloaded via FTP,
          it must be decompressed. This is dependent on whether a gzipped tarball
          has been downloaded or a zip file has been downloaded.<br /><br />

          Steps for a gzipped tarball:

          <br /><br />

          <tt>tar zxvf castor-0.9.3.9-src.tgz</tt><br />

          or<br />

          <tt>gunzip &lt; castor-0.9.3.9-src.tgz | tar xvf -</tt>

          <br /><br />

          Steps for a zip file:

          <br /><br />

          <tt>unzip castor-0.9.3.9-src.zip</tt><br />

          or<br />

          <tt>jar xvf castor-0.9.3.9-src.zip</tt><br />

          or<br />

          Get a copy of <a href="http://www.powerarchiver.com/">PowerArchiver</a><br /><br />

          </li>
          <li>If you're using Unix/Linux, the shell scripts must be made executable
          and the line endings must be changed. Use the following directions:

          <br /><br />

          <ol type="a">
              <li>
              Make the shell scripts executable:

              <br /><br />

              <tt>chmod +x *.sh</tt><br /><br />
              </li>

              <li>
              Change the line endings on the shell scripts:

              <br /><br />

              <tt>for i in *.sh; do dos2unix $i $i; done</tt><br /><br />
              </li>
          </ol>

          </li>

          <li>
          If it is not set yet, please set the <tt>JAVA_HOME</tt> environment variable.
          </li>

          <li>
          Edit <tt>src/examples/jdo/database.xml</tt> for the database being used.
          (There are examples for all supported databases in <tt>src/tests/jdo</tt>.)
          </li>

          <li>
          Build the examples like so:

          <br /><br />

          <tt>build.[sh|bat] examples</tt>

          <br /><br />

          This will not only build the examples, but will also build the Castor classes.
          </li>

          <li>
          Add the appropriate classes for the database driver to the <tt>CLASSPATH</tt>.
          </li>

          <li>
          Run the examples using the directions in the next section.
          </li>
      </ol>

      </p>

      <p>The script files <tt>example.sh</tt> and <tt>example.bat</tt> can
         be used to run the provided examples. The first argument is the example
         package name. For example, to build and run the JDO example:
<pre>
  build.sh examples
  example.sh jdo
</pre>
      </p>

    </section>

    <section title="Castor JDO">

      <p>The JDO sample will test persistence between a set of Java classes
         (Product, ProductGroup, ProductDetail) and a known SQL schema.
         You can use the <tt>create.sql</tt> file to generate the database schema
         for the purpose of this test.</p>

      <p>The mapping between the Java objects and SQL schema is described in
         the file <tt>mapping.xml</tt>. The JDBC connection to use is describes
         in the file <tt>database.xml</tt>. The provided file uses PostgreSQL as
         the database server and JDBC driver, you can modify this file for your database
         server and use any JDBC 1.0 or 2.0 driver.</p>

      <p>The database information and mapping are automatically read from the
         JDO example directory, there is no need to provide any parameters on
         the command line.</p>

      <p>The performance test uses the ODMG engine as well as direct JDBC
         access. You must provide the JDBC URI and class name to use for
         this test on the command line.</p>

      <p>Usage:
         <code>
  example.sh jdo
         </code></p>
    </section>

    <section title="Castor DSML">

      <p>Do not run this sample against a production LDAP server unless you
         are sure it will not affect the information in your directory!</p>

      <p>The DSML sample will attempt to import the supplied directory
         information from the test.xml file using the import policy described
         in the <tt>import.xml</tt>. file. It will then run a search against the
         LDAP server using the search criteria in the search.xml file and dump it
         to the console.</p>

      <p>You must modify <tt>search.xml</tt>, <tt>import.xml</tt> and
         <tt>test.xml</tt> and adapt them to your LDAP directory structure.
         The default files assumes the root directory dc=intalio,dc=com and
         includes some sample LDAP entries.</p>

      <p>Usage:
         <code><![CDATA[
  test.sh dsml [jndi|mozilla] <host> <root-dn> <root-pwd>

  jndi|mozilla  Selects whether to use the JNDI or Mozilla Directory
	        SDK implementations
  host          The LDAP host name (port number is optional)
  rood-dn       The root DN used for authenticating when importing
  root-pwd      The root password used for authenticating when importing
]]></code>
         For example:
         <code>
  example.sh dsml mozilla ldap.intalio.com dc=intalio,dc=com secret
         </code></p>

    </section>

    <section title="External Examples">
      <p>
         This sections provides a place link external examples of using
         Castor. If you have an example that you feel would be useful
         please send us the URL. Also notify us if any links are
         broken.
      </p>
      <section title="ebXMLsoft">
         <p>Goran Zugic and Duka Krunic of ebXMLsoft Inc. have some samples
            using Castor XML and Castor JDO. The examples use Castor 0.9.2
            and offer good insight in using XML and JDO together.<br />
         <url>http://www.ebxmlsoft.com/pilots/samples.html</url>
         </p>
      </section>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
