<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/index.xml">
  <body>
    <title>The Castor Project</title>

    <header>

      <p>
         Castor is an open source data binding framework for Java[tm].
         It's basically the shortest path between Java objects, XML documents and SQL tables.
         Castor provides Java to XML binding, Java to SQL persistence, and then
         some more.
      </p>

      <p><b>News:</b>
        <br />
        <b>$RELEASE_DATE$</b> Version $VERSION$ is now <a href="download.xml">available for download</a>.
        <ul>
            <li><b>06 Jun 2003</b> - Can't find it here? Check out the
                <a href="http://www.brainopolis.com/castorwiki/Wiki.jsp?page=Main">CastorWiki</a>.
                An effort put together by a number of Castor users to document the undocumented!
                Hosted off site by Lance Lavandowska, and championed by Tek1 (whose real name is
                a mystery to us all!).
            </li>

            <li><b>12 Mar 2003</b> - We're pleased to announce that the folks at
               <a href="http://www.refactorit.com/index.html?id=649">RefactorIt</a>
               have included Castor as part of their Open Source Community License.
               This means anyone who works on the Castor code base can download a
               copy of RefactorIt and use it when working on the Castor code.
            </li>

            <li><b>14 Nov 2002</b> - <b>Congratulations</b>
               to Bruce Snyder and his family on the birth of their second daughter,
               the youngest member of the Castor team, we can't wait until she's old enough
               to start programming!
            </li>

            <li><b>24 Oct 2002</b> - Please welcome our newest addition to the Castor team of
                committers, Mickaël Guessant! Mickaël is a very welcome addition to the
                Castor JDO team.</li>

            <li><b>10 July 2002</b> - Bruce Snyder has taken over for Thomas Yip as the Castor JDO
                Project Lead. Bruce's name should be very familar to most Castor users as
                he has been an active contributor and committer to Castor JDO for more than
                a year.
                <br />
                A special Thanks to Thomas Yip for the great job he did and all the contributions
                he made to the project.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>

      <p><a href="origins.xml">About the origins of the name</a></p>

      <p><b>Note:</b> Presently we are hosting two mailing lists. Traffic is not too high,
         so if you are interested in keeping up to date with new releases, or have problems,
         questions or feedback please <a href="lists.xml">subscribe
         to the appropriate list</a>.</p>

    </header>

    <section title="Features">

      <p>Short feature list (we haven't got all day):
        <ul>
          <li>
             Castor XML: Java object model to and from XML
             <br/>&#160;&#160; - Generate source code from an XML Schema
             <br/>&#160;&#160; - Default introspector or mapping file for existing object models
          </li>
          <li>Castor JDO: Java object persistence to RDBMS
              <li>Castor JDO is not the same-as or compatible with Sun's JDO. We have
                  a different approach to handling data object to RDBMS mappings.
                  Please see the <a href="jdo-faq.html">JDO FAQ</a> for more information.
              </li>
          </li>
          <li>XML-based mapping file to specify bindings for existing object models</li>
          <li>Support for schema-less Java to XML binding</li>
          <li>In memory caching and write-at-commit reduces JDBC operations</li>
          <li>Two phase commit transactions, object rollback and deadlock detection</li>
          <li>OQL query mapping to SQL queries</li>
          <li>EJB container managed persistence provider for OpenEJB</li>
          <li>Ability to create base mapping from existing Java classes</li>
          <li>Ability to create an XML Schema from an XML input document</li>
        </ul>
        See the <a href="status.xml">status page</a> for more information.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="About the Castor Project">


      <p>The Castor project has been developed out of need: the need to get stuff done
         and the need to write useful code. It has been designed and coded over many cups
         of Dunkin Donut's Hazlenut coffee, Starbuck's Latte, and tall no-whip White Mochas,
         as proof that coffee beans do come in handy.</p>

      <p>For <a href="contributors.xml">a full list of contributors</a>.</p>

      <p>The Castor Project was started and originally developed by
         <a href="mailto:kvisco@intalio.com">Keith Visco</a> and
         <a href="mailto:arkin@intalio.com">Assaf Arkin</a> of Intalio, Inc.
         Contributors are welcome to join this project. Please join us on the
         <a href="lists.xml">mailing list</a>.</p>
       <p>
         Castor includes software, such as Xerces, Jakarta ORO, and Jakarta Regexp,
         developed by the <a href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a>.
         Castor also includes <a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit testing framework</a>.
       </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
