<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/index.xml">
  <body>
    <title>The Castor Project</title>

    <header>

      <p>
         Castor is an open source data binding framework for Java[tm].
         It's basically the shortest path between Java objects, XML documents and SQL tables.
         Castor provides Java to XML binding, Java to SQL persistence, and then
         some more.
      </p>

      <!-- include the latest news -->
      <include href="news.xml"/>

      <p><a href="origins.xml">About the origins of the name</a></p>

      <p><b>Note:</b> Presently we are hosting two mailing lists. Traffic is not too high,
         so if you are interested in keeping up to date with new releases, or have problems,
         questions or feedback please <a href="lists.xml">subscribe
         to the appropriate list</a>.</p>

    </header>

    <section title="Features">

      <p>Short feature list (we haven't got all day):
        <ul>
          <li>
             Castor XML: Java object model to and from XML
             <br/>&#160;&#160; - Generate source code from an XML Schema
             <br/>&#160;&#160; - Default introspector or mapping file for existing object models
          </li>
          <li>Castor JDO: Java object persistence to RDBMS
              <li>Castor JDO is not the same-as or compatible with Sun's JDO. We have
                  a different approach to handling data object to RDBMS mappings.
                  Please see the <a href="jdo-faq.html">JDO FAQ</a> for more information.
              </li>
          </li>
          <li>XML-based mapping file to specify bindings for existing object models</li>
          <li>Support for schema-less Java to XML binding</li>
          <li>In memory caching and write-at-commit reduces JDBC operations</li>
          <li>Two phase commit transactions, object rollback and deadlock detection</li>
          <li>OQL query mapping to SQL queries</li>
          <li>EJB container managed persistence provider for OpenEJB</li>
          <li>Ability to create base mapping from existing Java classes</li>
          <li>Ability to create an XML Schema from an XML input document</li>
        </ul>
        See the <a href="status.xml">status page</a> for more information.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="About the Castor Project">


      <p>The Castor project has been developed out of need: the need to get stuff done
         and the need to write useful code. It has been designed and coded over many cups
         of Dunkin Donut's Hazlenut coffee, Starbuck's Latte, and tall no-whip White Mochas,
         as proof that coffee beans do come in handy.</p>

      <p>For <a href="contributors.xml">a full list of contributors</a>.</p>

      <p>The Castor Project was started and originally developed by
         <a href="mailto:kvisco@intalio.com">Keith Visco</a> and
         <a href="mailto:arkin@intalio.com">Assaf Arkin</a> of Intalio, Inc.
         Contributors are welcome to join this project. Please join us on the
         <a href="lists.xml">mailing list</a>.</p>
       <p>
         Castor includes software, such as Xerces, Jakarta ORO, and Jakarta Regexp,
         developed by the <a href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a>.
         Castor also includes <a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit testing framework</a>.
       </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
