<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/jdo-project.xml">
  <properties>
    <title>Castor JDO Project Plan</title>
    <author email="ferret@frii.com">Bruce Snyder</author>
    <abstract>
    This document outlines all work that has been identified for Castor JDO. 
    </abstract>
    <status>Draft</status>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <title>Castor JDO Refactoring Project Plan</title>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <p>
      Below is a list of tasks that have been identified for refactoring
      in Castor JDO. This list is continually evolving and should be checked
      often. There are no scheduled release dates for these items. This
      is because Castor JDO is entirely a volunteer effort and team members
      contribute in their spare time. Some of these tasks are in progress 
      and some have not been started at all.
      </p>

      <p>
      There is always plenty of work to be done. If you would like to 
      participate, please let us know. If you see a task that you would 
      like to work on please let us know. I you see a task that you would 
      like to work on but has already been assigned to someone, that doesn't 
      mean that you can't help out or even take it over. Simply contact the 
      JDO project leader (available <a href="http://www.castor.org/contributors.html">
      here</a>). 
      </p>

    </section>

    <section title="Tasks">

        <section title="Modularization of Castor JDO">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Castor is very tightly coupled in it's design. This tight coupling
        leads to maintainence trouble, difficult to understand code, etc. 
        </p>
        <p>
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        See the mail list threads titled 
        <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/castor-dev@exolab.org/msg06709.html">Castor JDO Status</a> and
        <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/castor-dev@exolab.org/msg06935.html">Strategy Proposal</a>. 
        These threads are especially long and tend to be broken on
        mail-archive.com. But there are some very good ideas amongst these two
        threads concerning the modularization of Castor JDO.
        <br />
        <br />
        This is a high-level architectural change that includes many of the
        items in this list. 
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Logging Refactoring">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Switching the logging mechanism in Castor 
        over to using the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/logging.html">
        Jakarta Commons Logging</a> with Log4J as the default logger. 
        Not only will this help to improve the logging quality, but it will
        also allow users to choose their logging framework of choice. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b> Bruce Snyder<br />
        <b>Status:</b> completed<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b> 5 May 2003<br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        Not sure if Jakarta Commons Logging should be used in Castor
        because of the inability to configure some finer features in Log4J.
        See <a
        href="http://www.zdnet.com.au/builder/program/java/story/0,2000034779,20272367,00.htm">this
        article</a> for some info. This article may be talking about
        programmatic configuration of Log4J which I'm not really worried
        about. All of the configuration in Castor will take place in a
        properties or XML file. <br />
        <b>Post Mortem:</b><br />
        Jakarta Commons Logging was used with Log4J as the default logger. Now
        the amount of logging just needs to be increase and configurations
        offered in the default properties files for ease of disabling stuff
        that's spewing. I'll be adding a class to support the TRACE level as
        well.<br />
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="CTF-JDO Improvements">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Writing test cases is a critical effort to the 
        evolution of Castor JDO. All bug fixes and new functionality must contain 
        test cases unless the bug fix is trivial. All test cases are written
        using the Castor Test Framework for JDO 
        (<a href="testing-framework.html">CTF-JDO</a>). 
        </p>
        <p>
        The verison of <a href="http://junit.org">JUnit</a> used by Castor is
        quite outdated (version 3.5). This needs to be updated to the latest
        version (as of this writing, version 3.8.1). There is a certain amount
        of work involved with this in changing all assert() calls to the
        newer, more specific assert calls (e.g. assertTrue(), assertEquals(),
        assertNull(), assertNotNull(), etc.). Also look into the use of 
        <a href="http://www.openfuture.de/Log4Unit/">Log4Unit</a> as opposed
        to JUnit. Log4Unit is an extension to JUnit that provides a logging
        component to JUnit to provide better logging for both failures and
        successes. 
        </p>
        <p>
        In addition to using JUnit, a database specific extension to JUnit
        called <a href="http://dbunit.sf.net/">DbUnit</a> should be
        considered. DbUnit helps to manage test data sets by
        importing/exporting flat XML data sets to/from a database for each
        test or set of tests being executed. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b> Bruce Snyder<br />
        <b>Status:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Refactor for Correct Use of JDBC Tx Isolation Levels">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Currently Castor JDO does not make any use of JDBC tx isolation levels
        and this needs to be corrected. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b> <br />
        <b>Status:</b> <br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        This impacts Connection duration and needs to be investigated further.
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Query Engine Refactoring">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        The Castor OQL engine should be refactored to make us of a parser
        generator like <a href="http://antlr.org">ANTLR</a> or <a
        href="http://www.experimentalstuff.com/Technologies/JavaCC/">JavaCC</a>. 
        This will make maintenance and adding features incredibly easier. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b> Paul Botta<br />
        <b>Status:</b> ANTLR implemenation complete<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        Many thanks to Paul Botta for his hard work on the ANTLR implemenation. 
        Now this implementation just needs some tests to prove it so that it can 
        be committted it to CVS. 
        </p>
        <p>
        This layer should also be made pluggable allowing one or more query 
        engines to plugged in simultaneously (e.g. OQL, XQuery, EJBQL, etc.).
        The <tt>tests.jdo.OqlTests</tt> class needs to be completed before
        this work can take place. This will provide a baseline before the
        removal of the current OQL engine. 
        </p>

        <p>
        Tranql may be used to achieve this task. As a side affect, Tranql may
        be also do a couple other jobs as well (e.g. caching and transaction
        context). There will also be a programmtic query API for this.
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Refactor the SQLTypeConvertors">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        The SQLTypeConvertors inner class of SQLTypes should be refactored to 
        make it easier to plug in additional convertors. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Query Externalization">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Castor should include a mechanism for queries to be externalized in the 
        object mapping descriptor. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        This would allow for named queries that do not require recompilation 
        for changes. These queries would be included automatically via the 
        Castor XML unmarshalling of the object mapping descriptor via the 
        &lt;includes> element.
        </p>
        <p>
        This may not be able to be accomplished at all with new programmtic
        query API.
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="ClassMolder Refactoring">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        The ClassMolder should be broken up into several classes to make use 
        of a dual <a
        href="http://www.ootips.org/strategy-vs-case.html">strategy pattern</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        The relationship type (e.g. one-to-one, one-to-many, many-to-many) is 
        the first strategy layer. The implementation type (e.g. interface,
        abstract, concrete) is the second strategy layer.
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="J2EE Transaction Factory">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        In 2002 I started adding an API for a TransactionManagerFactory so that 
        Castor JDO can make use of a J2EE container's transaction manager 
        (e.g. JBoss, Weblogic, Websphere, etc.).
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b> Werner Guttmann/Bruce Snyder<br />
        <b>Status:</b> completed<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b> Apr 2004<br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Possible TransactionContext Replacement">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Investigate whether the TransactionContext class can be replaced
        through the use of ThreadLocal. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b> Bruce Snyder<br />
        <b>Status:</b> completed<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b> Apr 2004<br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Cache Engine Refactoring">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Castor's current cache implemenation is not very robust. It lacks any
        procedure for manual object eviction and it should really be using
        some sort of balanced tree (e.g. java.util.TreeMap) for reasons of
        speed, etc., etc.
        </p>
        <p>
        Note that Vince Adamo has posted a 
        <a href="http://bugzilla.exolab.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1091">patch</a> for 
        object eviction in the current Castor API. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> open<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        There should really be a cache API. This would abstract the entire cache 
        engine allowing it to be made pluggable. In fact, I would much rather 
        consider using a <a href="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=107">JSR 107</a>
        implementation than writing our own API. Because this layer will be
        pluggable, a distributed cache implementation should be provided using
        <a href="http://www.javagroups.com/">JavaGroups</a>.
        <br />
        <br />
        Also, the dirty checking needs to be refactored so it's cleaner and
        more straightforward in its duties. 
        </p>

        <p>
        Tranql may be used to achieve this task. 
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Polymorphism">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Handling of interfaces and abstract classes with regard to both object 
        mapping and queries. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        Maybe this could be handled for the object mapping by using nested 
        &lt;class> elements??? 
        <br />
        <i>Interface idea</i> - introduce the 'implements' attribute to the
        &lt;class> element: 
        <pre><![CDATA[
<class name="myapp.Foo" ... >
    <class name="myapp.FooBar" implements="myapp.Foo" ...>
    </class>
</class>]]>
        </pre>
        Obviously an interface can be determined by using <tt>java.lang.Class#isInterfaces()</tt> and/or
        <tt>java.lang.Class#isInterface()</tt>. 
        <br />
        <br />
        <i>Abstract class idea</i> - make use of the 'extends' element plus
        some code testing: 
        <pre><![CDATA[
<class name="myapp.Foo" ... >
    <class name="myapp.FooBar" extends="myapp.Foo" ...>
    </class>
</class>]]>
        </pre>
        The use of the 'extends' attribute for the abstract class is not
        unique enough to determine that the class is abstract or concrete.
        But by using <tt>java.lang.Class#isAssignableFrom()</tt> and/or 
        <tt>java.lang.Class#getSuperclass()</tt> will work. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <i>Queries</i> - objects should already be cast properly:
        <pre><![CDATA[
SELECT p FROM myapp.Product p]]>
        </pre>
        The above query would return all <tt>Product</tt>s including
        <tt>Computer</tt>s, etc.
        </p>
        <p>
        Another item that will need to be added is a mapping for interfaces
        and abstract classes. The &lt;class> element could certainly be used
        for this possibly by introducing another attribute to the &lt;class> 
        element. I'm thinking about an attribute named 'abstract' that 
        is simply a boolean whose default is false so that it won't affect 
        concrete classes. Then it serves as a marker for interfaces and 
        abstract classes only. 
        </p>
        <p>
        Not sure if this will really work. It will need experimentation to 
        determine.
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Integrated Connection Pooling">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        A database connection pooler should be integrated directly into
        Castor. This would limit us to supporting <a href="">JDBC 3.0</a>
        compliant drivers. Anything that's not JDBC 3.0 compliant would 
        still be supported via an implemention within the driver for a 
        pooled DataSource.
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        Here is a list of database connection poolers:
        <ul type="bullet">
            <li>
                <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/dbcp/">DBCP</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a
                href="http://download-west.oracle.com/docs/cd/A91202_01/901_doc/java.901/a90211/connpoca.htm#1057365">
                Oracle JDBC driver</a> (Unable to locate 9.2.x docs)
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="http://poolman.sf.net/">PoolMan</a> 
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="http://jdbc.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL JDBC driver</a> 
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="http://proxool.sf.net/">Proxool</a> 
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="http://sqlrelay.sourceforge.net/">SQL Relay</a>
            </li>
        </ul>
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="JCA Research">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Research the possibility of creating a JCA Connector for Castor to
        hook into application servers that support JCA. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b><br />
        <b>Date Started:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Logos">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        This task covers two topics: 
        <ul type="1">
            <li>Logos for Castor users to display on their websites</li>
            <li>Logos of projects that Castor uses or with which Castor integrates</li>
        </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b><br />
        <b>Date Started:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        This is to increase awareness of Castor's use as well as Castor's
        awareness of other projects. 
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Timestampable Dynamic Proxy">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        Remove the requirement of all objects to explicitly implement the
        Timestampable interface.
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b><br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        Currently Castor requires all objects involved in a long transaction
        to implement the <a
        href="http://www.castor.org/javadoc/org/exolab/castor/jdo/TimeStampable.html">Timestampable</a>
        interface. This requirement can easily be removed via a dymanic proxy
        implementation. 
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Must Fix Bugs">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        There are a few bugs that *must* be fixed, specifically 
        <a href="http://bugzilla.exolab.org/show_bug.cgi?id=986">986</a>, 
        <a href="http://bugzilla.exolab.org/show_bug.cgi?id=925">925</a>, 
        These bugs have been around for quite a while and should have been 
        fixed long ago. 
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> not started<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        </p>
        </section>

        <section title="Javadoc improvements">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        This task surrounds the effort to continually improve the code
        documentation including code examples, adding an <tt>@author</tt> tag 
        to any class you modify, etc. This task must be carried 
        out by everyone.
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b> ongoing<br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        </p>
        </section>

        <!--
        Items to be added to this list (in no particular order):

        - Queries should check the cache before going to the database
        - Query by example would be a good thing to consider (e.g. 
          http://www.mail-archive.com/castor-dev%40exolab.org/msg06972.html )
        - Loading/reloading of mapping descriptor should be simplified
        - Support for sub-queries, joins, order by, group by, between, functions, 
          is null, is not null (these two are already supported), named parameters, 
          binary, logical and match operators, precedence via parens, etc. 
        - Make it easier to use straight SQL (e.g. no AS <object-name> syntax
          for certain cases)
        - Support for the mapping of multiple classes to one table and one 
          class to multiple tables
        - Support the splitting of object mapping (this is highly dependent 
          upon Castor XML)
        - Best practices/patterns document
        - Persistence of primitives and primitive wrappers
        - Make it really easy to implement type convertors (e.g. Oracle JDBC
          types, etc.)
        - Cascading deletes of an object graph via the object mapping descriptor
        - Lazy loading via either byte code manipulation or dynamic proxies
        - Sorted Collections
        - Support a choice of outer joins or ???
        - Updated JBoss JMX MBean 
        - Log4J CastorAppender
        - Updated XDoclet exolab plug-in
        - Better examples (e.g. servlet, EJB, client/server, etc.)
        - xPetstore Castor implementation
        - Castor tutorial document
        - More engine support (e.g. native XML databases, SAP DB, FirstSQL, 
          McKoi SQL, Pointbase, Pervasive, etc.)
        -->

        <!--
        <section title="">
        <p>
        <b>Description:</b><br />
        </p>
        <p>
        <b>Volunteer:</b><br />
        <b>Status:</b><br />
        <b>Date Started:</b><br />
        <b>Notes:</b><br />
        </p>
        </section>
        -->

    </section>

  </body>
</document>
