<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/oql.xml">
    <body>
        <title>OQL to SQL translator</title>
        <header>
            <p>
                Reference: <api package="org.exolab.castor.jdo.oql">The Java OQL to SQL translator</api></p>
        </header>

        <section title="Status">
            <p>
                This documentation is not yet finished</p>
        </section>

        <section title="Introduction">
            <p>
                This document describes an OQL to SQL translator to be added to the
                Castor JDO Java object persistence API. The translator will accept OQL
                queries passed as strings, and generate a parse tree of the OQL. It will
                then traverse the tree creating the appropriate SQL. The user will then
                be able to bind parameters to parameterized queries. Type checking will
                be performed on the bound parameters. When the user executes the query,
                the system will submit the query to the SQL database, and then
                postprocess the SQL resultset to create the appropriate result as a Java
                Object or literal. The current
                <api package="org.exolab.castor.mapping">mapping</api> and
                <api package="org.exolab.castor.persist">persistence</api>
                packages will be used for metadata and RDBMS communication.</p>
            <p>
                Four of the SourceXchange milestones for this project call for java
                source code. These milestones will be refered to here as phase 1, 2, 3,
                and 4. There are many possible OQL features that can be supported, but
                weren't discussed in the proposal or RFP. Many of these are probably
                unwanted. These additional features are specified as phase 5, which is
                out of the scope of this SourceXChange project.</p>
        </section>

        <section title="Overview">
            <p>
                The parser will construct a parse tree as output from an OQL query
                string given as input. The OQL syntax is a subset of the syntax
                described in the ODMG 3.0 specification section 4.12, with some
                additional constructs. Following is a description of the supported OQL
                syntax, and its SQL equivalent.</p>


            <p>
                Certain features of OQL may not be directly translatable to SQL, but
                may still be supported, by post processing the query. For example, the
                <b>first()</b> and <b>last()</b> collection functions supported in OQL
                are not directly translatable to standard SQL, but a resultset can be
                post-processed to return the appropriate values. Features requiring
                post-processing of SQL resultsets will be documented as such
                below.</p>

            <p>
                Currently the OQLQuery checks for corect syntax at the same time as
                it does type checking and other types of error checking. The new code
                will involve a multiple pass strategy, with the following passes:
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        Parse the String query checking for syntax errors, and return
                        a parse tree.</li>

                    <li>
                        Traverse the parse tree checking for correct types, valid member
                        and method identifiers, and use of features which are unsupported.
                        This pass may also generate some data necessary for creating the SQL.</li>

                    <li>
                        Traverse the tree one final time, creating the equivalent SQL
                        statement to the OQL Query originally passed</li></ol></p>
        </section>
        <section title="Syntax">
            <p>
                This section describes the first pass which will be done by the
                parser. The parser will create a StringTokenizer like this:
                <code>
StringTokenizer tokenizer
    = new StringTokenizer(oql,
    "\n\r\t,.()[]+-*/&lt;&gt;=:|$", true);</code>
                This will create a tokenizer with the delimiter
                characters listed in the second argument, and it will return delimeters
                as well as tokens. The parser will also create a Vector to be used as a
                token buffer. As tokens are returned from the tokenizer they will be
                added to the vector. Older tokens will be removed from the vector when
                it reaches a certain size. The vector will also be modified when the
                tokenizer returns multi character operators as seperate tokens, for
                example the -&gt; method invocation operator.</p>

            <p>
                The parser will consume tokens from the StringTokenizer, generating a
                ParseTree. Each ParseTree node will have a nodeType coresponding to its
                symbol in the OQL syntax. After each node is created it will look to the
                next token, and act acordingly, either modifying its properties (i.e.
                for DISTINCT property of selectExpr), creating a new child node, or
                returning an error. If the error travels up to the root node of the
                tree, there is a syntax error in the OQL submitted. At the end of this
                pass, the tree will contain an apropriate representation of the query,
                which will be analyzed, and used to create SQL. Below is the modified
                EBNF which will be the castor OQL syntax.</p>

            <p>
                <code>
query                   ::= selectExpr
                            | expr

selectExpr              ::= <B>select</B> [<B>distinct</B>] 
                            projectionAttributes
                            fromClause
                            [whereClause]
                            [groupClause]
                            [orderClause]

projectionAttributes    ::= projectionList
                          | *

projectionList          ::= projection {, projection }

projection              ::= field
                          | expr [<B>as</B> identifier]

fromClause              ::= <B>from</B> iteratorDef {, iteratorDef}

iteratorDef             ::= identifier [ [<B>as</B> ] identifier ]
                          | identifier <B>in</B> identifier

whereClause             ::= <B>where</B> expr

groupClause             ::= <B>group by</B> fieldList {havingClause}

havingClause            ::= <B>having</B> expr

orderClause             ::= <B>order by</B> sortCriteria

sortCriteria            ::= sortCriterion {, sortCriterion }

sortCriterion           ::= expr [ (<B>asc</B> | <B>desc</B>) ]

expr                    ::= castExpr

castExpr                ::= orExpr
                            | <B>(</B> type <B>)</B> castExpr

orExpr                  ::= andExpr {<B>or</B> andExpr}

andExpr                 ::= quantifierExpr {<B>and</B> quantifierExpr}

quantifierExpr          ::= equalityExpr
                            | <B>for all</B> inClause <B>:</B> equalityExpr
                            | <B>exists</B> inClause <B>:</B> equalityExpr

inClause                ::= identifier <B>in</B> expr

equalityExpr            ::= relationalExpr
                            {(<B>=</B> | <B>!=</B>) 
                                [compositePredicate] relationalexpr }
                            | relationalExpr {<B>like</B> relationalExpr}

relationalExpr          ::= additiveExpr
                            {(<B>&lt;</B> | <B>&lt;=</B> 
                                | <B>&gt;</B> | <B>&gt;=</B> ) 
                                    [ compositePredicate ] additiveExpr }
                                | additiveExpr <B>between</B> 
                                    additiveExpr <B>and</B> additiveExpr

compositePredicate      ::= <B>some</B> | <B>any</B> | <B>all</B>

additiveExpr            ::= multiplicativeExpr
                                {<B>+</B> multiplicativeExpr}
                            | multiplicativeExpr
                                {<B>-</B> multiplicativeExpr}
                            | multiplicativeExpr
                                {<B>union</B> multiplicativeExpr}
                            | multiplicativeExpr
                                {<B>except</B> multiplicativeExpr}
                            | multiplicativeExpr
                                {<B>||</B> multiplicativeExpr}

multiplicativeExpr      ::= inExpr {<B>*</B> inExpr}
                            | inExpr {<B>/</B> inExpr}
                            | inExpr {<B>mod</B> inExpr}
                            | inExpr {<B>intersect</B> inExpr}

inExpr                  ::= unaryExpr {<B>in</B> unaryExpr}

unaryExpr               ::= <B>+</B> unaryExpr
                            | <B>-</B> unaryExpr
                            | <B>abs</B> unaryExpr
                            | <B>not</B> unaryExpr
                            | postfixExpr

postfixExpr             ::= primaryExpr{<B>[</B> index <B>]</B>}
                            | primaryExpr
                            {(<B>.</B> | <B>-&gt;</B>)identifier[arglist]}

index                   ::= expr {<B>,</B> expr}
                            | expr <B>:</B> expr

argList                 ::= <B>(</B>[ valueList ]<B>)</B>

primaryExpr             ::= conversionExpr
                            | collectionExpr
                            | aggregateExpr
                            | undefinedExpr
                            | collectionConstruction
                            | identifier[ arglist ]
                            | queryParam
                            | literal
                            | <B>(</B> query <B>)</B>

conversionExpr          ::= <B>listtoset(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>element(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>distinct(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>flatten(</B> query <B>)</B>

collectionExpr          ::= <B>first(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>last(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>unique(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>exists(</B> query <B>)</B>

aggregateExpr           ::= <B>sum(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>min(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>max(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>avg(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>count(</B>( query | * )<B>)</B>

undefinedExpr           ::= <B>is_undefined(</B> query <B>)</B>
                            | <B>is_defined(</B> query <B>)</B>

fieldList               ::= field {, field}

field                   ::= identifier<B>:</B> expr

collectionConstruction  ::= <B>array(</B>[valueList]<B>)</B>
                            | <B>set(</B>[valueList]<B>)</B>
                            | <B>bag(</B>[valueList]<B>)</B>
                            | <B>list(</B>[valueList]<B>)</B>
                            | <B>list(</B>listRange<B>)</B>

valueList               ::= expr {, expr}

listRange               ::= expr..expr

queryParam              ::= <B>$</B>[(type)]longLiteral

type                    ::= [<B>unsigned</B>] <B>short</B>
                            | [<B>unsigned</B>] <B>long</B>
                            | <B>long long</B>
                            | <B>float</B>
                            | <B>double</B>
                            | <B>char</B>
                            | <B>string</B>
                            | <B>boolean</B>
                            | <B>octet</B>
                            | <B>enum</B> [identifier.]identifier
                            | <B>date</B>
                            | <B>time</B>
                            | <B>interval</B>
                            | <B>timestamp</B>
                            | <B>set &lt;</B>type<B>&gt;</B>
                            | <B>bag &lt;</B>type<B>&gt;</B>
                            | <B>list &lt;</B>type<B>&gt;</B>
                            | <B>array &lt;</B>type<B>&gt;</B>
                            | <B>dictionary &lt;</B>type, type<B>&gt;</B>
                            | <B>identifier</B>

identifier              ::= letter{letter| digit| _}

literal                 ::= booleanLiteral
                            | longLiteral
                            | doubleLiteral
                            | charLiteral
                            | stringLiteral
                            | dateLiteral
                            | timeLiteral
                            | timestampLiteral
                            | <B>nil</B>
                            | <B>undefined</B>

booleanLiteral          ::= <B>true</B>
                            | <B>false</B>

longLiteral             ::= digit{digit}

doubleLiteral           ::= digit{digit}.digit{digit}
                            [(<B>E</B> | <B>e</B>)[<B>+</B>|<B>-</B>]digit{digit}]

charLiteral             ::= 'character'

stringLiteral           ::= "{character}"

dateLiteral             ::= <B>date</B>
                                'longliteral-longliteral-longliteral'

timeLiteral             ::= <B>time</B>
                                'longliteral:longLiteral:floatLiteral'

timestampLiteral        ::= <B>timestamp</B>
                                'longLiteral-longLiteral-longLiteral
                                longliteral:longLiteral:floatLiteral'

character               ::= letter
                            | digit
                            | special-character

letter                  ::= <B>A</B>|<B>B</B>|...|<B>Z</B>|
                            <B>a</B>|<B>b</B>|...|<B>z</B>

digit                   ::= <B>0</B>|<B>1</B>|...|<B>9</B>

special-character       ::= <B>?</B>|<B>_</B>|<B>*</B>|<B>%</B>|<B>\</B>
                </code></p>

        <p>
            The following symbols were removed from the standard OQL Syntax for
            the following reasons:

            <ul>
                <li>
                    <B>andthen</B>: Cannot be implemented in
                    a single SQL query. </li>

                <li>
                    <B>orelse</B>: Same as above. </li>

                <li>
                    <B>import</B>: This is advanced
                    functionality which may be added later. This phase will use the
                    castor mapping mechanism to define the namespace. </li>

                <li>
                    Defined Queries: This is another feature
                    which can be added later. It is unclear where the queries would be
                    stored, and what their scope would be seeing as how this project
                    is an OQL to SQL translator, and not an ODBMS. </li>

                <li>
                    iteratorDef was changed so that all
                    instances of expr were replaced by identifier. This means that the
                    from clause can only contain extent names (class names), rather
                    than any expression. This is the most common case and others could
                    create complicated SQL sub-queries or post-processing
                    requirements. </li>
                <li>

                    objectConstruction and
                    structConstruction were removed. What is the scope of the
                    constructed object or struct, and how is a struct defined in Java? </li>
                    </ul></p>

        <p>
            The following symbols were added or modified.
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <B>between</B> added to relationalExpr. </li>

                <li>
                    Optional type specification added to
                    queryParam. </li></ul></p>
        <p>
            The rest of the standard OQL
            syntax remains unchanged. Certain syntactically correct queries may not
            be supported in Castor. For example, top level expressions which do not
            contain a selectExpr anywhere in the query may not be supported. This
            will be discussed further in the next section.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Type and validity checking">
        <p>
            The first pass over the tree will do type checking, and create some
            structures used in the SQL generation pass. It will also check whether
            the identifiers used are valid, and whether the query uses unsupported
            features. The following table describes the each type of tree node, and
            how it will be processed in the first pass.</p>

        <p>
            <TABLE cellpadding="4" border="1">
              <TBODY>
              <TR>
                <TD>expr</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul><li>
                            A query whose top level element is an expr, rather than a
                            selectExpr will not be supported within the scope of this project.
                            These queries can either be stated as a selectExpr, like
                            aggregateExpr's, or they would require post-processing of the SQL
                            results, like <B>element()</B><B>first()</B> and <B>last()</B>.</li></ul></TD>
                <TD>Phase 5</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>projectionAttributes</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul><li>
                            select * will return a Collection of Arrays of Objects.</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 5</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>projectionList</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Selecting multiple fields will
                            return a Collection of Arrays of Objects.</li>

                        <li>
                            When there are multiple fields
                            selected, a list of field names and aliases will be kept for
                            checking validity of expr's in the whereClause, groupClause,
                            and orderClause.</li>
                    </ul></TD>
                <TD>Phase 5</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>projection</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Alias identifier will be stored.</li>

                        <li>
                            expr in projection may only be identifier, without an arglist.</li>
                    </ul></TD>
                <TD>Phase 1</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>projection</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            expr in projection may only be
                            identifier (with optional argList), aggregateExpr,
                            undefinedExpr, and postfixExpr (for selecting fields and
                            accessors).</li>

                        <li>
                            The subquery in aggregateExpr and
                            undefinedExpr can be identifier (with optional arglist), or
                            postfixExpr for applying these functions to fields and
                            accessors.</li>

                        <li>
                            If an identifier before the
                            <B>.</B> or <B>-&gt;</B> contains an arglist, it will be
                            considered a SQL function, and passed through to the
                            RDBMS.</li>
                        <li>
                            If the postfixExpr contains one of
                            the above operators, the mapping mechanism will be used to
                            determine if the path expression is valid and to generate a
                            list of required join tables, using the manyKey and
                            manyTable from the JDOFieldDescriptor.</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 2</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>fromClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul><li>
                            The class of the extent being selected from will be stored,
                            and ClassDescriptor objects will be instantiated.</li></ul></TD>
                <TD>Phase 1</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>whereClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            expr in whereClause may only
                            contain orExpr, andExpr, equalityExpr (without
                            compositePredicate), relationalExpr, additiveExpr (without
                            set operators <B>union</B> and <B>except</B>),
                            multiplicativeExpr (without set operator <B>intersect</B>),
                            unaryExpr, postFixExpr (must be only primaryExpr, no array
                            or property reference or method calls).</li>

                        <li>
                            primaryExpr may only contain
                            identifier (without an argList), literal and queryParam.
                            Identifier will be checked against object name and alias in
                            projectionList.</li>

                        <li>
                            For equalityExpr, relationalExpr,
                            aditiveExpr, multiplicativeExpr, the left side and right
                            side expr's must evaluate to comparable types.</li>

                        <li>
                            For unaryExpr, simple type
                            checking for numerical or character based types will be
                            performed.</li>

                        <li>

                            If the operands for any of the
                            relational, equality, additive, multiplicative, or unary
                            operators is a query parameter, an expected type will be
                            determined. If the parameter included a specified type which
                            is incompatible with the system determined type, an error
                            will be generated.</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 1</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>whereClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Support for built in OQL functions
                            will be added to the whereClause: is_defined,
                            is_undefined.</li>

                        <li>
                            inExpr will be supported in whereClause.</li>

                        <li>
                            inExpr will only allow collectionConstruction for
                            the right side argument to <B>in</B>. No subQueries
                            will be allowed.</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 2</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>whereClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            identifiers will be able to
                            contain an optional arglist. If the arglist is before a
                            <B>.</B> or <B>-&gt;</B> the identifier will be considered a
                            SQL function and will be passed through to the DBMS.
                            Otherwise, the identifier will be for an accessor method, or
                            a property name.</li>
                        <li>
                            Accessor methods and property
                            references will cause a check through the ClassDescriptor
                            and FieldDescriptors for the object type, and the required
                            join tables.</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 3</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>whereClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            compositePredicate will be
                            suported in equalityExpr.</li>
                        <li>
                            exists(query) will be supported.</li>

                        <li>
                            quantifierExpr will support <B>for
                            all</B> and <B>exists</B>.</li>

                        <li>
                            Subqueries will be supported on the right side of
                            the <B>in</B> operator</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 4</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>groupClause, havingClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Will identify appropriate fields
                            in SQL schema for each expr.</li>

                        <li>
                            aggregateExpr will be supported.</li>

                        <li>
                            Only expr's which translate to SQL
                            columns whcih are already being selected will be
                            supported.</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 4</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>orderClause</TD>
                <TD>
                        <ul><li>
                            May only contain expr's which translate into SQL columns which
                            are already being selected.</li></ul></TD>
                <TD>Phase 3</TD></TR></TBODY></TABLE></p>
    </section>

    <section title="SQL Generation">
        <p>
            After the first pass, the parse tree is free of errors, and ready for
            the SQL generation step. The existing implementation of the OQLParser
            uses the persistence API for SQL generation. This API lacks the
            necessary features to generate SQL from any OQL. The SQLEngine class
            which implements Persistence is used to create a JDBCQueryExpression.
            The SQL is derived from the finder, which is a JDBCQueryExpression
            produced by the SQLEngine. The problem is that the SQLEngine only
            supports single objects. It cannot generate SQL for path expressions
            like this:
            <code>
select p.address from Person p </code>

            This query requires a SQL statement like this:
            <code>
select address.* from person, address
    where person.address_id = address.address_id</code></p>

        <p>
            The buildFinder method should not be used to generate a
            queryExpression. The SQLEngine should be used to get a ClassDescriptor,
            and to create a new QueryExpression. The OQLParser should use the
            methods in the QueryExpression to generate the SQL. The
            JDBCQueryExpression which is an implementation of QueryExpression is
            also lacking in necessary features. This class should continue to be
            used, but the following features will need to be added:
            <DL>
              <DT>addColumn(String)</DT>
              <DD>For adding something to select without specifying the tablename,
              for use with functions (i.e. select count(*))</DD>
              <DT>addTable(String)</DT>
              <DD>For when the table has to be added manually.</DD>
              <DT>addCondition(String)</DT>
              <DD>Add a condition created outside the class, for nested expressions,
              and other expressions that are not of the form table.column op
              table.column.</DD>
              <DT>setDistinct(boolean)</DT>
              <DD>Used for select distinct.</DD>
              <DT>addOrderColumn(String tableName, String columnName, boolean desc)</DT>
              <DD>Used for order by</DD>
              <DT>addGroupExpr(String)</DT>
              <DD>Used for group by</DD>
              <DT>addHavingExpr(String)</DT>
              <DD>Used for having.</DD></DL></p>

        <p>
            The following table lists each type of
            tree node, and how it will be processed in the SQL generation pass.</p>

        <p>
            <TABLE cellpadding="4" border="1">
              <TBODY>
              <TR>
                <TD>selectExpr</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul><li>
                        distinct in the selectExpr will result in a call to
                        setDistinct(true) in the queryExpr.</li></ul></TD>
                <TD>Phase 2</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>projection</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul><li>
                        The queryExpr will be populated with the columns and tables
                        necessary to retrieve the object. This will use code similar to
                        SQLEngine.addLoadSql(...). </li></ul></TD>
                <TD>Phase 1</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>projection</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            aggregateExpr and SQL functions
                            will be passed to addColumn.</li>

                        <li>
                            undefinedExpr will be translated
                            to <B>is null</B> and <B>is not null</B></li>

                        <li>
                            postfixExpr (for selecting fields
                            and accessors) will result in a different group of select
                            expressions and "from tables" being
                            generated.</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 2</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>whereClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            Entire expr in where clause will be translated, and then added
                            to the QueryExpr, using a single call to addCondition(String), and
                            multiple calls to addTable(String).</li></ul></TD>
                <TD>Phase 1</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>whereClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <B>is_defined()</B> will translate
                            into <B>is not null</B> and <B>is_undefined()</B> will
                            translate into <B>is null</B>.</li>

                        <li>
                            inExpr will translate directly,
                            with the collectionConstruction
                            removed.</li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 2</TD></TR>
              <TR>
                <TD>whereClause</TD>
                <TD>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            compositePredicate and
                            exists(query) translate directly to SQL.</li>
                        <li>
                            For quantifierExpr, <B>exists</B>
                            will translate into an exists() SQL subquery. <B>for all</B>
                            will translate into the contrapositive(?) exists query, for
                            example:

                            <code>
for all x in teachers:
    x.name = 'Nis'</code>
                            translates to:
                            <code>
not exists (select * from teachers
    where name != 'Nis')</code>
                            </li></ul></TD>

                <TD>Phase 4</TD></TR></TBODY></TABLE></p>
    </section>

    <section title="Summary">
        <p>
            The parser and parse tree classes will be improved through the phases
            of this project. The top level of OQL to SQL translation will look very
            simple, like this:
            <code>
OQLParser parser = new OQLParser(query);
ParseTree pt = parser.getParseTree();
pt.checkPass();
<comment>//the SQL generation pass</comment>
_expr = pt.getQueryExpr();
            </code>

            These methods will have some additional parameters passed
            for storing and retrieving data relevant to the query. Following is a
            table containing a list of what will be introduced in each coding phase
            of the project.</p>

        <p>
                <TABLE cellpadding="4" border="1">
                  <TBODY>
                  <TR>
                    <TD>Phase 1</TD>
                    <TD>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                New parser structure which
                                generates symbol tree</li>

                            <li>
                                Parser still supports only limited OQL</li>

                            <li>
                                selected field aliases</li>

                            <li>
                                whereClause supports or, and,
                                equality, additive, multiplicative, and unary
                                Operators.</li>

                            <li>
                                support for specifying parameter types</li>

                            <li>
                                check specified parameter type
                                against system determined type</li>

                            <li>
                                specifying ordered parameters.</li>

                            <li>
                                JDBCQueryExpression must support
                                addCondition(String condition)</li></ul></TD></TR>

                  <TR>
                    <TD>Phase 2</TD>
                    <TD>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                Distinct keyword will be supported
                                in selectExpr</li>

                            <li>
                                aggregateExpr and undefinedExpr
                                supported in projection (Select statement)</li>

                            <li>
                                isDefined, isUndefined in whereClause</li>

                            <li>
                                inExpr in whereClause</li>

                            <li>
                                type checking/conversion in bind()</li>

                            <li>
                                fields and accessors in the
                                projection. Mapping mechanism may need some additional
                                features.</li>

                            <li>
                                SQL functions in the projection</li>

                            <li>
                                order by</li></ul></TD></TR>
                  <TR>
                    <TD>Phase 3</TD>
                    <TD>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                fields and accessors in whereClause</li>

                            <li>
                                SQL functions in the where clause</li></ul></TD></TR>

                  <TR>
                    <TD>Phase 4</TD>
                    <TD>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                sub queries</li>

                            <li>
                                exists()</li>

                            <li>
                                compositePredicate</li>

                            <li>
                                quantifierExpr's: for all and exists</li>

                            <li>
                                group by</li>

                            <li>
                                having</li></ul></TD></TR>

                  <TR>
                    <TD>Phase 5:</TD>
                    <TD>
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                expr as top level symbol</li>

                            <li>
                                queries selecting multiple fields or as
                                comma separated list or * </li></ul></TD></TR>
            </TBODY></TABLE></p>
    </section>
</body>
</document>