<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/support.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Castor Support</title>

    <section title="Introduction">
       <p>Castor is an open-source product. This means that the source code is
          available at no charge and may be obtained using <a href="cvs.xml">CVS</a> or
         <a href="download.xml">downloaded</a> via our ftp server.</p>
	   
       <p>Since castor is freely available, including the source code,
          there is no guaranteed level of support available. The online
          <a href="#Documentation">documentation</a> is
          the best place to start. If you have trouble or have more advanced
          questions not available in the online documentation then please subscribe
          to the <a href="lists.xml">castor dev or user mailing lists</a> or join the
          <a href="/phpBB2">Castor Forums</a>. The lists and forums are the best
          place to ask questions about the product.</p>
	   
	   <p>Due to our move to <a href="http://www.codehaus.org">the Codehaus</a> in January 
		  2005, we greatly benefit from the infrastructure available at this site, and are
		  in a position to offer you to join us on the #castor IRC channel at 
		  irc.codehaus.org, where you'll mainly be able to talk to committers and
		  fellow users/developers exchanging ideas and bouncing off problems.</p>
		  
		<p>Please note though, that for problems of any kind, you should still use one of 
		   the mailing list as your prefered way of communicating to us.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Documentation">
       <p>
          The online documentation is available throughout the website. To get started
          simply click on the appropriate sections listed in the menu bar located to the
          left side of this page.
      </p>
      <p>
         If you can't find something in the documentation, try looking through the
         examples.
      </p>
      <p>
        There are also numerious <a href="presentations.xml">presentations and articles</a>
        about Castor to help get you started.
      </p>

    </section>

    <section title="Reporting Bugs and Bug Tracking">
       <p>
       If you find a bug, please file a report in our Bugzilla server at:
       <url>http://bugzilla.exolab.org</url>
      </p>
      <p>
         Before submitting bugs, please read the
         <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/page.cgi?id=etiquette.html">Bugzilla Etiguette</a> and
         <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/bugwritinghelp.html">Bug Writing Guidelines</a> from Mozilla.org.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="Commercial Support">
       <p>
       Commercial support is not provided at this time. We are also not aware
       of any third-party companies providing such support.
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>




