<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/tips-tricks.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Castor Tips &amp; Tricks</title>

    <section title="Logging and Tracing">

      <p>When developing using Castor it is recommended to use the various <tt>setLogWriter</tt>
         methods to get detailed information and error messages.</p>

      <p>Using a logger with <api>org.exolab.castor.mapping.Mapping</api> will provide detailed
         information about mapping decisions made by Castor, as well as show the SQL statements
         being used.</p>

      <p>Using a logger with <api>org.exolab.castor.jdo.JDO</api> will provide trace messages
         showing when Castor is loading, storing, creating and deleting objects. All database
         operations will appear in the log. If an object is retrieved from the cache or not modified,
         there will be no trace of load/store operations.</p>

      <p>Using a logger with <api>org.exolab.castor.xml.Unmarshaller</api> will provide trace
         messages showing conflicts between the XML document and loaded objects.</p>

      <p>A simple trace logger can be obtained from <javadoc>org.exolab.castor.util.Logger</javadoc>.
         This logger uses a standard output stream, but prefixs each line with a short message
         that indicates who generated it. It can also print the time and date of each message.
         Since logging is used for warning messages and simple tracing, Castor does not require
         a sophisticated logging mechanism.</p>

      <p>Interested in the integratation of Castor's logging with Log4J? Then see
      <a href="jdo-faq.html#Integrating-Castor's-logging-with-Log4J">this question</a> in the JDO FAQ.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="JDO: Access Mode">

      <p>If you are using JDO objects with the default access mode ('shared') and too many transactions
         abort when attempting to commit due to locks, you should consider upgrading to an 'exclusive'
         mode. When two transactions attempt to modify and store the same object at the same time,
         lock issues arise. Upgrading to an 'exclusive' mode will prevent concurrent transactions
         from modifying the same object at once.</p>

      <p>If too many transactions abort when attempting to commit due to dirty checking, you should
         consider upgrading to a 'locked' mode. When external database access modifies the same objects
         being managed by Castor, Castor will complain that objects are dirty. Upgrading to a 'locked'
         mode will prevent concurrent update.</p>

      <p>Be advised that 'exclusive' mode introduces lock contention in the Castor persistence engine,
         and 'locked' mode adds lock contention in the database. Lock contention has the affect of
         slowing down the application and consuming more CPU.</p>

      <p>If too many transaction abort due to deadlock detection, consider modifying the application
         logic. Deadlock occurs when two transactions attempt to access the same objects but not in
         the same order.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="JDO: Inheritence">

      <p>There are two types of inheritence: Java inheritence and relational inheritence.</p>

      <p>With Java inheritence two objects extend the same base class and map to two different
         tables. The mapping file requires two different mappings for each of the objects.
         For example, if <tt>Employee</tt> and <tt>Customer</tt> both extend <tt>Person</tt>,
         but <tt>Employee</tt> maps to the table <tt>emp</tt> and <tt>Person</tt> to the table
         <tt>person</tt>, the mapping file should map both of these objects separately.</p>

      <p>With relation inheritence, one table provides the base information and another table
         provides additional information using the same primary keys in both. Use the <tt>extends</tt>
         attribute to specify such inheritence in the mapping file. For example, if <tt>Computer</tt>
         extends <tt>Product</tt> and the table <tt>comp</tt> provides computer-specific columns
         in addition to product columns in <tt>prod</tt>, the mapping for <tt>Computer</tt> will
         specify <tt>Product</tt> as the extended class.</p>

      <p>When a class just extends a generic base class or implements an interface, this form
         of inheritence is not reflected in the mapping file.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="XML: Indentation">

      <p>By default the marshaller writes XML documents without indentation. When developing
         using Castor or debugging it might be desireable to use indentation to make the XML
         documents more readable. To turn indentation on, modify the Castor properties file,
         or create a new properties file in the classpath (named <tt>castor.properties</tt>)
         with the following content:
         <pre>
org.exolab.castor.indent=true
         </pre></p>

      <p>Indentation inflates the size of the generated XML documents, and also consumes more
         CPU. It is recommended not to use indentation in a production environment.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="XML:Marshall validation">
    	<p>It is possible to disable the validation in the marshalling framework by
    	   simply modifying the Castor properties file or create a new properties file in the classpath
    	   (named <tt>castor.properties</tt>) with the following content:
         <pre>
org.exolab.castor.marshalling.validation=true
         </pre></p>
    </section>

    <section title="JDO: Views of Same Object">

      <p>It is possible to use different objects and mappings to the same tables. For example,
         it is possible to define a subset of a table and load only several of the columns,
         or load an object without it's relations.</p>

      <p>To determine the first and last names and e-mail address of an object without loading
         the entire person object, create a subset class and map that class to a portion of
         the table. Such a class cannot be used to create a new person, but can be used to
         delete or modify the person's details.</p>

      <p>Use partial views with care. If you attempt to load the same record using a full
         object and a subset object, changes to one of these objects are allowed, but
         changes to both will result in a conflict and roll back the transaction.
         Locking will not work properly between full and subset objects.
         Also note, that each of the too objects will have its own cache, so
         if you update the first object and load the second, you may obtain old values.
         To avoid this situation you may turn off the cache for both objects:
         <code><![CDATA[
             <class ... >
                <cache-type type="none">
                ...
             </class>
         ]]></code>
         </p>

    </section>

    <section title="JDO: Upgrading Locks">

      <p>When an object is loaded into memory in the default access mode ('shared'),
         a read lock is acquired on that object. When the transaction commits, if there
         are changes to the object, a write lock will be required. There is no guarantee
         that a write lock can be acquired, e.g. if another transaction attempts to
         change the same object at the same time.</p>

      <p>To assure concurrent access, you may upgrade the object's lock by calling the
         <api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.Database">lock(java.lang.Object)</api> method.
         This method will acquire a write lock, or return if a timeout passed and the
         lock could not be acquired. Once a lock has been acquired, no other transaction
         can attempt to read the object until the current transaction completes.</p>

      <p>Object locking is recommended only if concurrent access results in conflicts
         and aborted transactions. Generally locks results in lock contention which has an
         affect on performance.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="XML/JDO: NoClassDefFoundError">
       <p>
          Check your CLASSPATH, check it often, there is no reason not too!
       </p>
    </section>

    <section title="XML: Mapping: auto-complete">
       <p>
          <b>Note: this only works with Castor-XML</b>
       </p>
       <p>
          To save time when writing your mappings, try using the <i>auto-complete</i>
          attribute of <i>class</i>. When using auto-complete, Castor will introspect
          your class and automatically fill in any missing fields.
       </p>
       <p>
          <b>Example:</b>
          <code>&lt;class name="com.acme.Foo" auto-complete="true"/&gt;</code>
       </p>
       <p>
          This is also compatible with generated descriptor files, you can use a mapping file
          to override some of the behavior of a compiled descriptor by using auto-complete.
          <br/><b>**</b>Note: Be careful to make sure you use the exact field name as specified
          in the generated descriptor file in order to modify the behavior of the field descriptor!
          Otherwise, you'll probably end up with two fields being marshalled!
       </p>
    </section>

    <section title="XML/JDO: Create method">
      <p>
         Castor requires that classes have a public, no-argument constructor
         in order to provide the ability marshal &amp; unmarshal objects of that type.
      </p>

      <p>
         create-method is an optional attribute to the &lt;field&gt; mapping
         element that can be used to overcome this restriction in cases where you
         have an existing object model that consists of, say, singleton classes,
         where public, no-argument constructors must not be present by definition.
      </p>

      <p>
         Assume for example that a class "A" that you want to be able to
         unmarshal uses a singleton class as one of its properties.
         When attempting to unmarshal class "A", you should get an exception,
         because the singleton property has no public constructor.
         Assume a reference to the singleton can be obtained via a static
         getInstance() method, you can add a "create method" to class A like so:
      </p>

      <code>
         <![CDATA[
            public MySingleton getSingletonProperty()
            {
               return MySingleton.getInstance();
            }
         ]]>
      </code>

      <p>
         and in the mapping file for class A, you can define the singleton
         property like so:
      </p>

      <code>
         <![CDATA[
            <field name="mySingletonProperty"
                  type="com.u2d.MySingleton"
                  create-method="getSingletonProperty">
               <bind-xml name="my-singleton-property" node="element" />
            </field>
         ]]>
      </code>

      <p>
         This illustrates how the create-method attribute is quite a useful
         mechanism for dealing with exception situations where you might
         want to take advantage of marshaling even when some classes do not
         have no-argument public constructors.
      </p>

      <p>
        <b>Note:</b> As of this writing, the specified create-method must
        exist as a method in the current class (i.e. the class being described
        by the current &lt;class&gt; element). In the future it may be possible
        to use external static factory methods.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="XML: MarshalListener and UnmarshalListener">
      <p>
         Castor allows control on the object being marshalled or unmarshalled by
         a set of two listener interfaces: MarshalListener and UnmarshalListener.
      </p>

      <p>
         The MarshalListener interface located in <code>org.exolab.castor.xml</code> listens to
         two different that are intercepted by the following methods:
         <ul>
             <li>preMarshal: this method is called before an object gets marshalled.</li>
             <li>postMarshall: this method is called once an object has been marshalled.</li>
         </ul>
      </p>

      <p>
         The UnmarshalListener located also in <code>org.exolab.castor.xml</code>  offers the possibility
         to intercept more events with the four following methods:
         <ul>
             <li>initialized: this method is called once an object has been instantiated.</li>
             <li>attributesProcessed: this method is called when the attributes have just been read and processed.</li>
             <li>fieldAdded: this method is called when an object is added to a parent.</li>
             <li>unmarshalled: this method is called when an object has been <b>fully</b> unmarshalled.</li>

         </ul>
      </p>

    </section>

  </body>
</document>









