<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="http://xslp.exolab.org/index.xml">
  <body>
    <title>The XSL:P Project</title>

    <header>
      <p> XSL:P is a free, open-source <a href="http://www.w3.org/style/xsl">XSLT </a> processor written in Java.
          Currently the processor implements the <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-xslt-19991116">XSLT 1.0 Recommendation (19991116)</a> .

      </p>
	<p>
          The goal is to not only to create a free XSL processor, but make it fast and reliable.
	    We plan on doing that with the help of those using the processor. We encourage people to download,
          use, and enhance the processor. If you any comments, find a bug, or need a feature implemented,
          that is currently not, please send an e-mail  to <a href="mailto:kvisco@intalio.com">Keith Visco </a>.
          We will prioritize the implementation of features and enhancements based on feedback.
          If you download the processor and make changes to it, please send them along so that They can be reviewed
          and incorporated.
      </p>

      <p><b>$RELEASE_DATE$</b> Version $VERSION$ is now <a href="download.xml">available for download</a>.</p>

      <p><b>Note:</b> Presently we are hosting two mailing lists. Traffic is not high, so if
         you are interested in keeping up to date with new releases, please <a href="lists.xml">subscribe
         to this list</a>.</p>

    </header>


  <section title="Features">

      <p>Short feature list:
        <ul>
          <li>Includes support for the XSLT 1.0 recommendation </li>
          <li>Improved, faster design </li>
          <li>Includes SAX 1.0 support (2.0 support on the way)  </li>
        </ul>
        See the <a href="status.xml">status page</a> for more information.</p>

    </section>



    <section title="About the XSL:P Project">


      <p>Keith Visco got the inspiration for the processor from Sean Russell's Docproc back in mid 1998.
         Without Docproc he probably never would have started using XSL at such an early stage.
         He started making lots of modifications to it, such as adding ECMAScript support using FESI
         (Free ECMAScript Interpreter), changing the XML parser to IBM's XML for Java, instead of Textuality's Lark,
         so that he could make use of the DOM. He fixed bugs, added functionality, and he did my best at optimizing!
         All in all, he ended up re-writing the majority of it. Once the XSL Working Draft 1.0 19980818 was released, he
         decided to start fresh, so he re-wrote the processor.

         He has re-implemented many portions of XSL:P as the XSL Working Group has been releasing
         the new versions of the XSL Working Draft.
      </p>

      <p>For <a href="contributors.xml">a full list of contributors</a>.</p>

      <p>Most of the code released through the XSL:P Project has been developed by
         <a href="mailto:kvisco@intalio.com">Keith Visco</a>.
         Contributors are welcome to join this project. Please join us on the
         <a href="lists.xml">mailing list</a>.</p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
