<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/origins.xml">
  <body>
    <title>About The Origins Of The Name</title>
    <header>
      <p><i>Why did you decide to call it Castor?</i></p>

      <p>First, let me say you are not the first to ask this question, and you won't be the last.
         For many, the term "Castor" has a mysterious aura which leaves the user with a craving,
         a necessity if you must, of wanting an explanation. The need to understand has plagued
         people of the human race for some time now.</p>

      <p>Some have speculated that Castor comes from the heavens. Either being an astronomer or
         having flipped through the pages of a Merriam Webster dictionary you may have run across
         the reference to Castor. Castor in this context is part of a "double star" within the
         Gemini constellation, the twin star is called Pollux. For all those looking to the sky
         for the answer, let me reassure you that we do not use Castor in this context. Actually
         with all the smog here in California, the developers of Castor rarely look to the sky
         for anything.</p>

      <p>Some have speculated that some how the name comes from the act of "casting" one type into
         another. This is a rather interesting speculation. Castor is a pretty advanced "Casting"
         framework, however, this speculation is as far from the truth as is the distance from earth
         to Castor and Pollux.</p>

      <p>Other more intuitive people, perhaps by looking at the Castor logo, have deduced that
         Castor is actually a Beaver. Yes it's true. Castor is the more formal or scientific name
         for a simple little Beaver. This raises a more interesting question.</p>

      <p><i>Why did you name your software after a beaver?</i></p>

      <p>The truth of the matter is that it's highly classified, and on a need-to-know basis.
         Even members of our own team do not know. However we are allowed to post more speculations
         on this topic. The most common speculation is that a beaver is well know for it's
         engineering skills. It cut's down trees, and builds dams and lodges. Since Castor builds
         source code, using blue prints (an XML Schema), then it too is an engineer.</p>

      <p>A more abstract yet rather interesting speculation that builds on the previous reads as
         follows. XML is based on "trees" or "groves". A beaver cuts down trees. Therefore Castor
         removes the notion of trees from processing XML documents. This is an interesting observation
         in that Castor does just that. Castor eliminates the "tree" methodology when dealing with XML.
         It is an XML data binding framework which allows you to deal directly with your data, instead
         of thinking in terms of a "tree".</p>

      <p>Another equally good speculation is that a beaver is one of the cutest little animals in
         the world, and we just couldn't resist giving it some due attention.</p>

      <p>There are other speculations, some of which we can not in good nature add to this page.
         We cannot comment on which speculation may be closer to the truth. We let each user decide
         on his or her own. Simply choose the speculation which most reduces your craving for more
         understanding, and feel free to come up with your own speculations.</p>

      <p>Keith "Castor" Visco, Chief XML Architect [<email>kvisco@intalio.com</email>]</p>
    </header>
  </body>
</document>
