<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/index.xml">
  <body>
    <title>The Castor Project</title>

    <header>

      <p>
         Castor is an open source data binding framework for Java[tm].
         It's basically the shortest path between Java objects, XML documents, SQL tables and LDAP
         directories. Castor provides Java to XML binding, Java to SQL/LDAP persistence, and then
         some more.
      </p>

      <p><b>$RELEASE_DATE$</b> Version $VERSION$ is now <a href="download.xml">available for download</a>.</p>

      <p><a href="origins.xml">About the origins of the name</a></p>

      <p><b>Note:</b> Presently we are hosting two mailing lists. Traffic is not too high,
         so if you are interested in keeping up to date with new releases, or have problems,
         questions or feedback please <a href="lists.xml">subscribe
         to the appropriate list</a>.</p>

    </header>

    <section title="Features">

      <p>Short feature list (we haven't got all day):
        <ul>
          <li>
             Castor XML: Java object model to and from XML
             <br/>&#160;&#160; - Generate source code from an XML Schema
          </li>
          <li>Castor JDO: Java object persistence to RDBMS</li>
          <li>Castor DAX: Java object persistence to LDAP</li>
          <li>Castor DSML: LDAP directory exchange through XML</li>
          <li>XML-based mapping file specify the mapping between one model and another</li>
          <li>Support for schema-less Java to XML binding</li>
          <li>In memory caching and write-at-commit reduces JDBC operations</li>
          <li>Two phase commit transactions, object rollback and deadlock detection</li>
          <li>OQL query mapping to SQL queries</li>
          <li>EJB container managed persistence provider for OpenEJB</li>
        </ul>
        See the <a href="status.xml">status page</a> for more information.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="About the Castor Project">


      <p>The Castor project has been developed out of need: the need to get stuff done
         and the need to write useful code. It has been designed and coded over many cups
         of Latte and tall no-whip White Mocha, as proof that coffee beans do come in handy.</p>

      <p>For <a href="contributors.xml">a full list of contributors</a>.</p>

      <p>Most of the code released through the Castor Project has been developed by
         <a href="mailto:kvisco@intalio.com">Keith Visco</a>, Chief XML Architect,
         Intalio Inc. and <a href="mailto:arkin@intalio.com">Assaf Arkin</a>.
         Contributors are welcome to join this project. Please join us on the
         <a href="lists.xml">mailing list</a>.</p>
       <p>
         Castor includes software, such as Xerces, Jakarta ORO, and Jakarta Regexp,
         developed by the <a href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a>.
         Castor also includes <a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit testing framework</a>.
       </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
