<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/extras.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Castor Extra Features and 3rd Party Tools</title>

    <header>
       <p>
          - <b><font color="red">New</font></b> - Shelly Mujtaba's <a href="#JDOMapper">JDOMapper</a>
       </p>
    </header>

    <section title="3rd Party Tools">
       <p>
          This section contains pointers to 3rd party tools.
       </p>
       <p>
          <b>Note: We do not provide
          support for these tools, please visit their respective websites for
          support, questions, or concerns.
          </b>
       </p>
       <section title="Castor-Doclet">
         <p>
            <table border="0">
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Description:</td>
                    <td>
                        Castor-Doclet is a tool for generating the Castor JDO mapping file from
                        javadoc tags added in the source code. It also has the ability to generate
                        a DDL file for different databases.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Current Author:</td>
                    <td>Mickael Guessant</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">URL:</td>
                    <td> <url>http://castordoclet.sourceforge.net</url></td>
                </tr>
            </table>
         </p>
       </section>

       <section title="Castor-Oil">
         <p>
            <table border="0">
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Description:</td>
                    <td>
                        Castor Oil is a GUI tool for generating the Castor mapping file from
                        from existing data base tables. To my knowledge Castor Oil was the
                        first GUI tool written for Castor. It was originally written by
                        Lance Lavandowska, but has recently found a new maintainer and
                        developer, Peter Kasson, who has been actively working to bring
                        Oil back up to compatibility with the latest version of Castor.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Current Author:</td>
                    <td>Peter Kasson</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">URL:</td>
                    <td><url>http://vintech.no-ip.org:8181/oss/index.jsp</url></td>
                </tr>
            </table>
         </p>
       </section>


       <section title="O2XMapper">
         <p>
            <table border="0">
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Description:</td>
                    <td>
                        This tool is a GUI front end to Castor's MappingTool. It allows
                        automatic creation and customization of mapping files. This tool
                        is primarily for Castor XML, but check out
                        <a href="#JDOMapper">JDOMapper</a> from the same author.
                     </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Author:</td>
                    <td>Shelly Mujtaba</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">URL:</td>
                    <td> <url>http://o2xmapper.sourceforge.net</url></td>
                </tr>
            </table>
         </p>
       </section>

       <section title="JDOMapper">
         <p>
            <table border="0">
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Description:</td>
                    <td>
                       JDOMapper provides a user interface for creating Castor JDO mapping files.
                       The application allows user to import Java classes and map them to an relational
                       schema . The tool performs series of validations to ensure that classes and fields
                       are correctly mapped. Existing mapping files can also be imported into the tool.
                       <br/>
                       JDOMapper will pre-fill most of the options for a class or field. Finally,
                       the User interface provides a more manageable view of the Mapping configuration,
                       especially as the number of mapped classes grows large.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Author:</td>
                    <td>Shelly Mujtaba</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">URL:</td>
                    <td> <url>http://o2xmapper.sourceforge.net/jdomapper/</url></td>
                </tr>
            </table>
         </p>
       </section>

       <section title="Raccoon">
         <p>
            <table border="0">
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Description:</td>
                    <td>
                       Another tool that allows one to automatically create a Castor mapping
                       file for a given set of Java Beans. This tool also provides a host of
                       other functionality which is geared towards integration with TIBCO
                       products.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Author:</td>
                    <td>Cedric Rouvrais</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">URL:</td>
                    <td> <url>http://raccoon.sourceforge.net</url></td>
                </tr>
            </table>
         </p>
       </section>

       <section title="SchemaWizard">
         <p>
            <table border="0">
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Description:</td>
                    <td>
                      SchemaWizard is a tool which automates building user interfaces to generate and modify XML instances following a XML schema.
                      SchemaWizard achieves this by mapping XML Schema types to HTML form elements with a series of Velocity templates, JSP pages and Javabeans.
                    </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">Author:</td>
                    <td>Ozgur Balsoy</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td valign="top">URL:</td>
                    <td> <url>http://ptlportal.communitygrids.iu.edu/schemawizard/index.html</url></td>
                </tr>
            </table>
         </p>
       </section>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>




