<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/lists.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Castor Mailing Lists</title>
    <header>
    </header>
    <section title="Mailing Lists">

      <p>
         <b>Note:</b> You can use a <b><font size="+1">searchable</font></b> archive of the castor-dev list at <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/castor-dev%40exolab.org">
         http://www.mail-archive.com/castor-dev%40exolab.org</a>  It appears there is a delay of one (1) or two (2) days for messages
         to be archived at that site. You can also use the "unsearchable" archive listed below to look
         at the very latest messages to the list.
      </p>


      <p><b>castor-dev</b></p>
      <p>Moderate volume (possibly more than 15 messages a day) mailing list dedicated to the developers of Castor.</p>

      <p><mailing-list name="castor-dev" description="The Castor Developer's Mailing List"
                       server="exolab.org" manager="minimalist"
                       archive="http://castor.exolab.org/list-archive/"/>
      </p>
       <p>
         <b>Note:</b> please familiarize yourself with the <a href="#Guidelines">guidelines</a>
         before posting to the list.
      </p>

      <p><b>castor-announce</b></p>
      <p>Low volume (possibly more than 1 message per week)
         mailing list for special announcements about Castor, such as
         new releases.
      </p>

      <p><mailing-list name="castor-announce" description="The Castor Announcement Mailing List"
                       server="exolab.org" manager="minimalist"/></p>
    </section>
    <section title="Guidelines">
    <p>
The following are some general "common-sense" guidelines for using the
mailing lists:</p>

<p><pre>
Most people are already following these guidelines. To those people, I
thank you. For those of you who are not...please read carefully.

1. Please refrain from using words and phrases like URGENT, IMPORTANT,
   MY WIFE WILL LEAVE ME IF YOU DO NOT RESPOND, etc, in the subject line
   of your postings. Or even in the body of the message for that matter.

   You may think that things which are URGENT, or IMPORTANT to you,
   are just as urgent and important to everyone else reading this
   list. You'd be surprised at just how wrong an assumption like
   that can be. As a matter of fact, I personally tend to read
   all such postings last and give them a low priority.

2. Please use meaningful subject lines. "Newbie Question",
   is not meaningful what-so-ever.

3. Please provide necessary information, where applicable.
   Statements like, "I recieve a NullPointerException when
   using Castor, what's up with that?", are not very helpful,
   add unnecessary traffic on the list, and will probably
   never get an answer.

4. As a follow on to #3, when submitting examples, please try
   to submit the smallest possible example which demonstrates
   the problem. Short examples are easier to follow and will
   get quicker responses from developers or other users than
   long examples with lots of extraneous code/data.

4. Please read the documentation before posting. One of the
   biggest problems is that there is not a lot of documentation
   to Castor. At the same time, because it doesn't take long,
   everyone should read what is written before posting.

5. Please check the mail archives before posting. Many questions
   on this list have already been answered before. I am aware
   that the current mail archive is not very good on a number
   of issues (searching, reliability, etc). We are working
   on these issues and hope to have a new archive system in
   place shortly.

6. Please refrain from posting confidential information. Once an
   e-mail is sent to the list, it goes out to all subscribers,
   including archive engines. We cannot remove or delete messages
   sent to the list. Once sent they are available for the public
   to see. If you are unsure about what is confidential or not,
   check with your manager, supervisor, or the person in charge
   at your company.

7. Please be kind and respectful to your fellow castor users.
   Remember, except for me, you were all newbies at one point.

8. If you are going on vacation. Please enjoy yourself. We
   really want you to have fun and get some much needed
   rest and relaxation. With that we being said and to be
   perfectly honest none of us really want to receive your
   automated vacation responses. So please either add a filter
   to your vacation response so it doesn't get sent to the
   list or users posting to the list, or simply remove yourself
   from the list before you go, and add yourself back when
   you return.

</pre></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
