<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.codehaus.org/cvs.xml">
  
    <properties>
        <title>CVS access</title>
        <author email="werner DOT guttmann AT gmx DOT net">Werner Guttmann</author>
        <abstract>
            Outlines how to acess the CVS repository.
        </abstract>
        <status>Final</status>
    </properties>
  
  <body>
  
    <title>CVS Access &amp; bug tracking</title>

	<section title="Issue Reporting and Tracking - JIRA">
	
		<p>Please use <a href="http://jira.codehaus.org/browse/CASTOR">JIRA</a> for reporting 
		   any issue and tracking their progress. In addition, Jira offers many additonal
		   (more sophisticated) features that allow you to keep in touch with
		   the project's current progress.</p>
    		   
  		<p>Before submitting issues, please read 
  		   <a href="how-to-submit-a-bug.xml">'How to submit an issue'</a>.</p>
      		   
	</section>
	
	<section title="CVS access">

		<p>To get the latest, most up-to-date source code, you'll need to use 
		   CVS. Please see the section on <a href="#Anonymous-CVS-Access">anonymous CVS access</a> 
		   below. If you wish to simply browse the CVS for specific files or to view 
		   changes and commit logs use <a href="http://cvs.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/castor/castor">FishEye access</a>
		   to the CVS repository.</p>

	    <p>Or as an altwernative, please <a href="download.xml">download</a> the full 
	       source distribution for a given release.</p>

		<section title="Anonymous CVS Access">

			<p>The source code, documentation and libraries are available for anonymous 
			   access from the <a href="www.codehaus.org">Codehaus CVS server</a>.</p>

			<p>CVS is updated regularly and may contain unstable (untested) code when 
			   you check it out - though in general this should not happen.</p>

			<p>To access the Castor CVS repository, please use the following settings:</p>
			
			<ul>
				<li><b>CVS root</b>: <tt>:pserver:anon@cvs.castor.codehaus.org:/home/projects/castor/scm</tt></li>
				<li><b>password</b>: is not required, and should thus be left empty.</li>
			</ul>

      		<p>To, for example, login to CVS from the command line and checkout the most recent
      		   code of Castor, use the following commands:</p>

      		<code-panel>
  $ cvs -d :pserver:anon@cvs.castor.codehaus.org:/home/projects/castor/scm login
  password:
  $ cvs -d :pserver:anon@cvs.castor.codehaus.org:/home/projects/castor/scm checkout castor
      		</code-panel>

    	</section>

    	<section title="Behind A Firewall?">
      
			<p>Sometimes firewalls are configured in such a way that the ports used by CVS
			   are blocked, and thus users behind the firewall cannot access the CVS 
			   repository. If you fall into this category, there's some alternatives outlined 
			   below.</p>

    		<p><a href="www.codehaus.org">Codehaus</a> provides a HTTP interface to CVS 
    		   repository using FishEye (tm). Using this tool, please download one of the
    		   following CVS snapshots from the CVS server from 
    		   <url>http://cvs.castor.codehaus.org</url>:</p>
            
			<ul>
				<li><a href="http://cvs.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/~tarball=zip/castor/castor/castor.zip">ZIP archive</a></li>
				<li><a href="http://cvs.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/~tarball=zip/castor/castor/castor.tgz">TGZ archive</a></li>
				<li><a href="http://cvs.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/~tarball=zip/castor/castor/castor.tbz2">TBZ2 archive</a></li>
			</ul>

			<p>Another option for accessing CVS from behind a firewall is to use 
			   <a href="http://cvsgrab.sf.net/">CVSGrab</a>. It's designed as a
			   solution for exactly this situation.</p>

	    </section>

	</section>
    
  </body>
</document>
