<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="xml.mapping">
    <title>XML Mapping</title>

    <section id="xml.mapping.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>Castor XML mapping is a way to simplify the binding of java classes to
      XML document. It allows to transform the data contained in a java object
      model into/from an XML document.</para>

      <para>Although it is possible to rely on Castor's default behavior to marshal and
        unmarshal Java objects into an XML document, it might be necessary to have more
        control over this behavior. For example, if a Java object model already exists,
        Castor XML Mapping can be used as a bridge between the XML document and that
        Java object model.</para>

      <para>Castor allows one to specify some of its marshalling/unmarshalling behavior
        using a mapping file. This file gives explicit information to Castor on how a
        given XML document and a given set of Java objects relate to each other.</para>

      <para>A Castor mapping file is a good way to dissociate the changes in the structure
        of a Java object model from the changes in the corresponding XML document
        format.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="xml.mapping.overview"><title>Overview</title>

      <para>The mapping information is specified by an XML document. This document is
        written from the point of view of the Java object and describes how the
        properties of the object have to be translated into XML. One constraint for the
        mapping file is that Castor should be able to infer unambiguously from it how a
        given XML element/attribute has to be translated into the object model during
        unmarshalling.</para>

      <para>The mapping file describes for each object how each of its fields have to be
        mapped into XML. A field is an abstraction for a property of an object. It can
        correspond directly to a public class variable or indirectly to a property via
        some accessor methods (setters and getters).</para>

      <para>It is possible to use the mapping and Castor default behavior in conjunction:
        when Castor has to handle an object or an XML data but can't find information
        about it in the mapping file, it will rely on its default behavior. Castor will
        use the Java Reflection API to introspect the Java objects to determine what to do.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> Castor can't handle all possible mappings. In some complex cases, it may be
        necessary to rely on an XSL transformation in conjunction with Castor to adapt the
        XML document to a more friendly format.</para>


      <section id="xml.mapping.overview.marshalling"><title>Marshalling Behavior</title>

        <para>For Castor, a Java class has to map into an XML element. When Castor marshals an
          object, it will:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>use the mapping information, if any, to find the name of the element to create</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>or</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>by default, create a name using the name of the class</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>It will then use the fields information from the mapping file to determine how a
          given property of the object has to be translated into one and only one of the
          following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>an attribute</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>an element</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>text content</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>nothing, as we can choose to ignore a particular field</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>This process will be recursive: if Castor finds a property that has a class type
          specified elsewhere in the mapping file, it will use this information to marshal
          the object.</para>

        <para>By default, if Castor finds no information for a given class in the mapping
          file, it will introspect the class and apply a set of default rules to guess the
          fields and marshal them. The default rules are as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>All primitive types, including the primitive type wrappers (Boolean,
            Short, etc...) are marshalled as attributes.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>All other objects are marshalled as elements with either text content
            or element content.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

      </section>

      <section id="xml.mapping.overview.unmarshalling"><title>Unmarshalling Behavior</title>

        <para>When Castor finds an element while unmarshalling a document, it will try to use
          the mapping information to determine which object to instantiate. If no mapping
          information is present, Castor will use the name of the element to try to guess
          the name of a class to instantiate (for example, for an element named
          'test-element', Castor will try to instantiate a class named 'TestElement' if no
          information is given in the mapping file). Castor will then use the field
          information of the mapping file to handle the content of the element.</para>

        <para>If the class is not described in the mapping file, Castor will instrospect the
          class using the Java Reflection API to determine if there is any function of the
          form getXxxYyy()/setXxxYyy(&lt;type> x). This accessor will be associated with XML
          element/attribute named 'xxx-yyy'. In the future, we will provide a way to
          override this default behavior.</para>

        <para>Castor will introspect object variables and use direct access _only_ if no
          get/set methods have been found in the class. In this case, Castor will look for
          public variables of the form:</para>

        <programlisting language="java">
public &lt;type> xxxYYY;
        </programlisting>

        <para>and expect an element/attribute named 'xxx-yyy'. The only handled
          collections for &lt;type> are java.lang.Vector and array. (up to version
          0.8.10)</para>

        <para>For primitive &lt;type>, Castor will look for an attribute first and then an
          element. If &lt;type> is not a primitive type, Castor will look for an element
          first and then an attribute.</para>

      </section>
    </section>


    <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile"><title>The Mapping File</title>
    
    	<para>
    		The following sections define the syntax for each of the mapping file artefacts
    		and their semantical meaning.
    	</para>
    
    	<section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.sampledomainobjects"><title>Sample domain objects</title>
    	
    		<para>
    			This section defines a small domain model that will be referenced by
    			various mapping file (fragments/samples) in the following sections. The model consists 
    			of two two classes <classname>Order</classname> and <classname>OrderItem</classname>, where an order 
    			holds a list of order items.
    		</para>

    		<programlisting language="java">
public class Order {

    private List <emphasis role="bold">orderItems</emphasis>;
    private String orderNumber;
    
    <emphasis role="bold">public List getOrderItems()</emphasis> {
        return orderItems;
    }
    <emphasis role="bold">public void setOrderItems(List orderItems)</emphasis> {
        this.orderItems = orderItems;
    }
    public String getOrderNumber() {
        return orderNumber;
    }
    public void setOrderNumber(String orderNumber) {
        this.orderNumber = orderNumber;
    }
}

public class OrderItem {
    
    private String id;
    private Integer orderQuantity;
    
    public String getId() {
        return id;
    }
    public void setId(String id) {
        this.id = id;
    }
    public Integer getOrderQuantity() {
        return orderQuantity;
    }
    public void setOrderQuantity(Integer orderQuantity) {
        this.orderQuantity = orderQuantity;
    }
}</programlisting>
           
	        <para>
	        	As shown above in bold, the <classname>Order</classname> instance has a (private) field <classname>'orderItems'</classname>
				to hold a collection of <classname>OrderItem</classname> instances. This field is publically exposed
				by corresponding getter and setter methods.
	        </para>
           

    	</section>

      <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.mapping"><title>The &lt;mapping> element</title>

        <programlisting language="java">
&lt;!ELEMENT mapping ( description?, include*, field-handler*, class*, key-generator* )>
        </programlisting>

        <para>The &lt;mapping> element is the root element of a mapping file. It contains:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>an optional description</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>zero or more &lt;include> which facilitates reusing mapping files</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>zero of more &lt;field-handler> defining custom, configurable field handlers</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>zero or more &lt;class> descriptions: one for each class we intend to give
            mapping information</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>zero or more &lt;key-generator>: not used for XML mapping</para></listitem>

        </itemizedlist>

        <para>A mapping file look like this:</para>

        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE mapping PUBLIC "-//EXOLAB/Castor Mapping DTD Version 1.0//EN"
      castor.org
                         "http://castor.org/mapping.dtd">

<mapping>
	<description>Description of the mapping</description>
	
	<include href="other_mapping_file.xml"/>
	
	<!-- mapping for class 'A' -->
	<class name="A">
	        .........
	</class>
	
	<!-- mapping for class 'B' -->
	<class name="B">
	        .........
	</class>

</mapping>]]></programlisting>

      </section>

      <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.class"><title>The &lt;class&gt; element</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT class ( description?, cache-type?, map-to?, field+ )>
<!ATTLIST class
          name            ID       #REQUIRED
          extends         IDREF    #IMPLIED
          depends         IDREF    #IMPLIED
          auto-complete   ( true |false ) "false"
          identity        CDATA    #IMPLIED
          access          ( read-only | shared | exclusive | db-locked )  "shared"
          key-generator   IDREF    #IMPLIED >]]></programlisting>


        <para>The  <classname>&lt;class></classname> element contains all the information used to 
           map a Java class into an XML document. The content of <classname>&lt;class></classname>
           is mainly used to describe the fields that will be mapped.</para>

        <table frame="all">
            <title>Description of the attributes</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
        	<thead>
        	    <row>
	        		<entry>Name</entry>
	        		<entry>Description</entry>
        		</row>
        	</thead>
        	<tbody>
        	<row>
        		<entry><emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis></entry>
        		<entry>The fuly-qualified name of the Java class that we want to map to.</entry>
        	</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">extends</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>The fully qualified name of a parent class. This attribute should be used <emphasis role="bold">only</emphasis>
					if this class extends another class for which a class mapping is provided. It 
					should <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> be used if there's no class maping for the extended 
					class.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">depends</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Used with Castor JDO only; for more information on this field, please
				    see the <ulink url="http://www.castor.org/jdo-mapping.html">JDO documentation</ulink>.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">auto-complete</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>If true, the class will be introspected to determine its field and 
				    the fields specified in the mapping file will be used to overide the 
				    fields found during the introspection.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">identity</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Used with Castor JDO only; for more information on this field, please see
				    see the <ulink url="http://www.castor.org/jdo-mapping.html">JDO documentation</ulink>.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">access</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Used with Castor JDO only; for more information on this field, please see
				    see the <ulink url="http://www.castor.org/jdo-mapping.html">JDO documentation</ulink>.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">key-generator</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Used with Castor JDO only; for more information on this field, please see
				    see the <ulink url="http://www.castor.org/jdo-mapping.html">JDO documentation</ulink>.</entry>
			</row>
			</tbody>
			</tgroup>
        </table>
    
        <para>The auto-complete attributes is interesting as it allow a fine degree
           of control of the introspector: it is possible to specifiy only the
           fields whose Castor default behavior does not suite our needs. These
           feature should simplify the handling of complexe class containing many
           fields. Please see below for an example usage of this attribute.</para>

		<table frame="all">
		  <title>Description of the content</title>
		  <tgroup cols="2">
			<thead>
			 <row>
				<entry>Name</entry>
				<entry>Description</entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">description</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>An optional description.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">cache-type</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Used with Castor JDO only; for more information on this field, please see
				    see the <ulink url="http://www.castor.org/jdo-mapping.html">JDO documentation</ulink>.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">map-to</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>
					Used if the name of the element is not the name of the class. By
					default, Castor will infer the name of the element to be mapped from
					the name of the class: a Java class named 'XxxYyy' will be transformed
					in 'xxx-yyy'. If you don't want Castor to generate the name, you need
					to use &lt;map-to> to specify the name you want to use. &lt;map-to> is
					only used for the root element.
				</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">field</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Zero or more &lt;field> elements, which are used to describe the properties 
				    of the Java class being mapped.</entry>
			</row>
			</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>

		<section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.sampleclassmappings">
           <title>Sample &lt;class&gt; mappings</title>
		
        <para>The following mapping fragment defines a class mapping for the <classname>OrderItem</classname>
           class:</para>

        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<class name="mypackage.OrderItem>
           
   <map-to xml="item"/>

   <field name="id" type="string">
      <bind-xml name="identity" node="attribute"/>
   </field>

   </field name="orderQuantity" type="integer">
      <bind-xml name="quantity" node="element"/>
   </field>

</class>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
        	When marshalling an	<classname>OrderItem</classname> instance, this yields the 
        	following XML:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>        
<item identity="12">
   <quantity>100</quantity>
</item>]]></programlisting>

			<para>The following mapping fragment defines a class mapping for the same
			   class, where for all properties but <classname>id</classname> introspection should
			   be used; the use of the <classname>auto-complete</classname> attribute instructs Castor XML
			   to use introspection for all attributes other than <classname>'id'</classname>, where
			   the given field mapping will be used.</para>

        <programlisting language="java">
&lt;class name="mypackage.OrderItem <emphasis role="bold">auto-complete="true"</emphasis>>
           
   &lt;map-to xml="item"/>

   &lt;field name="id" type="string">
      &lt;bind-xml name="identity" node="attribute"/>
   &lt;/field>

&lt;/class></programlisting>

        <para>
        	When marshalling the very same <classname>OrderItem</classname> instance, this yields the 
        	following XML:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>        
<item identity="12">
   <order-quantity>100</order-quantity>
</item>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
        	By removing the &lt;map-to&gt; element from above class mapping, ...
        </para>

        <programlisting language="java">
&lt;class name="mypackage.OrderItem <emphasis role="bold">auto-complete="true"</emphasis>>
           
   &lt;field name="id" type="string">
      &lt;bind-xml name="identity" node="attribute"/>
   &lt;/field>

&lt;/class></programlisting>
        
        <para>
        	... Castor will use introspection to infer the element name from the Java 
        	class name (<classname>OrderItem</classname>), applying a default naming convention scheme.
        </para>

        <para>
        	When marshalling the very same <classname>OrderItem</classname> instance, this yields the 
        	following XML:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>        
<order-item identity="12">
   <order-quantity>100</order-quantity>
</order-item>]]></programlisting>
			   
        </section>

      </section>

      <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.mapto"><title>The &lt;map-to> element</title>

        <programlisting>
&lt;!ELEMENT map-to EMPTY>
&lt;!ATTLIST map-to
          table               NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
          xml                 NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
          ns-uri              NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
          ns-prefix           NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
          ldap-dn             NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
          element-definition  (true|false) "false"     <emphasis role="bold">NEW as of 1.0M3</emphasis>
          ldap-oc             NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED></programlisting>

        <para><classname>&lt;map-to></classname> is used to specify the name of the element that should 
           be associated with the given class. <classname>&lt;map-to></classname> is only used for 
           the root class. If this information is not present, Castor will:</para>
          
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>for marshalling, infer the name of the element to be mapped from the name of
            the class: a Java class named 'XxxYyy' will be transformed into 'xxx-yyy'.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>for unmarshalling, infer the name of the class from the name of the element:
            for an element named 'test-element' Castor will try to use a
            class named 'TestElement'</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <para>Please note that it is possible to change the naming scheme used by Castor 
           to translate between the XML name and the Java class name in the 
           <classname>castor.properties</classname> file.</para>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>Description of attributes</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <tbody>
        	<row>
        		<entry><emphasis role="bold">xml</emphasis></entry>
        		<entry>Name of the element that the class is associated to.</entry>
        	</row>
        	<row>
	          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ns-uri</emphasis></entry>
	          <entry>Namespace URI</entry>
    	    </row>
	        <row>
	          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ns-prefix</emphasis></entry>
	          <entry>Desired namespace</entry>
	        </row>
	        <row>
	          <entry><emphasis role="bold">element-definition</emphasis></entry>
	          <entry><classname>True</classname> if the descriptor as created from a schema definition that 
	              was of type element (as opposed to a &lt;complexType&gt; definition). This 
	              only is useful in the context of source code generation.</entry>
	        </row>
	        <row>
	          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ldap-dn</emphasis></entry>
	          <entry>Not used for Castor XML</entry>
	        </row>
	        <row>
	          <entry><emphasis role="bold">ldap-oc</emphasis></entry>
	          <entry>Not used for Castor XML</entry>
            </row>
            </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        
        
        <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.mapto.samples">
            <title>&lt;map-to&gt; samples</title>
        
			<para>The following mapping fragment defines a &lt;map-to element for the 
			   <classname>OrderItem</classname> class, manually setting the element name to a value 
			   of <classname>'item'</classname>.</para>
			   
			<programlisting language="xml">
&lt;class name="myPackage.OrderItem">
   ...
   &lt;map-to xml="item" />
   ...
&lt;/class></programlisting>

			<para>The following mapping fragment instructs Castor to assign a namespace URI of 
			   <classname>http://castor.org/sample/mapping/</classname> to the &lt;item&gt; element, 
			   and use a namespace prefix of <classname>'castor'</classname> during un-/marshalling.</para>

			<programlisting language="xml">
&lt;class name="myPackage.OrderItem">
   ...
   &lt;map-to xml="item" <emphasis role="bold">ns-uri="http://castor.org/sample/mapping/"</emphasis>
           <emphasis role="bold">ns-prefix="castor"</emphasis>/>
   ...
&lt;/class></programlisting>

        <para>
        	When marshalling an <classname>OrderItem</classname> instance, this will yield the 
        	following XML:
        </para>

        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" ?>        
<castor:order-item xmlns:castor="http://castor.org/sample/mapping/" identity="12">
   <castor:order-quantity>100</castor:order-quantity>
</castor:order-item>]]></programlisting>
        
        </section>

        </section>

      <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.field"><title>The &lt;field> element</title>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT field ( description?, sql?, bind-xml?, ldap? )>
<!ATTLIST field
    name           NMTOKEN  #REQUIRED
    type           NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
    handler        NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
    required       ( true | false )  "false"
    direct         ( true | false )  "false"
    lazy           ( true | false )  "false"
    transient      ( true | false )  "false"
    nillable       ( true | false )  "false"
    container      ( true | false )  "false"
    get-method     NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
    set-method     NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
    create-method  NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
    collection     ( array | vector | hashtable | collection | set | map )  #IMPLIED>
        ]]></programlisting>

        <para><classname>&lt;field></classname> is used to describe a property of a Java object 
           we want to marshal/unmarshal. It gives:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>its identity ('name')</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>its type (infered from 'type' and 'collection')</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>its access method (infered from 'direct', 'get-method', 'set-method')</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>From this information, Castor is able to access a given property in the Java
           class.</para>

        <para>In order to determine the signature that Castor expects, there are two easy
          rules to apply.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">1. Determine &lt;type>.</emphasis></para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">If there is no 'collection' attribute</emphasis>, the &lt;type> is just the Java type
            specified in &lt;type_attribute> (the value of the 'type' attribute in the XML
            document). The value of &lt;type_attribute> can be a fully qualified Java object
            like 'java.lang.String' or one of the allowed short name:</para>

          	<table frame="all">
          	     <title>Type shortnames</title>
          		<tgroup cols="3">
          			<thead>
          				<row>
          					<entry>short name</entry>
          					<entry>Primitive type?</entry>
          					<entry>Java Class</entry>
          				</row>
          			</thead>
          			<tbody>
          				<row>
          					<entry>other</entry>
          					<entry>N</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Object</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>string</entry>
          					<entry>N</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.String</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>integer</entry>
          					<entry>Y</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Integer.TYPE</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>long</entry>
          					<entry>Y</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Long.TYPE</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>boolean</entry>
          					<entry>Y</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Boolean.TYPE</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>double</entry>
          					<entry>Y</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Double.TYPE</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>float</entry>
          					<entry>Y</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Float.TYPE</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>big-decimal</entry>
          					<entry>N</entry>
          					<entry>java.math.BigDecimal</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>byte</entry>
          					<entry>Y</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Byte.TYPE</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>date</entry>
          					<entry>N</entry>
          					<entry>java.util.Date</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>short</entry>
          					<entry>Y</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Short.TYPE</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>char</entry>
          					<entry>Y</entry>
          					<entry>java.lang.Character.TYPE</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>bytes</entry>
          					<entry>N</entry>
          					<entry>byte[]</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>chars</entry>
          					<entry>N</entry>
          					<entry>char[]</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>strings</entry>
          					<entry>N</entry>
          					<entry>String[]</entry>
          				</row>
          				<row>
          					<entry>locale</entry>
          					<entry>N</entry>
          					<entry>java.util.Locale</entry>
          				</row>
          				<!-- 
          					<row><entry>&lt;other&gt;</entry><entry></entry><entry>&lt;ConfigurableFieldHandler&gt;</entry></row>
          				-->
          			</tbody>
          		</tgroup>
          	</table>

          	<para>Castor will try to cast the data in the XML file in the proper Java type.</para>
            
<!-- 
            <para>If the value of the &lt;type_attribute&gt; is any other than the predefined ones in
            the list above, Castor tries to find a custom &lt;field-handler&gt; with a corresponding name.
            The Java type to which the data will be converted is defined by the field handler.
            The field handler must be defined in the mapping file. See 
            <a href="xml-fieldhandlers.html#Use-ConfigurableFieldHandler-for-more-flexibility">ConfigurableFieldHandler</a>
            for more detailed information.</para>
-->                        
            </listitem>


          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">If there is a collection attribute</emphasis>
	, you can use the following table:</para>

	<table frame="all">
	   <title>Type implementations</title>
		<tgroup cols="3">
			<thead>
				<row>
					<entry>name</entry>
					<entry>&lt;type></entry>
					<entry>default implementation</entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry>array</entry>
					<entry>&lt;type_attribute>[]</entry>
					<entry>&lt;type_attribute>[]</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>arraylist</entry>
					<entry>java.util.List</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Arraylist</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>vector</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Vector</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Vector</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>hashtable</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Hashtable</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Hashtable</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>collection</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Collection</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Arraylist</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>set</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Set</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Hashset</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>map</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Map</entry>
					<entry>java.util.Hashmap</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>sortedset</entry>
					<entry>java.util.SortedSet</entry>
					<entry>java.util.TreeSet</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</table>

	<para>The type of the object inside the collection is &lt;type_attribute>. The 'default
              implementation' is the type used if the object holding the collection is found
              to be null and need to be instantiated.</para>

            <para>For hashtable and maps (since 0.9.5.3), Castor will save both key and values.
               When marshalling output &lt;key&gt; and &lt;value&gt;
               elements. These names can be controlled by using a top-level or nested class mapping for
               the org.exolab.castor.mapping.MapItem class.
            </para>

            <para>Note: for backward compatibility with prior versions of Castor, the <emphasis role="italic">saveMapKeys</emphasis>
              property can be set to false in the castor.properties file.</para>

            <para>For versions prior to 0.9.5.3, hashtable and maps, Castor will save only the value
               during marshalling and during unmarshalling will add a map entry using the object as
               both the key and value, e.g. map.put(object, object).
            </para>
            
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>It is necessary to use a collection when the content model of the
          element expects more than one element of the specified type.</para>


        <para><emphasis role="bold">Determine the signature of the function</emphasis></para>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">If 'direct' is set to true</emphasis>, Castor expects to find a class variable with the
            given signature:</para>

          <programlisting language="java">
public &lt;type> &lt;name>;
          </programlisting></listitem>

          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">If 'direct' is set to false or omitted</emphasis>, Castor will access the property
              though accessor methods. Castor determines the signature of the accessors as
              follow: If the 'get-method' or 'set-method' attributes are supplied, it will
              try to find a function with the following signature:</para>

            <programlisting language="java">
public &lt;type> &lt;get-method>();
            </programlisting>
            <para>or</para>
            <programlisting language="java">
public void &lt;set-method>(&lt;type> value);
            </programlisting>

            <para>If 'get-method' and 'set-method' attributes are not provided, Castor will try to
              find the following function:</para>
            
            <programlisting language="java">
public &lt;type> get&lt;capitalized-name>();
            </programlisting>
            <para>or</para>
            <programlisting language="java">
public void set&lt;capitalized-name>(&lt;type> value);
            </programlisting>

            <para>&lt;capitalized-name> means that Castor takes the &lt;name> attribute and put its first
              letter in uppercase without modifying the other letters.</para>

            <para>The content of &lt;field> will contain the information on how to map this given
              field to SQL, XML, ...</para>
            </listitem>
          
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Exceptions concerning collection fields:</emphasis></para>
            
                <para>The default is to treat the 'get-method' as a simple getter returning 
                   the collection field, and the 'set-method' as a simple getter used to set
                   a new instance on the collection field.</para>

                <table frame="all">
                    <title>Collection field access</title>
                	<tgroup cols="2">
                		<thead>
                		  <row>
                			<entry>Parameter</entry>
                			<entry>Description</entry>
                		  </row>
                		</thead>
                		<tbody>
                			<row>
                				<entry>'get-method'</entry>
                				<entry>
                					<para>
                						If a 'get-method' is provided
                						for a collection field, Castor -
                						in adition to the default
                						behaviour described above - will
                						deviate from the standard case
                						for the following special
                						prefixes:
                					</para>

                					<programlisting language="java">
public Iterator iterate...();
                					</programlisting>

                					<para>
                						A 'get-method' starting with the
                						prefix '
                						<classname>iterate</classname>
                						' is treated as Iterator method
                						for the given collection field.
                					</para>

                					<programlisting language="java">
public Enumeration enum...();
                					</programlisting>

                					<para>
                						A 'get-method' starting with '
                						<classname>enum</classname>
                						' is treated as Enumeration
                						method for the given collection
                						field.
                					</para>
                				</entry>
                			</row>
                			<row>
                				<entry>'set-method'</entry>
                				<entry>
                					<para>
                						If 'set-method' is provided for
                						a collection field, Castor - in
                						addition to the default
                						behaviour described above - will
                						accept an 'add' prefix and
                						expect the following signature:
                					</para>

                					<programlisting language="java">
public void add...(&lt;type&gt; value);
                					</programlisting>

                					<para>
                						This method is called for each
                						collection element while
                						unmarshalling.
                					</para>
                				</entry>
                			</row>
                		</tbody>
                	</tgroup>
                </table>

            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <table frame="all">
            <title>Description of the attributes</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
                <row>
                <entry>Name</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>The field 'name' is required even if no such field exists in the
                    class. If 'direct' access is used, 'name' should be the name of 
                    a public instance member in the object to be mapped (the field 
                    must be public, not static and not transient). If no direct access 
                    and no 'get-/set-method' is specified, this name will be used to 
                    infer the name of the accessors methods.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>The Java type of the field. It is used to access the field. Castor 
                    will use this information to cast the XML information (like string 
                    into integer). It is also used to define the signature of the accessor 
                    methods. If a collection is specified, this is used to specify the 
                    type of the objects held by the collection. See description
                    above for more details.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">required</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>A field can be optional or required.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">nillable</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>A field can be of content '<classname>nil</classname>'.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">transient</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>If true, this field will be ignored during the marshalling. This 
                    is usefull when used together with the auto-complete="true"
                    option.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">direct</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>If true, Castor will expect a public variable in the containing class
                    and will access it directly (for both reading and writing).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">container</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>Indicates whether the field should be treated as a container, 
                    i.e. only it's fields should be persisted, but not the containing
                    class itself. In this case, the container attribute should be set 
                    to true (supported in Castor XML only).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">collection</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>If a parent expects more than one occurrence of one of its 
                    element, it is necessary to specify which collection Castor will 
                    use to handle them. The type specified is used to define the type 
                    of the content inside the collection.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">get-method</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>Optional name of the 'get method' Castor should use. If this attribute 
                    is not set and the set-method attribute is not set, then Castor will try 
                    to infer the name of this method with the algorithm described above.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">set-method</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>Optional name of the 'set method' Castor should use. If this attribute 
                    is not set and the get-method attribute is not set, then Castor will try 
                    to infer the name of this method with the algorithm described above.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">create-method</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>Optionally defines a factory method for the instantiation of a FieldHandler</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">handler</emphasis></entry>
                <entry>If present, specifies one of the following:
                    <itemizedlist>
                       <listitem><para>The fully-qualified class name of a custom field handler implementation, or</para></listitem>
                       <listitem><para>The (short) name of a 
                           <ulink url="http://www.castor.org/xml-fieldhandlers.html#Use-ConfigurableFieldHandler-for-more-flexibility">configurable field handler</ulink>
                           definition.</para></listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></entry>
            </row>
            </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>

      </section>

        
         <section><title>Description of the content</title>

         <para>
             In the case of XML mapping, the content of a field element should be one and
             only one <emphasis role="bold">&lt;bind-xml></emphasis> element describing how this given field will be mapped into the
             XML document.
         </para>
          
          <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.field.constructorarguments"><title>Mapping constructor arguments (since 0.9.5)</title>
            <para>
               Starting with release 0.9.5, for <emphasis role="italic">attribute</emphasis> 
               mapped fields, support has been added to map a constructor field using 
               the <classname>set-method</classname> attribute.
            </para>
            <para>
               To specify that a field (mapped to an attribute) should be used as a constructor 
               argument during object initialization, please specify a <classname>set-method</classname> attribute on the
               <classname>&lt;field&gt;</classname> mapping and use "%1" - "%9" as the value of the
               <classname>set-method</classname> attribute.
            </para>
            <para>For example:</para>
            <programlisting language="java">
&lt;field name="foo" <emphasis role="bold">set-method="%1"</emphasis> get-method="getFoo" type="string"&gt;
   &lt;bind-xml node="attribute"/&gt;
&lt;/field&gt;</programlisting>
               
           <para>
              Note that because the <classname>set-method</classname> is specified, the <classname>get-method</classname> also 
              must be specified.
           </para>
	       <para>
	          <emphasis role="bold">Tip</emphasis>: the <olink targetdoc="xml-howto.xml">XML HOW-TO section</olink> has a HOW-TO document for 
	          mapping constructor arguments, incl. a fully working mapping.
	       </para>
          </section>
          
       	<section><title>Sample 1: Defining a custom field handler</title>
        
			<para>The following mapping fragment defines a <classname>&lt;field&gt;</classname> element for the 
			   <classname>member</classname> property of the <classname>org.some.package.Root</classname> class, 
			   specifying a custom <api class="org.exolab.castor.mapping.FieldHandler">FieldHandler</api>
			   implementation.</para>
				   
			<programlisting language="java">
&lt;class name="org.some.package.Root"&gt;
   &lt;field name="member" type="string" <emphasis role="bold">handler="org.some.package.CustomFieldHandlerImpl"</emphasis>/&gt;
&lt;/class&gt;</programlisting>

		</section>
	   
       	<section><title>Sample 2: Defining a custom configurable field handler</title>
   			<para>
   			   The same custom field handler as in the previous sample can be defined 
   			   with a separate configurable &lt;field-handler&gt; definition, where additional 
   			   configuration can be provided.
   			</para>
	   			
   			<programlisting language="java">
&lt;field-handler <emphasis role="bold">name="myHandler"</emphasis> class="org.some.package.CustomFieldHandlerImpl"&gt;
   &lt;param name="date-format" value="yyyyMMddHHmmss"/&gt;
&lt;/field-handler&gt;</programlisting>
	   			
   			<para>
   				and subsequently be referred to by its <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis> as shown in the 
   				following field mapping:
   			</para>
	
   			<programlisting language="java">
&lt;class name="org.some.package.Root"&gt;
   &lt;field name="member" type="string" <emphasis role="bold">handler="myHandler"</emphasis>/&gt;
&lt;/class&gt;</programlisting>
        
        </section>

        <section><title>Sample 3: Using the container attribute</title>
        
            <para>
               Assume you have a class mapping for a class <classname>Order</classname> which defines -
               amongst others - a field mapping as follows, where the field <classname>item</classname>
               refers to an instance of a class <classname>Item</classname>.
            </para>
                
            <programlisting language="java">
&lt;class name="some.example.Order"&gt;
            
   ...
   &lt;field name="item" type="some.example.Item" &gt;
      &lt;bind-xml&gt; name="item" node="element" /&gt;
   &lt;/field&gt;
   ...
&lt;/class&gt;

&lt;class name="some.example.Item"&gt;
   &lt;field name="id" type="long" /&gt;
   &lt;field name="description" type="string" /&gt;
&lt;/class&gt;</programlisting>

            <para>
                Marshalling an instance of <classname>Order</classname> would produce XML as follows:
            </para>
            
            <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;order&gt;
    ...
    &lt;item&gt;
        &lt;id&gt;100&lt;/id&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;...&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/item&gt;
&lt;/order&gt;</programlisting>

           <para>
               If you do not want the <classname>Item</classname> instance to be marshalled,
               but only its fields, change the field mapping for the <classname>item</classname>
               member to be as follows:
           </para>

           <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;field name="item" type="some.example.Item" container="false" &gt;
   &lt;bind-xml&gt; name="item" node="element" /&gt;
&lt;/field&gt;</programlisting>        

            <para>
                The resulting XML would look as follows:
            </para>
            
            <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;order&gt;
    ...
    &lt;id&gt;100&lt;/id&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;...&lt;/description&gt;
&lt;/order&gt;</programlisting>
        
        </section>
          
      </section>

      <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.bindxml"><title>The &lt;bind-xml> element</title>

        <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.bindxml.grammar"><title>Grammar</title>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT bind-xml (class?, property*)>
<!ATTLIST bind-xml
          name     NMTOKEN     #IMPLIED
          type     NMTOKEN     #IMPLIED
          location CDATA       #IMPLIED
          matches  NMTOKENS    #IMPLIED
          QName-prefix NMTOKEN #IMPLIED
          reference   ( true | false ) "false"
          node        ( attribute | element | text )    #IMPLIED
          auto-naming ( deriveByClass | deriveByField ) #IMPLIED
          transient   ( true | false ) "false">]]></programlisting>

        <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.bindxml.definition"><title>Definiton</title>
        
        <para>
            The <classname>&lt;bind-xml></classname> element is used to describe how a given Java field 
                should appear in an XML document. It is used both for marshalling 
                and unmarshalling.
        </para>
        </section>
        </section>

        <table frame="all">
            <title>Description of the attributes</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
        	<row>
        		<entry><emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis></entry>
        		<entry>The name of the element or attribute.
		              <note><para>The name is a QName, and a namespace prefix may be used to indicate the
		              element or attribute belongs to a certain namespace. Note the prefix is not
		              preserved or used during marshalling, it's simply used for
		              qualification of which namespace the element or attribute belongs.</para></note></entry>
		    </row>
		    <row>
		    	<entry><emphasis role="bold">auto-naming</emphasis></entry>
		    	<entry>If no name is specified, this attribute controls how castor will 
		    	    automatically create a name for the field. Normally, the name is 
		    	    created using the field name, however many times it is necessary 
		    	    to create the name by using the class type instead (such as
            		heterogenenous collections).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            	<entry><emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis></entry>
            	<entry>XML Schema type (of the value of this field) that requires specific 
            	    handling in the Castor Marshalling Framework (such as 'QName' for 
            	    instance).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            	<entry><emphasis role="bold">location</emphasis> (since 0.9.4.4)</entry>
            	<entry>Allows the user to specify the "sub-path" for which the value
                    should be marshalled to and from. This is useful for "wrapping" values in 
                    elements or for mapping values that appear on sub-elements to the 
                    current "element" represented by the class mapping. For more information,
                    see the <link linkend="xml.mapping.mappingfile.locationattribute">Location attribute</link> below.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            	<entry><emphasis role="bold">QName-prefix</emphasis></entry>
            	<entry>When the field represents a QName value, a prefix can be provided that
                    is used when marshalling value of type QName. More information on the 
                    use of 'QName-prefix' can be found in the 
                    <ulink url="http://www.castor.org/SourceGeneratorUser.pdf">SourceGenerator Documentation</ulink></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            	<entry><emphasis role="bold">reference</emphasis></entry>
            	<entry>Indicates if this field has to be treated as a reference by the 
            	    unmarshaller. In order to work properly, you must specify the node 
            	    type to 'attribute' for both the 'id' and the 'reference'. In 
            	    newer versions of Castor, 'element' node for reference is allowed. 
            	    Remember to make sure that an <emphasis role="italic">identity</emphasis> field is specified
                    on the <classname>&lt;class&gt;</classname> mapping for the object type being 
                    referenced so that Castor knows what the object's identity is.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            	<entry><emphasis role="bold">matches</emphasis></entry>
            	<entry>Allows overriding the matches rules for the name of the element. It 
            	    is a standard regular expression and will be used instead of the 'name'
            	    field. A '*' will match any xml name, however it will only be matched 
            	    if no other field exists that matches the xml name.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            	<entry><emphasis role="bold">node</emphasis></entry>
            	<entry>Indicates if the name corresponds to an attribute, an element,
                    or text content. By default, primitive types are assumed to be 
                    an attribute, otherwise the node is assumed to be an elemen</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            	<entry><emphasis role="bold">transient</emphasis></entry>
            	<entry>Allows for making this field transient for XML. The default value is 
            	    inherited from the &lt;field&gt; element.</entry>
            </row>
            </tbody>
            </tgroup>
		</table>
		
		
		<section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.bindxml.nestedclassmapping"><title>Nested class mapping</title>
		
          <para>Since 0.9.5.3, the bind-xml element supports a nested class mapping, which 
             is often useful when needing to specify more than one mapping for a 
             particular class. A good example of this is when mapping Hashtable/HashMap/Map.</para>
              
          <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<bind-xml ...>
   <class name="org.exolab.castor.mapping.MapItem">
      <field name="key" type="java.lang.String">
        <bind-xml name="id"/>
      </field>
      <field name="value" type="com.acme.Foo"/>
   </class>
</bind-xml>]]></programlisting>

		</section>
		
      </section>

    </section>
    
    <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.bindxml.usagepattern"><title>Usage Pattern</title>

      <para>Here is an example of how Castor Mapping can be used. We want to map an XML
        document like the following one (called 'order.xml').
        model.</para>

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<Order reference="12343-AHSHE-314159">
  <Client>
    <Name>Jean Smith</Name>
    <Address>2000, Alameda de las Pulgas, San Mateo, CA 94403</Address>
  </Client>

  <Item reference="RF-0001">
    <Description>Stuffed Penguin</Description>
    <Quantity>10</Quantity>
    <UnitPrice>8.95</UnitPrice>
  </Item>

  <Item reference="RF-0034">
    <Description>Chocolate</Description>
    <Quantity5</Quantity>
    <UnitPrice>28.50</UnitPrice>
  </Item>

  <Item reference="RF-3341">
     <Description>Cookie</Description>
     <Quantity>30</Quantity>
     <UnitPrice>0.85</UnitPrice>
  </Item>
</Order>]]></programlisting>

      <para>Into the following object model composed of 3 classes:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">MyOrder:</emphasis> represent an order</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Client:</emphasis> used to store information on the client</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Item:</emphasis> used to store item in an order</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The sources of these classes follow.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">
import java.util.Vector;
import java.util.Enumeration;

public class MyOrder {

    private String _ref;
    private ClientData _client;
    private Vector _items;
    private float _total;

    public void setReference(String ref) {
        _ref = ref;
    }

    public String getReference() {
        return _ref;
    }

    public void setClientData(ClientData client) {
        _client = client;
    }

    public ClientData getClientData() {
        return _client;
    }

    public void setItemsList(Vector items) {
        _items = items;
    }

    public Vector getItemsList() {
        return _items;
    }


    public void setTotal(float total) {
        _total = total;
    }

    public float getTotal() {
        return _total;
    }

    // Do some processing on the data
    public float getTotalPrice() {
        float total = 0.0f;

        for (Enumeration e = _items.elements() ; e.hasMoreElements() ;) {
            Item item = (Item) e.nextElement();
            total += item._quantity * item._unitPrice;
        }

        return total;
    }
}</programlisting>

      <programlisting language="java">
public class ClientData {

    private String _name;
    private String _address;

    public void setName(String name) {
        _name = name;
    }

    public String getName() {
        return _name;
    }

    public void setAddress(String address) {
        _address = address;
    }

    public String getAddress() {
        return _address;
    }
}</programlisting>

      <programlisting language="java">
public class Item {
    public String _reference;
    public int    _quantity;
    public float  _unitPrice;
    public String _description;
}</programlisting>

      <para>The XML document and the java object model can be connected by using the
        following mapping file:</para>

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE mapping PUBLIC "-//EXOLAB/Castor Mapping DTD Version 1.0//EN"
                         "http://castor.org/mapping.dtd">

<mapping>
  <class name="MyOrder">
    <map-to xml="Order"/>

    <field name="Reference"
           type="java.lang.String">
      <bind-xml name="reference" node="attribute"/>
    </field>

    <field name="Total"
           type="float">
      <bind-xml name="total-price" node="attribute"/>
    </field>

    <field name="ClientData"
           type="ClientData">
      <bind-xml name="Client"/>
    </field>

    <field name="ItemsList"
           type="Item"
              collection="vector">
      <bind-xml name="Item"/>
    </field>
  </class>

  <class name="ClientData">
    <field name="Name"
           type="java.lang.String">
      <bind-xml name="Name" node="element"/>
    </field>

    <field name="Address"
           type="java.lang.String">
      <bind-xml name="Address" node="element"/>
    </field>
  </class>

  <class name="Item">
    <field name="_reference"
           type="java.lang.String"
           direct="true">
      <bind-xml name="reference" node="attribute"/>
    </field>

    <field name="_quantity"
           type="integer"
           direct="true">
      <bind-xml name="Quantity" node="element"/>
    </field>

    <field name="_unitPrice"
           type="float"
           direct="true">
      <bind-xml name="UnitPrice" node="element"/>
    </field>

    <field name="_description"
           type="string"
           direct="true">
      <bind-xml name="Description" node="element"/>
    </field>
  </class>

</mapping>]]></programlisting>

      <para>The following class is an example of how to use Castor XML Mapping to
        manipulate the file 'order.xml'. It unmarshals the document 'order.xml',
        computes the total price, sets the total price in the java object and
        marshals the object model back into XML with the calculated price.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">
import org.exolab.castor.mapping.Mapping;
import org.exolab.castor.mapping.MappingException;

import org.exolab.castor.xml.Unmarshaller;
import org.exolab.castor.xml.Marshaller;

import java.io.IOException;
import java.io.FileReader;
import java.io.OutputStreamWriter;

import org.xml.sax.InputSource;

public class main {

    public static void main(String args[]) {

        Mapping      mapping = new Mapping();

        try {
            // 1. Load the mapping information from the file
            mapping.loadMapping( "mapping.xml" );

            // 2. Unmarshal the data
            Unmarshaller unmar = new Unmarshaller(mapping);
            MyOrder order = (MyOrder)unmar.unmarshal(new InputSource(new FileReader("order.xml")));

            // 3. Do some processing on the data
            float total = order.getTotalPrice();
            System.out.println("Order total price = " + total);
            order.setTotal(total);

            // 4. marshal the data with the total price back and print the XML in the console
            Marshaller marshaller = new Marshaller(new OutputStreamWriter(System.out));
            marshaller.setMapping(mapping);
            marshaller.marshal(order);

        } catch (Exception e) {
            System.out.println(e);
            return;
        }
    }
}
       </programlisting>

    </section>

    <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.xsitype"><title>xsi:type</title>

      <para>Ordinarily, a mapping will only reference types that are concrete classes (i.e. not interfaces
        nor abstract classes).  The reason is that to unmarshal a type requires instantiating it and
        one cannot instantiate an interface.  However, in many real situations, object models depend
        on the use of interfaces.  Many class properties are defined to have interface types to support
        the ability to swap implementations.  This is often the case in frameworks.</para>

      <para>The problem is that a different mapping must be used each time the same model is to be
       used to marshal/unmarshal an implementation that uses different concrete types.  This is
       not convenient.  The mapping should represent the model and the specific concrete type
       used to unmarshal a document is a configuration parameter; it should be specified in the
       instance document to be unmarshalled, not the mapping.</para>

      <para>For example, assume a very simple object model of an engine that has one property that
      is a processor:</para>

            <programlisting language="java">
public interface IProcessor {
    public void process();
}

public class Engine {
    private IProcessor processor;
    public IProcessor getProcessor() {
        return processor;
    }
    public void setProcessor(IProcessor processor) {
        this.processor = processor;
    }
}
            </programlisting>

      <para>A typical mapping file for such a design may be:</para>

            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[  
<mapping>
    <class name="Engine">
        <map-to xml="engine" />

        <field name="processor" type="IProcessor" required="true">
           <bind-xml name="processor" node="element" />
        </field>

     </class>
  </mapping>]]></programlisting>

      <para>It is possible to use such a mapping and still have the marshal/unmarshal process work
       by specifying the concrete implementation of IProcessor in the document to be unmarshalled,
       using the xsi:type attribute, as follows:</para>

            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
  <engine>
     <processor xsi:type="java:com.abc.MyProcessor" />
  </engine>
            ]]></programlisting>

      <para>In this manner, one is still able to maintain only a single mapping, but vary the
      manner in which the document is unmarshalled from one instance document to the next.
      This flexibility is powerful because it enables the support of polymorphism within
      the castor xml marshalling framework.</para>

      <para>Suppose we wanted the following XML instead:</para>
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
  <engine>
     <myProcessor/>
  </engine>]]></programlisting>

      <para>In the above output our XML name changed to match the type of the class used instead of
         relying on the xsi:type attribute. This can be achieved by modifying the mapping
         file as such:
      </para>
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
  <mapping>
     <class name="Engine">
        <map-to xml="engine" />
        <field name="processor" type="IProcessor" required="true">
           <bind-xml auto-naming="deriveByClass" node="element" />
        </field>
     </class>

     <class name="MyProcessor">
        <map-to xml="myProcessor" />
     </class>

  </mapping>]]></programlisting>

    </section>

    <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.locationattribute"><title>Location attribute</title>

       <para>Since 0.9.5</para>

       <para>
          The location attribute allows the user to map fields from nested
          elements or specify a wrapper element for a given field. Wrapper
          elements are simply elements which appear in the XML instance, but
          do not have a direct mapping to an object or field within the
          object model.
        </para>
        <para>
          For example to map an instance of the following class:
          </para>
          <programlisting language="java">
public class Foo {

    private Bar bar = null;

    public Foo();

    public getBar() {
        return bar;
    }

    public void setBar(Bar bar) {
        this.bar = bar;
    }
}</programlisting>
    <para>
          into the following XML instance:
    </para>
          <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<foo>;
   <abc>
      <bar>...</bar>
   </abc>
</foo>]]></programlisting>
<para>
          <emphasis role="italic">(notice that an 'abc' field doesn't exist in the Bar class)</emphasis>
          One would use the following mapping:</para>
          <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
   ...
   &lt;class name="Foo"&gt;
      &lt;field name="bar" type="Bar"&gt;
         &lt;bind-xml name="bar" <emphasis role="bold">location="abc"</emphasis>/&gt;
      &lt;/field&gt;
   &lt;/class&gt;
   ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>
          Note the "location" attribute. The value of this attribute is the name
          of the wrapper element. To use more than one wrapper element, the name
          is separated by a forward-slash as such:
</para>
          <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<bind-xml name="bar" location="abc/xyz" />]]></programlisting>
<para>
          Note that the name of the element is not part of the location itself and
          that the location is always relative to the class in which the field is
          being defined.

          This works for attributes also:
</para>
          <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<bind-xml name="bar" location="abc" node="attribute" />]]></programlisting>
          <para>
          will produce the following:
</para>
          <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<foo>
   <abc bar="..."/>;
</foo>]]></programlisting>

    </section>

    <section id="xml.mapping.mappingfile.tips"><title>Tips</title>
       <para>Some helpful hints...</para>
       <section><title>Automatically create a mapping file</title>
       <para>
         Castor comes with a tool that can automatically create a mapping from
         class files. Please see the <ulink url="xml.faq">XML FAQ</ulink> for more
         information.
       </para>
       </section>
       <section><title>Create your own FieldHandler</title>
       <para>
          Sometimes to handle complex situations you'll need to create your
          own FieldHandler. Normally a FieldHandler deals with a specific class
          and field, however generic, reusable FieldHandlers can also be created
          by extending org.exolab.castor.mapping.GeneralizedFieldHandler or
          org.exolab.castor.mapping.AbstractFieldHandler.
          The FieldHandler can be specified on the &lt;field&gt; element.
       </para>
       <para>
          For more information on writing a custom FieldHandler please
          see the following:
          <olink targetdoc="xml-fieldhandlers.xml">XML FieldHandlers</olink>.
       </para>
       </section>
       <section><title>Mapping constructor arguments (since 0.9.5)</title>
       <para>
          You may map any attributes to constructor arguments. For more information
          on how to map constructor arguments see the information available
          in the section on <ulink url="xml.mapping.mappingfile.field.constructorarguments">set-method</ulink>
          above.
       </para>
       <para>Please note that mapping <emphasis role="bold">elements</emphasis> to constructor arguments is 
          not yet supported.
       </para>
       <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Tip</emphasis>: the <ulink url="xml.how-to">XML HOW-TO section</ulink> has a HOW-TO document for 
          mapping constructor arguments.
       </para>
       </section>
       <section><title>Preventing Castor from checking for a default constructor (since 0.9.5)</title>
       <para>
          Sometimes it's useful to prevent Castor from checking for a default constructor,
          such as when trying to write a mapping for an interface or type-safe enum. You can use the
          "undocumented" verify-constructable="false" attribute on the &lt;class&gt; element to
          prevent Castor from looking for the default constructor.
       </para>
       </section>

       <section><title>Type safe enumeration mapping (since 0.9.5)</title>
      <para>
          While you can always use your own custom FieldHandler for handling type-safe enumeration
          classes, Castor does have a built-in approach to dealing with these types of classes.
          If the type-safe enum class has a <emphasis role="bold">public static &lt;type&gt; valueOf(String)</emphasis> method
          Castor will call that method so that the proper instance of the enumeration is returned.
          Note: You'll also need to disable the default constructor check in the mapping file
          (see section 7.4 above to see more on this).
       </para>
       </section>


    </section>
</section>
