<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.org/tutorial/how-to-setup-castor-project-in-eclipse.xml">
  <properties>
    <title>How to setup Castor project in eclipse</title>
    <abstract>
       Short decription of how to check out the latest Castor code from SVN into an eclipse project.
    </abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <title>How to setup Castor project in eclipse</title>
    <header></header>
    
    <section title="Introduction">
    
      <p>
        Are you just interested in how Castor source looks like, want to report a bug or enhancement request
        or like to contribute to the project? The first step we suggest you to do is to setup a Castor project
        with eclipse IDE. As we use eclipse to work at Castor, there is everything in place to work with
        eclipse. While you are free to use other IDE's, you will need to configure things yourself
        with them.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="Prerequisites">
      <ul>
        <li>Download and install <a href="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp"><b>JDK 1.5 or newer</b></a></li>
        <li>Download and install <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/downloads/index.php"><b>Eclipse 3.x</b></a></li>
        <li>Install the latest <a href="http://subclipse.tigris.org/download.html"><b>Subclipse eclipse plugin</b></a></li>
        <li>Optionally install the latest <a href="http://eclipse-cs.sourceforge.net/"><b>CheckStyle eclipse plugin</b></a></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Create Project">
      <ul>
        <li>Create a New Project in eclipse from <b>File -> New -> Projects</b></li>
        <li>Select <b>"Checkout Projects from SVN"</b> in <b>"SVN"</b> from <b>"Select a wizard"</b>
          window and click <b>Next</b> (this option will only come if you have installed the subclipse plugin)</li>
        <li>Select <b>"Create a new repository location"</b> and click <b>Next</b></li>
        <li>Enter the URL <b>"https://svn.codehaus.org/castor/castor"</b> and click <b>Next</b></li>
        <li>Select the folder <b>"trunk"</b> from the list and click <b>Next</b></li>
        <li>In <b>"Check Out As"</b> window the name of the project will be <b>"castor"</b> then click <b>Next</b></li>
        <li>At last, you can choose the workspace and click <b>Finish</b></li>
        <li>You can see castor project in your <b>"Project Navigator" of eclipse</b></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Troubleshooting">
      <p><b>If you have trouble with Subclipse behind a proxy server:</b> In Windows development environment, open 
        the file: <b>C:\Documents and Settings\MyUserId\Application Data\Subversion\servers</b> in text editor. Near
        the bottom of that file is a [global] section with http-proxy-host and http-proxy-port (user and password also)
        settings. Uncommented those lines, modified them for your proxy server and go back to the SVN Repository view
        in Eclipse. This should solve the problem.</p>  
    </section>        
  </body>
</document>
