<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/conf-lib.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Configuration, Libraries and Building Castor</title>

    <section title="The Castor configuration file">

      <p>Castor uses a configuration file for environmental properties that are
         shared across all the Castor sub systems. The configuration file is
         specified as a Java properties file with the name <tt>castor.properties</tt>.</p>

      <p>The Castor JAR includes a default configuration file. A configuration
         file in the Java library directory (e.g. <tt>/jdk1.2/lib</tt>) can be used to
         override the default configuration file with system wide properties.
         In addition, a configuration file can be placed in the classpath and
         will override both the system wide properties and default
         configuration.</p>

      <p>When running the provided examples, Castor will use the configuration
         file located in the examples directory which specifies additional
         debugging information and pretty printing of all produced XML
         documents.</p>

      <p>The following properties are currently supported in the configuration
         file:</p>
<pre>
  # Defines the default XML parser to be used by castor
  # The parser must implement org.xml.sax.Parser
  #
  org.exolab.castor.parser=org.apache.xerces.parsers.SAXParser

  # Defines the default XML serializer to be used by castor
  # The serializer must implement org.apache.xml.serialize.Serializer
  #
  org.exolab.castor.serializer=org.apache.xml.serialize.XMLSerializer

  # True if all documents should be indented on output by default
  #
  org.exolab.castor.indent=false

  # True if all documents should be validated on input by default
  #
  org.exolab.castor.validation=true

  # Comma separated list of SAX 2 features that should be enabled
  # for the default parser
  #
  org.exolab.castor.features=

  # True if should produce verbose messages
  #
  org.exolab.castor.debug=false

  # List of collection handlers for Java 1.1 and Java 1.2 run-times
  #
  org.exolab.castor.mapping.collections=\
    org.exolab.castor.mapping.loader.J1CollectionHandlers,\
    org.exolab.castor.mapping.loader.J2CollectionHandlers

  # List of persistence factories for the supported database servers
  #
  org.exolab.castor.jdo.engines=\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.OracleFactory,\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.PostgreSQLFactory,\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.SybaseFactory,\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.SQLServerFactory,\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.DB2Factory,\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.GenericFactory

  # List of key generator factories 
  #
  org.exolab.castor.jdo.keyGeneratorFactories=\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.MaxKeyGeneratorFactory,\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.HighLowKeyGeneratorFactory,\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.IdentityKeyGeneratorFactory,\
    org.exolab.castor.jdo.drivers.SequenceKeyGeneratorFactory

  # Collection handlers for the source code generator
  #
  org.exolab.castor.builder.type.j2=\
    org.exolab.castor.builder.FieldInfoFactoryJ2
  org.exolab.castor.builder.type.j1=\
    org.exolab.castor.builder.FieldInfoFactory
  org.exolab.castor.builder.type.odmg=\
    org.exolab.castor.builder.FieldInfoFactoryODMG30

  # Default time zone to apply to dates/times fetched from database fields, if not
  # already part of the data.  Specify same format as in java.util.TimeZone.getTimeZone, or
  # an empty string to use the computer's local time zone. Please see
  # http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitzone for detailed information about time zones.
  #
  org.exolab.castor.jdo.defaultTimeZone=
  #org.exolab.castor.jdo.defaultTimeZone=GMT-8:00

</pre>
    </section>

    <section title="Dependent Libraries">

      <p>JARs required to build Castor and dependencies for various packages
         are contained in the <tt>lib</tt> directory. JARs required for
         distribution are marked with bold text:</p>

         <table cellpadding="4" border="1">
           <tr><td>ant.jar</td><td>The Ant build tool</td></tr>
           <tr><td><b>jdbc-se2.0.jar</b></td><td>JDBC 2.0 standard extension (JDO)</td></tr>
           <tr><td><b>jndi.jar</b></td><td>The JNDI API (DSML/JNDI)</td></tr>
           <tr><td><b>jta1.0.1.jar</b></td><td>The JTA API (transactions)</td></tr>
           <tr><td>jtf-0.1.jar</td><td>The Java Testing Framework</td></tr>
           <tr><td><b>ldapjdk.jar</b></td><td>Mozilla Directory SDK (DSML/MDS)</td></tr>
           <tr><td>ldapsp.jar</td><td>JNDI LDAP service provider from Mozilla</td></tr>
           <tr><td>postgresql-6.3.jar</td><td>PostgreSQL 6.3 driver with DataSource
                                              support (used in default example)</td></tr>
           <tr><td>servlet.jar</td><td>Used by the Servlet examples</td></tr>
           <tr><td><b>xerces.jar</b></td><td>Xerces XML library</td></tr>
           <tr><td>xslp.jar</td><td>XSL processor, used for documentation</td></tr>
         </table>

      <section title="Castor XML">
        <p>Castor XML is dependent on the latest release of Xerces available from
           the library directory and XML Apache. Other XML parser may be used
           instead of Xerces, however, Xerces is required to provide the XML
           serializer package for XML document production.</p>
      </section>

      <section title="Castor JDO">
        <p>Castor JDO uses Castor XML for processing the XML mapping file and
           has the same dependency on Xerces.</p>

        <p>In addition applications that use Castor JDO must include
           <tt>jdbc-se2.0.jar</tt> or any alternative JAR that includes the
           <tt>javax.sql.DataSource</tt> interface.</p>

        <p>The JDO example uses the PostgreSQL database and depends on the
           provided JDBC driver which includes <tt>javax.sql.DataSource</tt> support.
           This driver is not required for distribution or if a different
           database server is used.</p>
      </section>

      <section title="Castor DSML">
        <p>Castor DSML is dependent on the latest release of Xerces available from
           the library directory and XML Apache. Other XML parser may be used
           instead of Xerces, however, Xerces is required to provide the XML
           serializer package for XML document production.</p>

        <p>Castor DSML has two implementations, one that uses JNDI and one that
           uses the Mozilla Directory SDK. Applications that use the JNDI package
           (<tt>org.exolab.castor.dsml.jndi</tt>) are required to include <tt>jndi.jar</tt>
           or any alternative JAR that includes the JNDI 1.2 API. Applications that use
           the Mozilla Directory SDK (<tt>org.exolab.castor.dsml.mozilla</tt>) are required
           to include <tt>ldapjdk.jar</tt> or any alternative JAR that includes version 4.0
           of the Mozilla Directory SDK.</p>

        <p>We recommend using the Mozilla Directory SDK as the JNDI LDAP service
           provider and have positive experience using it with OpenLDAP. The JNDI
           LDAP service provider is included in the <tt>ldapsp.jar</tt>.</p>
     </section>

   </section>

   <section title="Building Castor">

     <p>Castor uses Ant as the build environment. To build Castor from the
        source run <tt>build.sh</tt> or <tt>build.bat</tt> in the Castor root
        directory with one (or any) of the following targets:</p>

         <table cellpadding="4" border="1">
           <tr><td>targets</td><td>Lists the build targets</td></tr>
           <tr><td>clean</td><td>Cleans the build and distribution directories</td></tr>
           <tr><td>all</td><td>Cleans and builds all the packages and examples</td></tr>
           <tr><td>release</td><td>Cleans and builds all the release packages
                                  (JAR, source, doc, tarball) in the dist directory</td></tr>
           <tr><td>main</td><td>Builds the main packages (including debugging info)</td></tr>
           <tr><td>examples</td><td>Builds the example packages (including debugging info)</td></tr>
           <tr><td>tests</td><td>Builds the test packages (including debugging info)</td></tr>
           <tr><td>jar</td><td>Builds the binary JAR in the dist directory</td></tr>
           <tr><td>doc</td><td>Builds the documentation</td></tr>
           <tr><td>api</td><td>Builds the API JavaDocs</td></tr>
           <tr><td>javadoc</td><td>Builds the full JavaDocs</td></tr>
           <tr><td>source</td><td>Builds the source tarball in the dist directory</td></tr>
           <tr><td>tarball</td><td>Builds the binary distribution in the dist directory</td></tr>
           <tr><td>cvs</td><td>Update the sources from the CVS</td></tr>
         </table>

     <p>The tarball will includes the Castor JAR, all dependent library
        JARs, readme and license files, and all DTDs and XML schemas in
        the <tt>schema</tt> directory.</p>

   </section>

   <section title="Directory Structure">

         <table cellpadding="4" border="1">
           <tr><td>src/main</td><td>The source base for all the Castor modules</td></tr>
           <tr><td>src/doc</td><td>Documentation (in XML form)</td></tr>
           <tr><td>src/schema</td><td>DTD and XML schema for Castor mapping files</td></tr>
           <tr><td>src/examples</td><td>Examples for the various packages</td></tr>
           <tr><td>src/tests</td><td>Test cases for the various packages</td></tr>
           <tr><td>src/etc</td><td>Additional files that are not part of the code base</td></tr>
           <tr><td>lib</td><td>JARs required to build Castor and distributable JARs</td></tr>
           <tr><td>build/classes</td><td>When using Ant the Java classes are build in this directory</td></tr>
           <tr><td>build/doc</td><td>When using Ant the HTML documentation is build in this directory</td></tr>
           <tr><td>build/examples</td><td>When using the examples are build in this directory</td></tr>
           <tr><td>build/test</td><td>When using the test cases are build in this directory</td></tr>
           <tr><td>dist</td><td>The distribution directory</td></tr>
         </table>

   </section>

  </body>
</document>









