<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.codehaus.org/changes.xml">
    <properties>
        <title>Recent changes to the HTML documentation</title>
        <author email="werner DOT guttmann AT gmx DOT net">Werner Guttmann</author>
        <abstract>
            Outlines recent changes to the HTML documentation.
        </abstract>
        <status>Final</status>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <title>Recent changes to the HTML documentation</title>
        
        <section title="Castor 1.0.3">
        
        	<section title="Additions">
        	
        		<ul>
        			<li>Added HOW-TO on mapping a <tt>java.util.List</tt> as 
        			    a root element.</li>
        		</ul>
        		
        	</section>
        	
        	<section title="Changes/improvements">
        	
        		<ul>
        			<li>Moved all documentation for the Castor XML code generator
        			    to its own main section named <i>Castor CodeGen</i>.</li>
        			<li>Improved documentation for the Ant task definition for the
        			    Castor XML code generator.</li>
        			<li>Moved documentation on code generator bindings into a
        			    <a href="srcgen-binding.html">separate page</a>.</li>
        			<li>Moved documentation on code generator properties into a
        			    <a href="srcgen-properties.html">separate page</a>.</li>
        		</ul>
        		
        	</section>
        	
        </section>
        
        <section title="Castor 1.0.2 and earlier">

        <section title="Additions">
        
            <ul>
                <li>Added a <a href="jdo-self-executable-examples.html">page</a>
                    describing how to execute the new self-executable
                    Castor JDO samples to the Castor JDO section. (Castor JDO)</li>
                <li>Added HOW-TO document on preparing a (unified) patch for
                    submission. (Castor XML)</li>
                <li>Added HOW-TO document on mapping a collection of elements. (Castor XML)</li>
                <li>Added HOW-TO document on mapping a map/hashtable of elements. (Castor XML)</li>
                <li>Added a new page full of information relevant for people that want to 
                    contribute in one way or the other to the project.</li>
                <li>Added HOW-TO document on fetching XML dependencies from JAR files</li>
                <li>Added HOW-TO document on using identities and references in XML</li>
                <li>Added HOW-TO document on unmarshalling raw XML segments into arbitrary types</li>
            </ul>    
            
        </section>
        
        <section title="Changes/improvements">

            <ul>
                <li>Complete rewrite of information related to caching in Castor JDO. The new
                    and improved documentation can be found 
                    <a href="jdo-caching-detail.html">here</a>.</li>
                <li>Modified <a href="scm.html">SVN/JIRA</a> and various other areas
                    of documentation to reflect migration of Castor repository from
                    CVS to SVN.</li>
                <li>The <a href="download.html">download page</a> now holds information
                    about libraries required for using/building Castor.</li>
                <li>Modified XML Mapping documentation so that DOCTYPE public IDs match
                    those defined in org.exolab.castor.util.DTDResolver</li>
            </ul>            
            
        </section>
        
        </section>

        
    </body>
</document>