<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.codehaus.org/jdo-caching-detail.xml">
  <properties>
    <title>Castor JDO - Caching</title>
    <abstract>
       Castor JDO - Caching concepts
    </abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <title>Castor JDO - Caching concepts</title>

    <header/>

    <section title="Introduction">
        
        <p>As explained at <a href="jdo-introduction.html">the introduction to Castor JDO</a>,
           Castor has support for many advanced features such as caching. The below sections 
           detail the features related to caching in Castor JDO, as their understanding 
           is required to use Castor JDO in a performant and secure way.</p>
           
        <p>In general, performance caches enhance the application performance 
           by reducing the number of read operations against the persistence 
           storage, by storing and reusing the last read or committed values of 
           the object. Performance caches do not affect the behavior of short 
           transactions or locking. It only affects persistence objects that have 
           been released from any transactional context.</p>
           
        <p>Starting from Castor 0.8.6, a performance cache implementation has been 
           added. At a technical level, Castor maintains separate (performance) caches 
           for each object type specified in the JDO mapping provided, allowing users 
           to specify - for each object type individually - the type and 
           capacity of the cache.</p>
           
        <p>By default, the following cache types are available:</p>
           
        <ctable>
            <cheader>
                <th>name</th>
                <th>Vendor</th>
                <th>Version</th>
                <th>Distributable?</th>
                <th>Open source/<br/>commercial</th>
                <th>high volume/<br/>performance</th>
                <th>Added in<br/>release</th>
            </cheader>
            <crow>
                <td>none</td>
                <td>Built-in</td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td align="center"></td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>unlimited</td>
                <td>Built-in</td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td align="center"></td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>count-limited</td>
                <td>Built-in</td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td align="center"></td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>time-limited</td>
                <td>Built-in</td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td align="center"></td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>coherence</td>
                <td><url href="http://www.tangosol.com/coherence.jsp">Tangosol Coherence</url></td>
                <td>2.5</td>
                <td align="center">Yes</td>
                <td>Commercial</td>
                <td align="center">Yes</td>
                <td align="center">0.9.9</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jcs</td>
                <td><url href="http://jakarta.apache.org/jcs">JCS</url></td>
                <td>1.2.5</td>
                <td align="center">Yes</td>
                <td>Open source</td>
                <td align="center">Yes</td>
                <td align="center">0.9.9</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>fkcache</td>
                <td><url href="http://jcache.sourceforge.net/">FKCache</url></td>
                <td>1.0-beta6</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td align="center">0.9.9</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>oscache</td>
                <td><url href="http://www.opensymphony.com/oscache/">OSCache</url></td>
                <td>2.5</td>
                <td align="center">Yes</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td align="center">1.0</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>fifo</td>
                <td>Built-in</td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">Yes</td>
                <td align="center">1.0</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>lru</td>
                <td>Built-in</td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td align="center">No</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">Yes</td>
                <td align="center">1.0</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>ehcache</td>
                <td>Built-in</td>
                <td>-</td>
                <td align="center">Yes</td>
                <td>Open Source</td>
                <td align="center">?</td>
                <td align="center">1.0.1</td>
            </crow>
        </ctable>

        <p>As some of these cache providers allow for allow you to use it 
           in a <b>distributed</b> mode, this allows Castor JDO to be used 
           in a clustered (multi-JVM) environment. Please see
           the section <a href="#Caching and clustered environments">below</a> for short summary of this feature.</p>

        <p>Per definition, all performance caches are <b>write-through</b>, because all 
           changes to objects as part of a transaction should be persisted into the cache
           at commit time without delay.</p>

        <p>For problems related to the use of performance caches, please consult with the relevant 
           entries in the <a href="jdo-faq.html#Castor and performance caches">JDO F.A.Q.</a>.</p>
        
    </section>
    
    <section title="Caching and long transactions">
        
        <p>As it stands currently, performance caches also serve a dual purpose 
           as dirty checking caches for <a href="long-transact.html">long-transactions</a>.
           This limitation implies that the object's availability in the performance cache 
           determines the allowed time span of a long transaction.</p>
           
        <p>This might become an issue when performance caches of type 'count-limited' or 
           'time-limited' are being used, where objects will eventually be disposed. 
           If an application tries to update an object that has been disposed from 
           the dirty checking cache, an ObjectModifedException will be thrown.</p>
        
    </section>
    
    <section title="Configuration">
        
        <p>The DTD declaration is as follows:
           <code-panel><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT cache-type  ( param* )>
<!ATTLIST cache-type
    type           ( none | count-limited | time-limited | unlimited |
                     coherence | fkcache | jcache | jcs | oscache |
                     fifo | lru ) "count-limited"
    debug          (true|false) "false"
    capacity       NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED>

<!ELEMENT param EMPTY>
<!ATTLIST param
          name   NMTOKEN  #REQUIRED
          value  NMTOKEN  #REQUIRED>]]></code-panel></p>
          
        <p>With release 1.0 of Castor the DTD has changed but it is backward compatible
           to the old one and allows to enable debugging of cache access for a specific
           class as well as passing individual configuration parameters to each cache
           instance. Only <b>count-limited</b> and <b>time-limited</b> of the current
           cache types support parameters. Parameter names are case sensitive and are
           silently ignored if they are unknown to a cache type.</p>
                   
        <p>It need to be noted that there are 3 parameter names that are reserved for
           internal use. If you specify a parameter with one of the names: <b>type</b>,
           <b>name</b> or <b>debug</b> their value will silently be overwritten with
           another one used internally.</p>
                
        <section title="Configuration sample - count-limited">
            
            <p>A <b>count-limited</b> least-recently-used cache (LRU) for 500 objects can be
               specified by:</p>
               
            <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="count-limited" capacity="500"/>]]></code-panel>

            <p>or</p>
           
            <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="count-limited"/>
    <param name="capacity" value="500"/>
</cache-type>]]></code-panel>

            <p>If both, the capacity attribute and parameter with name="capacity" is
               specified, the parameter value takes precedence over the attribute 
               value.</p>

        </section>
                
        <section title="Configuration sample - time-limited">
            
            <p>A <b>time-limited</b> first-in-first-out cache (FIFO) that expires objects
               after 15 minutes can be specified by:</p>
               
            <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="time-limited" capacity="900"/>]]></code-panel>
            
            <p>or</p>
            
            <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="time-limited"/>
    <param name="ttl" value="900"/>
</cache-type>]]></code-panel>

           <p>If both, the capacity attribute and parameter with name="ttl" is specified,
           the parameter value takes precedence over the attribute value.</p>
        
        </section>
                   
        <p>The <b>debug</b> attribute can be used to enable debugging for objects
           of a single class. In addition to setting this attribut to <b>true</b> you
           also need to set logging level of <b>org.castor.cache.Cache</b> to debug.</p>

        <note>The default cache-type is <tt>count-limited</tt> with a capacity of 30. 
              This will be used when no cache-type is specified in the mapping for 
              a class.</note>
              
    </section>
        
    <section title="fifo and lru cache providers">

        <p>The cache types <b>fifo</b> and <b>lru</b> are based on a set of articles in the
           O'Reilly Network by William Grosso, to implement a simplified and 1.3-compatible
           implementation of a Hashbelt algorithm.</p>

        <p>Hashbelts are simple, in principle. Instead of walking all objects and finding out
           when they're supposed to expire, use a "conveyor belt" approach. At any particular
           point in time, objects going into the cache go into the front of the conveyor belt.
           After a certain amount of time or when the size limit of a container has been
           reached, move the conveyor belt - put a new, empty container at the front of the
           conveyor belt to catch new objects, and the one that drops off of the end of the
           conveyor belt is, by definition, ready for garbage collection.</p>

        <p>As seen in his system, you can use a set of pluggable strategies to implement the
           actual hashbelt bits. A container strategy allows you to change out the
           implementation of the container itself - from simple hashtable-based
           implementations, up through more complex uses of soft referenced or hashset-based
           implementations, depending on what you need and what you want it to be used for.
           A pluggable "expire behavior" handler allows you to determine what action is taken
           on something which drops off of the bottom of the conveyor belt.</p>

        <p>In difference to all other cache types the <b>fifo</b> and <b>lru</b> cache
           types offer various configuration options. Both of them have 6 parameters to
           configure their behaviour.</p>

        <ctable>
            <cheader>
                <th align="left">parameter</th>
                <th align="left">description</th>
            </cheader>
            <crow>
                <td>containers</td>
                <td>The number of containers in the conveyor belt. For example: If a box
                    will drop off of the conveyor belt every 30 seconds, and you want a cache
                    that lasts for 5 minutes, you want 5 / 30 = 6 containers on the belt. Every
                    30 seconds, another, clean container goes on the front of the conveyor belt,
                    and everything in the last belt gets discarded. If not specified 10 containers
                    are used by default.
                    <br/>
                    For systems with fine granularity, you are free to use a large number of
                    containers; but the system is most efficient when the user decides on a
                    "sweet spot" determining both the number of containers to be managed on the
                    whole and the optimal number of buckets in those containers for managing. This
                    is ultimately a performance/accuracy tradeoff with the actual discard-from-cache
                    time being further from the mark as the rotation time goes up. Also the number
                    of objects discarded at once when capacity limit is reached depends upon the
                    number of containers.
                </td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>capacity</td>
                <td>Maximum capacity of the whole cache. If there are, for example, ten
                    containers on the belt and the capacity has been set to 1000, each container
                    will hold a maximum of 1000/10 objects. Therefore if the capacity limit is
                    reached and the last container gets droped from the belt there are up to 100
                    objects discarted at once. By default the capacity is set to 0 which causes
                    capacity limit to be ignored so the cache can hold an undefined number of
                    objects.
                </td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>ttl</td>
                <td>The maximum time an object lifes in cache. If the are, for example, ten
                    containers and ttl is set to 300 seconds (5 minutes), a new container will be
                    put in front of the belt every 300/10 = 30 seconds while another is dropped at
                    the end at the same time. Due to the granularity of 30 seconds, everything just
                    until 5 minutes 30 seconds will also end up in this box. The default value for
                    ttl is 60 seconds. If ttl is set to 0 which means that objects life in cache
                    for unlimited time and may only discarded by a capacity limit.
                </td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>monitor</td>
                <td>The monitor intervall in minutes when hashbelt cache rports the current
                    number of containers used and objects cached. If set to 0 (default) monitoring
                    is disabled.
                </td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>container-class</td>
                <td>The implementation of <b>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.Container</b>
                    interface to be used for all containers of the cache. Castor provides the following
                    3 implementations of the Container interface.
                    <ul>
                        <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.FastIteratingContainer</li>
                        <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.MapContainer</li>
                        <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.WeakReferenceContainer</li>
                    </ul>
                    If not specified the MapContainer will be used as default.
                </td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>reaper-class</td>
                <td>Specific reapers yield different behaviors. The GC reaper, the default,
                    just dumps the contents to the garbage collector. However, custom
                    implementations may want to actually do something when a bucket drops off the
                    end; see the javadocs on other available reapers to find a reaper strategy
                    that meets your behavior requirements. Apart of the default
                    <api>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NullReaper</api> we provide 3 abstract
                    implementations of <api>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.Reaper</api> interface:
                    <ul>
                        <li><api>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NotifyingReaper</api></li>
                        <li><api>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.RefreshingReaper</api></li>
                        <li><api>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.ReinsertingReaper</api></li>
                    </ul>
                    to be extended by your custom implementation.
                </td>
            </crow>
        </ctable>
        
        <section title="Configuration sample - fifo">
            
            <p>A <b>fifo</b> cache with default values explained above is specified by:</p>
            
           <code-panel>
<font color="darkgrey">&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...</font>
       &lt;cache-type type="<b>fifo</b>"/&gt;
<font color="darkgrey">       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</font></code-panel>

        </section>

        <section title="Configuration sample - lru">

            <p>A <b>lru</b> cache with capacity=300 and ttl=300 is defined by:</p>
                
           <code-panel>
<font color="darkgrey">&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...</font>
       &lt;cache-type type="<b>lru</b>" capacity="300"/&gt;
<font color="darkgrey">       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</font></code-panel>

           <p>or better by:</p>

           <code-panel>
<font color="darkgrey">&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...</font>
       &lt;cache-type type="<b>lru</b>"&gt;
          &lt;param name="capacity" value="300"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="ttl" value="300"/&gt;
       &lt;/cache-type&gt;
<font color="darkgrey">       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</font></code-panel>

        </section>
        
        <section title="Configuration sample - fifo (custommized)">

            <p>An example of a customized configuration of a <b>fifo</b> cache is:</p>
                
           <code-panel>
<font color="darkgrey">&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...</font>
       &lt;cache-type type="<b>fifo</b>"/&gt;
          <b>&lt;param name="container" value="10"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="capacity" value="1000"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="ttl" value="600"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="monitor" value="5"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="container-class" value="org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.WeakReferenceContainer"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="reaper-class" value="org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NullReaper"/&gt;</b>
       &lt;/cache-type&gt;
<font color="darkgrey">       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</font></code-panel>

        </section>
        
    </section>

    <section title="Caching and clustered environments">
    
        <p>All of the cache providers added with release 0.9.9 are distributed caches per se or can be 
        configured to operate in such a mode. This effectively allows Castor JDO to be used in a 
        clustered J2EE (multi-JVM) environment, where Castor JDO runs on each of the cluster instances,
        and where cache state is automatically snychronized between these instances.</p>
            
        <p>In such an environment, Castor JDO wil make use of the underlying cache provider 
        to replicate/distribute the content of a specific cache between the various 
        JDOManager instances. Through the distribution mechanism of the cache provider, a client
        of a Castor JDO instance on one JVM will see any updates made to domain objects performed 
        against any other JVM/JDO instance.</p>
    
        <section title="Configuration sample - Coherence">
            
            <p>The following class mapping, for example, ... </p>
            
            <code-panel>
<font color="darkgrey">&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...</font>
        &lt;cache-type type="<b>coherence</b>" /&gt;
<font color="darkgrey">       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</font></code-panel>
    
            <p>defines that for all objects of type <tt>com.xyz.MyOtherObject</tt> Tangosol's 
               <i>Coherence</i> cache provider should be used.</p>

        </section>
            
    </section>
    
    <section title="Custom cache provider">
     
       <p>As of release 0.9.6, Castor allows for the addition of user-defined cache 
          implementations. Whilst Castor provides a set of pre-built cache providers, 
          offering a variety of different cache algorithms, special needs still might
          require the application developer to implement a custom cache 
          algorithm. Castor facilitates such need by making available standardized
          interfaces and an easy to understand recipe for integrating a custom 
          cache provider with Castor.</p>

       <p>As explained in <api package="org.exolab.castor.jdo.persist">API docs for 
          the persists package</api>, 
          <api class="org.exolab.castor.persist.LockEngine">LockEngine</api> implements 
          a persistence engine that caches objects in memory for performance reasons 
          and thus reduces the number of operations against the persistence storage.</p>
    
       <p>The main component of this package is the interface 
          <api class="org.castor.cache.Cache">Cache</api>, which declares 
          the external functionality of a (performance) cache. Existing 
          (and future) cache implementations (have to) implement this interface, 
          which is closely modelled after the <tt>java.util.Map</tt> interface.</p>
            
       <p>Below is a summary of the steps required to build a custom cache provider 
          and register it with Castor JDO:</p>
    
       <p><ol>
            <li>Create a class that implements 
                <api class="org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.Cache"><tt>Cache</tt></api>.</li>
            <li>Create a class that implements 
                <api class="org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.CacheFactory">CacheFactory</api></li>
            <li>Register your custom cache implementation with Castor JDO in the
                <tt>castor.properties</tt> file.</li>
       </ol></p>

        <section title="Cache implementation">

            <p>Please create a class that implements the interface
               <api class="org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.Cache">Cache</api>.</p>    
       
            <p>To assist users in this task, a 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.AbstractBaseCache">AbstractBaseCache</api> 
               class has been supplied, which users should derive their custom 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.Cache">Cache</api> instances 
               from, if they wish so. Please consult existing 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.Cache">Cache</api> implementations 
               such as <api class="org.castor.cache.simple.TimeLimited">TimeLimited</api>} or 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.simple.CountLimited">CountLimited</api> 
               for code samples.</p>
             
            <code-panel>
/**
 * My own cache implementation
 */ 
 public class <b>CustomCache</b> extends <b>AbstractBaseCache</b> {
 
    ...
    
 }</code-panel>
 
        </section>

        <section title="CacheFactory implementation">
          
            <p>Please add a class that imnplements the 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.CacheFactory">CacheFactory</api> interface 
               and make sure that you provide valid values for the two 
               properties <tt>name</tt> and <tt>className</tt>.</p>    
       
            <p>To assist users in this task, a 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.AbstractCacheFactory">AbstractCacheFactory</api> 
               class has been supplied, which users should derive their custom 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.CacheFactory">CacheFactory</api> instances 
               from, if they wish so. Please consult existing 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.CacheFactory">CacheFactory</api> implementations 
               such as <api class="org.castor.cache.simple.TimeLimitedFactory">TimeLimitedFactory</api>} or 
               <api class="org.castor.cache.simple.CountLimitedFactory">CountLimitedFactory</api> 
               for code samples.</p>    

            <code-panel>
/**
 * My own cache factory implementation
 */ 
 public class <b>CustomCacheFactory</b> extends <b>AbstractCacheFactory</b> {
 
    /**
     * The name of the factory
     */
    <b>private static final String NAME = "custom"</b>;

    /**
     * Full class name of the underlying cache implementation.
     */
    <b>private static final String CLASS_NAME = "my.company.project.CustomCache"</b>; 
    
    /**
     * Returns the short alias for this factory instance.
     * @return The short alias name. 
     */
    <b>public String getName()</b> {
        return NAME;
    }
    
    /**
     * Returns the full class name of the underlying cache implementation.
     * @return The full cache class name. 
     */
    <b>public String getCacheClassName()</b> {
        return CLASS_NAME;   
    }
    
 }</code-panel>
                 
        </section>

        <section title="Configuration">
    
            <p>The file <tt>castor.properties</tt> holds a property
               <tt>org.castor.cache.Factories</tt> that enlists the available
               cache types through their related CacheFactory instances.</p>    

            <code-panel>
# 
# Cache implementations
# 
org.castor.cache.Factories=\
  org.castor.cache.simple.NoCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.TimeLimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.CountLimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.UnlimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.FKCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.JcsCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.JCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.CoherenceCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.OsCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.hashbelt.FIFOHashbeltFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.hashbelt.LRUHashbeltFactory</code-panel>

            <p>To add your custom cache implementation, please append the fully-qualified
               class name to this list as shown below:</p>
       
            <code-panel>
# 
# Cache implementations
# 
org.castor.cache.Factories=\
  org.castor.cache.simple.NoCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.TimeLimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.CountLimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.UnlimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.FKCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.JcsCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.JCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.CoherenceCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.OsCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.hashbelt.FIFOHashbeltFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.hashbelt.LRUHashbeltFactory,\
  <b>org.whatever.somewhere.nevermind.CustomCache</b></code-panel>
       
        </section>
        
    </section>
        
    <section title="CacheManager - monitoring and clearing caches">
   
	  <p>Sometimes it is necessary to interact with Castor's (performance) caches to 
         e.g.  (selectively) clear a Castor cache of its content, or inquire about 
         whether a particular object instance (as identified by its identity) is 
         cached already.</p>
	     
	  <p>For this purpose a 
         <api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager">CacheManager</api> can 
	     be obtained from a <api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.Database">Database</api> 
         instance by issuing the following code:</p>
	  
	  <code-panel>
JDO jdo = ....;
Database db = jdo.getDatabase();
CacheManager manager = db.getCacheManager();
	  </code-panel>
	
	  <p>This instance can subsequently be used to selectively clear the 
         Castor performance cache using one of the following methods:</p>
	     
	  <p><ul>
	        <li><api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager">expireCache()</api></li>
	        <li><api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager">expireCache(Class,Object)</api></li>
	        <li><api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager">expireCache(Class,Object[])</api></li>
	        <li><api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager">expireCache(Class[])</api></li>
	     </ul></p>
	     
	  <p>To inquire whether an object has already been cached, please use the 
         following method:</p>

	  <p><ul>
	        <li><api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager">isCached (Class, Object);</api></li>
	     </ul></p>
	     
	  <p>Please note that once you have closed the Database instance from which you 
         have obtained the CacheManager, the CacheManager cannot be used anymore and 
         will throw a 
	     <api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.PersistenceException">PersistenceException</api>.</p>
   
   </section> 
          
   </body>
</document>
