<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.codehaus.org/scm.xml">

  <properties>
    <title>SVN Access &amp; bug tracking</title>
    <abstract>Outlines how to access the SVN repository.</abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <title>SVN Access &amp; bug tracking</title>

    <section title="Issue Reporting and Tracking - JIRA">

      <p>Please use <a href="http://jira.codehaus.org/browse/CASTOR">JIRA</a> for
         reporting any issue and tracking their progress. In addition, Jira offers many
         additonal (more sophisticated) features that allow you to keep in touch with
         the project's current progress.</p>

      <p>Before submitting issues, please read
         <a href="how-to-submit-a-bug.xml">'How to submit an issue'</a>.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="SVN access">

      <p>To get the latest, most up-to-date source code, you'll need to use SVN. Please
         see the section on <a href="#Anonymous-SVN-Access">anonymous SVN access</a>
         below. If you wish to simply browse the SVN for specific files or to view
         changes and commit logs use
         <a href="http://cvs.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/castor/castor/trunk">FishEye access</a>
         to the SVN repository.</p>

      <p>Or as an alternative, please <a href="download.xml">download</a> the full source
         distribution for a given release.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="Anonymous SVN Access">

      <p>The source code, documentation and libraries are available for anonymous access
         from the <a href="www.codehaus.org">Codehaus SVN server</a>.</p>

      <p>SVN is updated regularly and may contain unstable (untested) code when you check
         it out - though in general this should not happen.</p>

      <p>To access the Castor SVN repository, please use the following URL:</p>

      <code-panel>
  $ svn://svn.castor.codehaus.org/castor/scm/castor/trunk
      </code-panel>

      <p>To, for example, checkout the most recent code of Castor, use the following
         command:</p>

      <code-panel>
  $ svn checkout svn://svn.castor.codehaus.org/castor/scm/castor/trunk castor
      </code-panel>

      <p>For more information about Subversion and various tools to access SVN
         repositories you may want to take a look at
         <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion site</a>.
         Additional information is also provided at
         <a href="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/HAUS/Subversion+at+the+haus">Codehaus wiki</a>.</p>
         
    </section>

    <section title="Behind A Firewall?">

      <p>Sometimes firewalls are configured in such a way that the ports used by SVN are
         blocked, and thus users behind the firewall cannot access the SVN repository.
         If you fall into this category, there's some alternatives outlined below.</p>

      <p><a href="www.codehaus.org">Codehaus</a> provides a HTTP interface to SVN
         repository using FishEye (tm). Using this tool, please download one of the
         following SVN snapshots from the SVN server from
         <url>http://svn.castor.codehaus.org</url>:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><a href="http://svn.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/~tarball=zip/castor/castor/trunk/trunk.zip">ZIP archive</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://svn.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/~tarball=tgz/castor/castor/trunk/trunk.tgz">TGZ archive</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://svn.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/~tarball=tbz2/castor/castor/trunk/trunk.tbz2">TBZ2 archive</a></li>
      </ul>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
