<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.codehaus.org/srcgen-maven-plugin.xml">

  <properties>
    <title>The Maven plugin for the Castor XML Code Generator</title>
    <abstract>
       Describes how to use the Maven 2 plugin for the Castor XML Code Generator.
    </abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <title>Using the Maven 2 plugin for the Castor XML Code Generator</title>

    <section title="Maven 2 plugin for the Castor XML code generator">

      <p>
        For those of you working with Maven 2 instead of Ant, the Maven 2 plugin for Castor 
        can be used to integrate source code generation from XML schemas with the Castor XML
        code generator as part of the standard Maven build life-cycle. The following sections
        show how to configure the Maven 2 Castor plugin and hwo to instruct Maven 2
        to generate sources from your XML schemas.</p>

		<section title="Configuration">

        	<p>To integrate source code generation from XML schema into your standard
               build life-cycle, you will have to configure the Maven 2 Castor plugin
               as follows:</p>

	        <code-panel><![CDATA[
<plugin>
   <groupId>org.codehaus.mojo</groupId>
   <artifactId>castor-maven-plugin</artifactId>
   <version>1.0</version>
</plugin>
]]></code-panel>

			<p>Above configuration will trigger source generation using the default
			   values as explained at the plugin page, assuming that the XML schema(s)
			   are located at <tt>src/main/castor</tt>, and code will be saved at
			   <tt>target/generated-sources/castor</tt>. When generating sources
			   for multiple schemas at the same time, you can put namespace to 
			   package mappings into <tt>src/main/castor/castorbuilder.properties</tt>.</p>
			   
			<p>To e.g. change some of these default locations, please add a 
			   &lt;configuration&gt; section to the plugin configuration as 
			   follows:</p>

	        <code-panel><![CDATA[
<plugin>
   <groupId>org.codehaus.mojo</groupId>
   <artifactId>castor-maven-plugin</artifactId>
   <version>1.0</version>
   <configuration>
      <schema>src/main/resources/org/exolab/castor/builder/binding/binding.xsd</schema>
      <packaging>org.exolab.castor.builder.binding</packaging>
      <properties>src/main/resources/org/exolab/castor/builder/binding.generation.properties</properties>
   </configuration>
 </plugin>		
]]></code-panel>

			<p>Details on the available configuration properties can be found here.</p>

			<p>By default, the Maven Castor plugin has been built and tested against 
			   a particular version of Castor. To switch to a newer version of Castor (not the
			   plugin itself), please use a &lt;dependencies&gt; section as shown below
			   to point the plugin to e.g. a newer version of Castor:</p>
			   
	        <code-panel><![CDATA[
<plugin>
   <groupId>org.codehaus.mojo</groupId>
   <artifactId>castor-maven-plugin</artifactId>
   <version>1.0</version>
   <dependencies>
     <dependency> 
       <groupId>org.codehaus.castor</groupId>
       <artifactId>castor</artifactId>
       <version>1.1-M3-SNAPSHOT</version>
     </dependency>
   </dependencies>
 </plugin>		
]]></code-panel>

		</section>

		<section title="Example">

        	<p>Below command shows how to instruct Maven (manually) to generate Java sources
               from the XML schemas as configured above.</p>

	        <code-panel><![CDATA[
> mvn castor:generate]]></code-panel>

		</section>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
