<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/cvs.xml">
  <body>
    <title>CVS Access</title>

    <section title="WebCVS, Snapshots, Bugzilla">

      <p><a href="http://castor.exolab.org/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi/castor/?cvsroot=castor">WebCVS access to the repository.</a></p>

      <p>Or, <a href="download.xml">download the full source distribution</a>
         containing the latest snapshot of the CVS.</p>

      <p><a href="http://bugzilla.exolab.org">Use Bugzilla for bug tracking.</a></p>

    </section>

    <section title="Anonymous Access">

      <p>The source code, documentation and libraries are available for anonymous access
         from the Exolab CVS server.</p>

      <p>The CVS is updated regularly and may contain an unstable version when you
         check it out. We commit working code to the CVS immediately prior to putting
         out a release.</p>

      <p>The CVS root is <tt>:pserver:anoncvs@castor.exolab.org:/cvs/castor</tt>
         and the password <tt>anoncvs</tt>.</p>

      <p>To login to CVS from the command line and checkout a version of Castor
         use the following commands:</p>

      <pre>
  $ cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@castor.exolab.org:/cvs/castor login
  password: anoncvs
  $ cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@castor.exolab.org:/cvs/castor checkout castor
      </pre>

      <p><b>Note:</b> There have been reports of problems using jCVS with ours CVS servers.
         Please use an alternative CVS client until this problem is resolved.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="Guidelines For Code Contribution">

      <p>All code contributions must be under the license and copyright of the
         project to which you contribute. By contributing code you agree that we
         can distribute the contribution under the terms of the license, that it
         can be distributed without any royalties, copyright, trademark, patent or
         other legal lock ups. Open source means no discrimination against any
         group or individual that may wish to use the code.</p>

      <p>When making a contribution you are granting us a world wide, royalty free,
         unlimited in time license to re-distribute the code under the Exolab license.
         In case you wonder, you remain the original author and copyright holder
         of the contribution, you just give other people a license to use it as well.
         Thank you.</p>

      <p>It's perfectly ok to put your name and e-mail address in the code.</p>

      <p>When sending patches, diff files with context (3 lines before, 3 lines
         after) work best:
<pre><![CDATA[
  cvs diff -c <file>
or
  diff -c <file>
]]></pre>
      </p>

    </section>

    <section title="Guidelines For Committers">

      <p><i>Familiarize yourself.</i> Take some time to understand the directory
         structure, build environment, interaction between components, coding and commenting
         style. Nothing out of the ordinary, but still not all projects are identical.</p>

      <p><i>Before starting to work please advertise.</i> It's pointless to have two people
         working on the same feature. Send an e-mail to the developer mailing list and
         announce what and how. If you don't get a reply within a day, you can assume the
         coast is clear.</p>

      <p><i>Test before you commit.</i> Before committing any changes run a <tt>cvs update</tt>
         to make sure you have the latest code base. Run the test cases to make sure nothing
         is broken.</p>

      <p><i>Commit all at once.</i> If the change involves more than a single file, make sure
         to commit all the changes together. A partially committed CVS tree is not a pretty
         sight. No lunch breaks, meetings or sleep during commits.</p>

      <p><i>Be ready to receive complaints.</i> Hopefully all works fine, but if changes
         to break existing code, people will complain. Be ready to answer their e-mails
         and apply the proper fixes. No going on vacation five minutes after a commit.</p>

      <p><i>Put your name so people know who to credit.</i> (Also who to blame). Initials
         work just fine, your full name and e-mail address are already on the main page.
         If you've added a new file, feel free to put your name and e-mail address as the
         author. If you're fixing a file, put your initials on the comment.</p>

      <p><i>Observe release time.</i> We're going to announce a new release five hours prior
         to making it. That gives you four hours to commit any changes, make sure nothing
         breaks. Don't leave the computer before the release is done. If you can't make
         it, there's alway the next release.</p>

      <p><i>Document what you've done.</i> In-code documentation, CVS commit messages,
         and the changelog. Major changes should always be recorded in the changelog.</p>

      <p><i>Use the document DTD.</i> When adding new documentation use the document DTD.
         Specify the proper document URL, properties, body and section. Everything
         inside the body/header/section is XHTML. That means well formed HTML.
         If it's not, you won't be able to build the docs.</p>

      <p>We don't have a particular style for documentation, and we do appreciate
         a sense of humor, sarcasm and literary expression. Just don't overdue it,
         and please, no cliche.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="Licensing Policy">

      <p>We have a simple policy regarding distributable code. Either it's open source
         and compatible in license, or it's an API that is freely distributable.</p>

      <p>BSD-like and MPL-like licenses are compatible and can be mixed in the
         same code base. Liberal licenses and public domain are also fine.</p>

      <p>APIs need not be open source, but they must be freely distributable.
         As a policy we like to stick with standard APIs and never modify them,
         so the license has little affect. We do favor public domains APIs like
         SAX over tightly controlled APIs, and hopefully we can all do something
         about that.</p>

      <p>Pay special attention to pre-release availability and trademark issues.
         Several committees and companies require proper trademark acknowledgement in
         the documentation. Some of them are available for distribution only
         once they have been formally released. This policy applies to all APIs
         coming from Sun.</p>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
