<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/index.xml">
  <body>
    <title>The Castor Project</title>

    <header>
      <p>Castor is the shortest path between Java[tm] objects, XML documents, SQL tables and LDAP
         directories. It provides Java to XML binding, Java to SQL/LDAP persistence, and then
         some more.</p>

      <p><a href="ora-mar-2k/castor.htm">The presentation we did at the Java O'Reilly Conference
         is now available online</a>. For those who could not attend we promise to make another
         one during the JavaOne conference.</p>

      <p><a href="origins.xml">About the origins of the name</a></p>

      <p><b>Note:</b> Presently we are only hosting one mailing list. Traffic is not high, so if
         you are interested in keeping up to date with new releases, please <a href="lists.xml">subscribe
         to this list</a>.</p>

    </header>

    <section title="Features">

      <p>Short feature list (we haven't got all day):
        <ul>
          <li>Castor XML: Java object to XML document</li>
          <li>Castor JDO: Java object persistence to RDBMS</li>
          <li>Castor DAX: Java object persistence to LDAP</li>
          <li>Castor DSML: LDAP directory exchange through XML</li>
          <li>XML-based mapping file specify the mapping between one model and another</li>
          <li>Support for schema-less Java to XML binding</li>
          <li>In memory caching and write-at-commit reduces JDBC operations</li>
          <li>Two phase commit transactions, object rollback and deadlock detection</li>
          <li>OQL query mapping to SQL queries</li>
          <li>EJB container managed persistence provider for OpenEJB</li>
        </ul>
        See the <a href="status.xml">status page</a> for more information.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="News">
      <p>Version $VERSION$ is now <a href="download.xml">available for download</a>.
      <ul>
        <li>Apr 7, 2000: Version 0.8.2, Minor bug fixes</li>
        <li>Apr 5, 2000: Version 0.8.1, JDO API useability, new mapping file, improved lock mechanism</li>
        <li>Mar 24, 2000: Version 0.8, unified mapping model, pluggable DB engine, dirty checking</li>
        <li>Mar 10, 2000: Version 0.7.11, supports one-many relations, XML-Servlet</li>
        <li>Mar 3, 2000: Version 0.7.10, addresses performance of the cache engine</li>
        <li>Jan 7, 2000: Version 0.7, first to include JDO</li>
        <li>Dec 21, 1999: Version 0.6</li>
      </ul>
      See the <a href="changelog.xml">change log page</a> for more information.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="About the Castor Project">

      <p>The Castor project has been developed out of need: the need to get stuff done
         and the need to write useful code. It has been designed and coded over many cups
         of Latte and tall Americano, as proof that coffe beans do come in handy.</p>

      <p>Contributors:
        <ul>
          <li>Oleg Nitz <email>on@ibis.odessa.ua</email></li>
          <li>Stefan Liebner <email>MailLiebner@gmx.ne</email></li>
          <li>Venkatakrishnan Sundaranatha <email>ssvk@msn.com</email></li>
        </ul>
      </p>

      <p>Most of the code released through the Castor Project has been developed by Keith Visco,
         Chief XML Architect, Exoffice Technologies, Inc. &lt;<email>visco@exoffice.com</email>&gt;
         and Assaf Arkin, CTO &lt;<email>arkin@exoffice.com</email>&gt;. Contributors are welcome
         to join this project. Please join us on the <a href="lists.xml">mailing list</a>.</p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
