<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/long-transact.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Castor JDO Long Transactions Support</title>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <p>The usual Castor transactions are called here short
         transactions: an object is read, modified and written within the
         bounds of one transaction.
         Long transactions consist of two Castor transactions:
         an object is read in the first and written in the second.
         Between them the object is sent "outwards" and modified there.
         For example, the object may be send to a client application and
         dispayed to a user, or it may be sent to a servlet engine and is
         displayed on a web page. After that the modified object returns
         back and is written to the database in the second transaction.
         At this point the object is usually not the same physical instance
         as one that was read in the first transaction.
         The example code for writing the object in the second Castor
         transaction follows:
         <code>
    <comment>
    // a customer go to a webpage to review her personal information.
    // The servlet then call this server side function: getCustomerInfo</comment>
    public CustomerInfo getCustomerInfo( Integer customNum ) {
         <comment>
             // in most case, users simply review information and
             // make no change. Even if they make changes, it often 
             // takes time for them to decide. We don't want to 
             // lock the database row, so commit right after we load.</comment>
         db.begin();
         CustomerInfo info = (CustomerInfo) 
            db.load( CustomerInfo.class, customNum );

         <comment>
                 // we also want to keep track of customers patterns
                 // well...it helps us provide better service.</comment>
         info.setLastVisit( today );
         db.commit();
         return info;
    }

    <comment>
        // Three days passed, the indecisive customer finally agrees to 
        // marry Joe. She changes her last name in the webpage and 
        // clicked the "Submit" button on the webpage.
    </comment>

    <comment>
        // The servlet then calls updateCustomerInfo to update the
        // last name for the indecisive customer.</comment>
    public void updateCustomerInfo( CustomerInfo info ) {
        db.begin();
        db.update(info);
        db.commit();
    }
         </code>
         Note, that it is natural to read the object in the first
         transaction in the read-only mode.
      </p>
      <p>Since the time interval between the first and the second
         transaction is relatively big, it is desirable to perform dirty
         checking, i.e. to check that the object has not been modified
         in the database during the long transaction.
         For that the object must hold a timestamp: it is set by
         Castor during the first Castor transaction and is checked during
         the second one.
         In order to enable the dirty checking for long transactions,
         the object should implement the interface
         org.exolab.castor.jdo.TimeStampable
         having two methods: <code>long jdoGetTimeStamp()</code> and
         <code>void jdoSetTimeStamp(long timeStamp)</code>
         There are two types of timestamps: local (in the Castor cache) and 
         global (in the database). 
         Respectively, the are two dirty checking algorithms: 
         bounded and reliable. 
         They are decribed below in details.
         The reliable dirty checking isn't implemented yet.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="Bounded dirty checking">
      <p>The advantage of the bounded dirty checking is that it doesn't need 
         any changes to the database schema, because it uses the Castor 
         cache to store object timestamps. 
         The disadvantage of this algorithm is that it is bounded by 
         a lifetime of the cached copy of the object. 
         After the cached copy has been purged, db.update() 
         causes ObjectModifiedException.
      </p>
      <p>Thus, parameters of the cache define dirty checking capabilities.
         Let's consider the existing cache types:
         <ul>
           <li>none - the bounded dirty checking is impossible
           </li>
           <li>count-limited - the count limit for the cache is a count 
           limit for the objects of this class that can participate in long 
           and short transactions simultaneously.
           </li>
           <li>time-limited - the time limit for the cache is a time limit 
           for the long transaction.
           </li>
           <li>unlimited - the bounded dirty checking gives correct results
           while the cache exists, i.e. until the crash of the server.
           </li>
         </ul>
       </p>
    </section>

    <!--section title="Reliable dirty checking">
      <p>In order to use the reliable dirty checking, you have to add a 
         timestamp field to the database table. 
         Some database servers (e.g., Sybase and MS SQL Server) support 
         timestamp fields automatically.
         For other databases you should add a NUMERIC field and a 
         trigger that increases the field's value on UPDATE.
         And the last possibility is to tell Castor to increase the field 
         value on UPDATEs.
      </p>
    </section-->


  </body>
</document>









