<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.exolab.org/status.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Status</title>

    <section title="Supported Features">

      <section title="Castor XML">
        <ul>
          <li>Java to XML mapping automates transformation of Java objects from
              and into XML documents and provides Java object validation</li>

          <li>Java to XML mapping uses an XML document to specify the mapping
              textually, Bean-like descriptors to specify them programatically,
              and introspection to create default mappings</li>

          <li>Code generator can produce Java objects, validation and the proper
              mapping based on an XML schema</li>

          <li>Supports XML schema data types including integer, real (float/double),
              NMTOKEN, NCName, timeInstant, ID/IDREF, boolean and binary (base 64 encoded)</li>

          <li>Supports arbitrary object marshalling when object type is known at
              run-time and XML schema is determined dynamically based on the
              object type</li>

          <li>Supports for creation of objects based on class name attribute</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section title="Castor JDO">
        <ul>
          <li>Java to SQL mapping (object/relational) automates Java persistence
              into any relational database server using JDBC</li>

          <li>Java to SQL mapping uses an XML document to specify the mapping
              textually, and provides an API to specify them programatically</li>

          <li>Supports one-one and one-many relation types, SQL/Java inheritance,
              object graph to single row mapping, and multiple column primary
              keys and automatic type conversion</li>

          <li>Optimistic and pessimistic locking modes, in-memory concurrency
              engine, and dead-lock detection</li>

          <li>Provides support for EJB 1.1 CMP entity beans (release 0.9)
              and CMP finder declaration using OQL</li>

          <li>Efficient implementation incurs little overhead compared to
              direct JDBC access</li>

          <li>Support for JTA transaction demarcation, inclusion as resource
              in transactional environment, and JDBC connection pooling
              (release 0.9 integrated with Tyrex)</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section title="Castor DAX">
        <ul>
          <li>Still work in progress</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section title="Castor DSML">
        <ul>
          <li>Import/export an LDAP directory or search results to/from XML
              based on the industry standard DSML schema</li>

          <li>XML document for specifying LDAP queries and import rules</li>

          <li>Supports both JNDI service providers and the Mozilla Directory SDK</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="What's missing">
      <ul>
        <li>Work is under way on a direct SQL->XML bridge which uses the same
            mapping file but does not involve any Java objects in the process.</li>

        <li>This release of Castor JDO provides only preliminary support for OQL
            queries with simple syntax and single object retrieval. A project
            to extend the OQL engine is underway.</li>

        <li>The EJB CMP implementation is now developed in the scope of the
            OpenEJB project.</li>

        <li>This release of Castor JDO supports JTA transactional environments,
            but lacks support for JTA factories. Integration with transaction
            managers and Tomcat/OpenEJB will be introduced in release 0.9.</li>

        <li>Key generation, engines for Oracle/Sybase, stored procedures,
            BLOBs, XML content, read-only queries, XML defined finders.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section title="TODO">
      <ul>
        <li>Many-many relations and possible bug fixes for inheritence</li>

        <li>Remove excessive methods in source code generator</li>

        <li>Add type convertors to bind parameters and load() method</li>

        <li>KeyGenerator - use one from SQLEngine, way to specify the key generator from the mapping file,
            way to pass a key generator parameter on database creation</li>

        <li>Support for read-only fields</li>

        <li>Cache control at JDO configuration and mapping file specification - no-cache option,
            cache object limit, cache time limit, LRU removal deamon</li>

        <li>Serializable, SQLData, DOM field types</li>

        <li>Java 1.2 collection handlers</li>

        <li>Stored procedures</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>




