<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
     "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

  <section id="advanced-jdo.caching">
    <sectioninfo>
      <title>Castor JDO - Caching</title>
<!--  
      <abstract>
        <para>Castor JDO - Caching concepts</para>
      </abstract>
-->
    </sectioninfo>
    <title>Castor JDO - Caching concepts</title>

    <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        
        <para>
           As explained at 
           <link linkend="jdo.introduction">the introduction to Castor JDO</link>,
           Castor has support for many advanced features such as caching. 
           The below sections detail the features related to caching in Castor JDO, 
           as their understanding is required to use Castor JDO in a performant and 
           secure way.
        </para>
           
        <para>
           In general, performance caches enhance the application performance 
           by reducing the number of read operations against the persistence 
           storage, by storing and reusing the last read or committed values of 
           the object. Performance caches do not affect the behavior of short 
           transactions or locking. It only affects persistence objects that have 
           been released from any transactional context.
        </para>
           
        <para>
           Starting from Castor 0.8.6, a performance cache implementation has been 
           added. At a technical level, Castor maintains separate (performance) caches 
           for each object type specified in the JDO mapping provided, allowing users 
           to specify - for each object type individually - the type and 
           capacity of the cache.
        </para>
           
        <para>By default, the following cache types are available:</para>
           
        <table frame="all">
          <title>Available cache types</title>
          
          <tgroup cols="7">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>name</entry>
                <entry>Vendor</entry>
                <entry>Version</entry>
                <entry>Distributable?</entry>
                <entry>Open source/commercial</entry>
                <entry>high volume/performance</entry>
                <entry>Added in release</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>none</entry>
                <entry>Built-in</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry align="center"></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>unlimited</entry>
                <entry>Built-in</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry align="center"></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>count-limited</entry>
                <entry>Built-in</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry align="center"></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>time-limited</entry>
                <entry>Built-in</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry align="center"></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>coherence</entry>
                <entry>
                  <ulink url="http://www.tangosol.com/coherence.jsp">Tangosol 
                  Coherence</ulink>
                </entry>
                <entry>2.5</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry>Commercial</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry align="center">0.9.9</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>jcs</entry>
                <entry><ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/jcs">JCS</ulink></entry>
                <entry>1.2.5</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry>Open source</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry align="center">0.9.9</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>fkcache</entry>
                <entry><ulink url="http://jcache.sourceforge.net/">FKCache</ulink></entry>
                <entry>1.0-beta6</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry align="center">0.9.9</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>oscache</entry>
                <entry>
                  <ulink url="http://www.opensymphony.com/oscache/">OSCache</ulink>
                </entry>
                <entry>2.5</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry align="center">1.0</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>fifo</entry>
                <entry>Built-in</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry align="center">1.0</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>lru</entry>
                <entry>Built-in</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry align="center">No</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry align="center">1.0</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ehcache</entry>
                <entry>Built-in</entry>
                <entry>-</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry>Open Source</entry>
                <entry align="center">?</entry>
                <entry align="center">1.0.1</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>gigaspaces</entry>
                <entry><ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/jcs">JCS</ulink></entry>
                <entry>5.0</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry>Commercial</entry>
                <entry align="center">Yes</entry>
                <entry align="center">1.0.1</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>
           As some of these cache providers allow for allow you to use it in a 
           <emphasis role="bold">distributed</emphasis> mode, this allows Castor 
           JDO to be used in a clustered (multi-JVM) environment. Please see the 
           section 
           <link linkend="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.clustered-environments">below</link> 
           for short summary of this feature.
        </para>

        <para>
           Per definition, all build-in performance caches are 
           <emphasis role="bold">write-through</emphasis>, because all 
           changes to objects as part of a transaction should be persisted into the 
           cache at commit time without delay.
        </para>

        <para>
           For problems related to the use of performance caches, please consult with 
           the relevant entries in the 
           <link linkend="jdo.faq.performance-caches">JDO F.A.Q.</link>.
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.long-transactions">
        <title>Caching and long transactions</title>
        
        <para>
           As it stands currently, performance caches also serve a dual purpose 
           as dirty checking caches for 
           <link linkend="advanced-jdo.long-transactions">long-transactions</link>.
           This limitation implies that the object's availability in the performance 
           cache determines the allowed time span of a long transaction.
        </para>
           
        <para>
           This might become an issue when performance caches of type 'count-limited' or 
           'time-limited' are being used, where objects will eventually be disposed. 
           If an application tries to update an object that has been disposed from 
           the dirty checking cache, an ObjectModifedException will be thrown.
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration">
        <title>Configuration</title>
        
        <para>
           The DTD declaration is as follows:
           <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT cache-type  ( param* )>
<!ATTLIST cache-type
    type           ( none | count-limited | time-limited | unlimited |
                     coherence | fkcache | jcache | jcs | oscache |
                     fifo | lru | ehcache | gigaspaces ) "count-limited"
    debug          (true|false) "false"
    capacity       NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED>

<!ELEMENT param EMPTY>
<!ATTLIST param
          name   NMTOKEN  #REQUIRED
          value  NMTOKEN  #REQUIRED>]]></programlisting>
        </para>
          
        <para>
           With release 1.0 of Castor the DTD has changed but it is backward compatible
           to the old one and allows to enable debugging of cache access for a specific
           class as well as passing individual configuration parameters to each cache
           instance. Only <emphasis role="bold">count-limited</emphasis> and 
           <emphasis role="bold">time-limited</emphasis> of the current
           build-in cache types support parameters. Parameter names are case sensitive 
           and are silently ignored if they are unknown to a cache type.
        </para>
                   
        <para>
           It need to be noted that there are 3 parameter names that are reserved for
           internal use. If you specify a parameter with one of the names: 
           <emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis> 
           or <emphasis role="bold">debug</emphasis> their value will silently be 
           overwritten with another one used internally.
        </para>
                
        <example id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.sample-count-limited">
            <title>Configuration sample - count-limited</title>
            
            <para>
               A <emphasis role="bold">count-limited</emphasis> least-recently-used 
               cache (LRU) for 500 objects can be specified by:
            </para>
               
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="count-limited" capacity="500"/>]]></programlisting>

            <para>or</para>
           
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="count-limited"/>
    <param name="capacity" value="500"/>
</cache-type>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
               If both, the capacity attribute and parameter with name="capacity" is
               specified, the parameter value takes precedence over the attribute 
               value.
            </para>
        </example>
                
        <example id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.sample-time-limited">
            <title>Configuration sample - time-limited</title>
            
            <para>
               A <emphasis role="bold">time-limited</emphasis> first-in-first-out 
               cache (FIFO) that expires objects after 15 minutes can be specified by:
            </para>
               
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="time-limited" capacity="900"/>]]></programlisting>
            
            <para>or</para>
            
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="time-limited"/>
    <param name="ttl" value="900"/>
</cache-type>]]></programlisting>

           <para>
              If both, the capacity attribute and parameter with name="ttl" is 
              specified, the parameter value takes precedence over the attribute value.
           </para>
        </example>
                   
        <para>
           The <emphasis role="bold">debug</emphasis> attribute can be used to enable 
           debugging for objects of a single class. In addition to setting this 
           attribut to <emphasis role="bold">true</emphasis> you also need to set 
           logging level of <emphasis role="bold">org.castor.cache.Cache</emphasis> 
           to debug.
        </para>

        <note>
           <para>
              The default cache-type is <literal>count-limited</literal> with a 
              capacity of 30. This will be used when no cache-type is specified in 
              the mapping for a class.
           </para>
        </note>
    </section>
        
    <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.fifo-lru">
        <title>fifo and lru cache providers</title>

        <para>
           The cache types <emphasis role="bold">fifo</emphasis> and 
           <emphasis role="bold">lru</emphasis> are based on a set of articles in the
           O'Reilly Network by William Grosso, to implement a simplified and 
           1.3-compatible implementation of a Hashbelt algorithm.
        </para>

        <para>
           Hashbelts are simple, in principle. Instead of walking all objects and 
           finding out when they're supposed to expire, use a "conveyor belt" approach. 
           At any particular point in time, objects going into the cache go into the 
           front of the conveyor belt. After a certain amount of time or when the size 
           limit of a container has been reached, move the conveyor belt - put a new, 
           empty container at the front of the conveyor belt to catch new objects, and 
           the one that drops off of the end of the conveyor belt is, by definition, 
           ready for garbage collection.
        </para>

        <para>
           As seen in his system, you can use a set of pluggable strategies to 
           implement the actual hashbelt bits. A container strategy allows you to 
           change out the implementation of the container itself - from simple 
           hashtable-based implementations, up through more complex uses of soft 
           referenced or hashset-based implementations, depending on what you need 
           and what you want it to be used for. A pluggable "expire behavior" handler 
           allows you to determine what action is taken on something which drops off 
           of the bottom of the conveyor belt.
        </para>

        <para>
           In difference to all other cache types the 
           <emphasis role="bold">fifo</emphasis> and 
           <emphasis role="bold">lru</emphasis> cache types offer various configuration 
           options. Both of them have 6 parameters to configure their behaviour.
        </para>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>cache types parameters</title>
        
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="1*" />
            <colspec colwidth="12*" />
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">parameter</entry>
                <entry align="left">description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>containers</entry>
                <entry>
                   The number of containers in the conveyor belt. For example: If a 
                   box will drop off of the conveyor belt every 30 seconds, and you 
                   want a cache that lasts for 5 minutes, you want 5 / 30 = 6 
                   containers on the belt. Every 30 seconds, another, clean container 
                   goes on the front of the conveyor belt, and everything in the last 
                   belt gets discarded. If not specified 10 containers are used by default.

                   For systems with fine granularity, you are free to use a large 
                   number of containers; but the system is most efficient when the 
                   user decides on a "sweet spot" determining both the number of 
                   containers to be managed on the whole and the optimal number of 
                   buckets in those containers for managing. This is ultimately a 
                   performance/accuracy tradeoff with the actual discard-from-cache 
                   time being further from the mark as the rotation time goes up. 
                   Also the number of objects discarded at once when capacity limit 
                   is reached depends upon the number of containers.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>capacity</entry>
                <entry>
                   Maximum capacity of the whole cache. If there are, for example, ten
                   containers on the belt and the capacity has been set to 1000, each 
                   container will hold a maximum of 1000/10 objects. Therefore if the 
                   capacity limit is reached and the last container gets droped from 
                   the belt there are up to 100 objects discarted at once. By default 
                   the capacity is set to 0 which causes capacity limit to be ignored 
                   so the cache can hold an undefined number of objects.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ttl</entry>
                <entry>
                   The maximum time an object lifes in cache. If the are, for example, 
                   ten containers and ttl is set to 300 seconds (5 minutes), a new 
                   container will be put in front of the belt every 300/10 = 30 seconds 
                   while another is dropped at the end at the same time. Due to the 
                   granularity of 30 seconds, everything just until 5 minutes 30 
                   seconds will also end up in this box. The default value for ttl 
                   is 60 seconds. If ttl is set to 0 which means that objects life 
                   in cache for unlimited time and may only discarded by a capacity 
                   limit.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>monitor</entry>
                <entry>
                   The monitor intervall in minutes when hashbelt cache rports the 
                   current number of containers used and objects cached. If set to 0 
                   (default) monitoring is disabled.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>container-class</entry>
                <entry>
                   The implementation of 
                   <interface>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.Container</interface>
                   interface to be used for all containers of the cache. 
                   Castor provides the following 3 implementations of the Container 
                   interface.
                    <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>
                           org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.FastIteratingContainer
                        </para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>
                          org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.MapContainer
                        </para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>
                          org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.WeakReferenceContainer
                        </para>
                      </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    If not specified the MapContainer will be used as default.
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>reaper-class</entry>
                <entry>
                   Specific reapers yield different behaviors. The GC reaper, 
                   the default, just dumps the contents to the garbage collector. 
                   However, custom implementations may want to actually do something 
                   when a bucket drops off the end; see the javadocs on other available 
                   reapers to find a reaper strategy that meets your behavior 
                   requirements. Apart of the default 
                   <classname>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NullReaper</classname> we provide 
                   3 abstract implementations of 
                   <interface>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.Reaper</interface> interface:
                    <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>
                          <classname>
                            org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NotifyingReaper
                          </classname>
                        </para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>
                          <classname>
                            org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.RefreshingReaper
                          </classname>
                        </para>
                      </listitem>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>
                          <classname>
                            org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.ReinsertingReaper
                          </classname>
                        </para>
                      </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    to be extended by your custom implementation.
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        
        <example id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.fifo-lru.sample-fifo">
          <title>Configuration sample - fifo</title>
            
          <para>
            A <emphasis role="bold">fifo</emphasis> cache with default values 
            explained above is specified by:
          </para>
            
             <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...
       &lt;cache-type type="<emphasis role="bold">fifo</emphasis>"/&gt;
       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</programlisting>
        </example>

        <example id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.fifo-lru.sample-lru">
          <title>Configuration sample - lru</title>

          <para>
            A <emphasis role="bold">lru</emphasis> cache with capacity=300 and 
            ttl=300 is defined by:
          </para>
                
          <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...
       &lt;cache-type type="<emphasis role="bold">lru</emphasis>" capacity="300"/&gt;
       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</programlisting>

           <para>or better by:</para>

           <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...
       &lt;cache-type type="<emphasis role="bold">lru</emphasis>"&gt;
          &lt;param name="capacity" value="300"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="ttl" value="300"/&gt;
       &lt;/cache-type&gt;
       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</programlisting>
        </example>
        
        <example id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.fifo-lru.sample-fifo-customized">
            <title>Configuration sample - fifo (custommized)</title>

            <para>An example of a customized configuration of a <emphasis role="bold">fifo</emphasis> cache is:</para>
                
           <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...
       &lt;cache-type type="<emphasis role="bold">fifo</emphasis>"/&gt;
          <emphasis role="bold">&lt;param name="container" value="10"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="capacity" value="1000"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="ttl" value="600"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="monitor" value="5"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="container-class" value="org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.WeakReferenceContainer"/&gt;
          &lt;param name="reaper-class" value="org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NullReaper"/&gt;</emphasis>
       &lt;/cache-type&gt;
       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</programlisting>
        </example>
    </section>

    <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.clustered-environments">
        <title>Caching and clustered environments</title>
    
        <para>
           All of the cache providers added with release 0.9.9 are distributed caches 
           per se or can be configured to operate in such a mode. This effectively 
           allows Castor JDO to be used in a clustered J2EE (multi-JVM) environment, 
           where Castor JDO runs on each of the cluster instances, and where cache 
           state is automatically snychronized between these instances.
        </para>
            
        <para>
           In such an environment, Castor JDO wil make use of the underlying cache 
           provider to replicate/distribute the content of a specific cache between 
           the various JDOManager instances. Through the distribution mechanism of 
           the cache provider, a client of a Castor JDO instance on one JVM will see 
           any updates made to domain objects performed against any other JVM/JDO 
           instance.
        </para>
    
        <example id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.sample-coherence">
            <title>Configuration sample - Coherence</title>
            
            <para>The following class mapping, for example, ... </para>
            
            <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...
        &lt;cache-type type="<emphasis role="bold">coherence</emphasis>" /&gt;
       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</programlisting>
    
            <para>
               defines that for all objects of type 
               <literal>com.xyz.MyOtherObject</literal> Tangosol's 
               <emphasis role="italic">Coherence</emphasis> cache provider should 
               be used.
            </para>
        </example>

        <example id="advanced-jdo.caching.configuration.sample-gigaspaces">
            <title>Configuration sample - Gigaspaces</title>
            
            <para>The following class mapping, for example, ... </para>
            
            <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...
        &lt;cache-type type="<emphasis role="bold">gigaspaces</emphasis>" /&gt;
       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</programlisting>
    
            <para>
               defines that for all objects of type 
               <literal>com.xyz.MyOtherObject</literal> the 
               <emphasis role="italic">Gigaspaces</emphasis> cache provider should 
               be used. As Gigspaces supports various cache and clsuer modes, this 
               cache provider allows product-specific configuration as shown below:
            </para>

            <programlisting language="xml">
&lt;mapping&gt;
    ...
    &lt;class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject"&gt;
       ...
        &lt;cache-type type="<emphasis role="bold">gigaspaces</emphasis>" &gt;
           &lt;param name="spaceURL" value="/./" /&gt;
           &lt;param name="spaceProperties" value="useLocalCache" /&gt;
        &lt;/cache-type&gt;
       ...
    &lt;/class&gt;
    ...
&lt;/mapping&gt;</programlisting>
        </example>
    </section>
    
    <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.custom-provider">
       <title>Custom cache provider</title>
     
       <para>
          As of release 0.9.6, Castor allows for the addition of user-defined cache 
          implementations. Whilst Castor provides a set of pre-built cache providers, 
          offering a variety of different cache algorithms, special needs still might
          require the application developer to implement a custom cache 
          algorithm. Castor facilitates such need by making available standardized
          interfaces and an easy to understand recipe for integrating a custom 
          cache provider with Castor.
       </para>

       <para>
          As explained in <package>org.exolab.castor.jdo.persist</package> 
          (API docs for the persists package), 
          <classname>org.exolab.castor.persist.LockEngine</classname> implements 
          a persistence engine that caches objects in memory for performance reasons 
          and thus reduces the number of operations against the persistence storage.
       </para>
    
       <para>
          The main component of this package is the interface 
          <interface>org.castor.cache.Cache</interface>, which declares the external 
          functionality of a (performance) cache. Existing (and future) cache 
          implementations (have to) implement this interface, which is closely 
          modelled after the <interface>java.util.Map</interface> interface.
          </para>
            
       <para>
          Below is a summary of the steps required to build a custom cache provider 
          and register it with Castor JDO:
       </para>
    
       <para>
         <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Create a class that implements 
                <interface>org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.Cache</interface>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Create a class that implements 
                <interface>org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.CacheFacto</interface>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Register your custom cache implementation with Castor JDO in the
                <filename>castor.properties</filename> file.
              </para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
       </para>

       <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.custom-provider.cache-implementation">
            <title>Cache implementation</title>

            <para>
               Please create a class that implements the interface
               <interface>org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.Cache">Cache</interface>.
            </para>    
       
            <para>
               To assist users in this task, a 
               <classname>org.castor.cache.AbstractBaseCache</classname> 
               class has been supplied, which users should derive their custom 
               <classname>org.castor.cache.Cache</classname> instances 
               from, if they wish so. Please consult existing 
               <classname>org.castor.cache.Cache</classname> implementations such as 
               <classname>org.castor.cache.simple.TimeLimited</classname>} or 
               <classname>org.castor.cache.simple.CountLimited</classname> 
               for code samples.
            </para>
             
            <programlisting language="java">
/**
 * My own cache implementation
 */ 
 public class <emphasis role="bold">CustomCache</emphasis> extends <emphasis role="bold">AbstractBaseCache</emphasis> {
 
    ...
    
 }</programlisting>
       </section>

       <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.custom-provider.cachefactory-implementation">
           <title>CacheFactory implementation</title>
          
            <para>
               Please add a class that imnplements the 
               <interface>org.castor.cache.CacheFactory</interface> interface 
               and make sure that you provide valid values for the two 
               properties <literal>name</literal> and <literal>className</literal>.
            </para>    
       
            <para>
               To assist users in this task, a 
               <classname>org.castor.cache.AbstractCacheFactory</classname> 
               class has been supplied, which users should derive their custom 
               <interface>org.castor.cache.CacheFactory</interface> instances 
               from, if they wish so. Please consult existing 
               <interface>org.castor.cache.CacheFactory</interface> implementations 
               such as <classname>org.castor.cache.simple.TimeLimitedFactory</classname>} or 
               <classname>org.castor.cache.simple.CountLimitedFactory</classname> 
               for code samples.
            </para>    

            <programlisting language="java">
/**
 * My own cache factory implementation
 */ 
 public class <emphasis role="bold">CustomCacheFactory</emphasis> extends <emphasis role="bold">AbstractCacheFactory</emphasis> {
 
    /**
     * The name of the factory
     */
    <emphasis role="bold">private static final String NAME = "custom"</emphasis>;

    /**
     * Full class name of the underlying cache implementation.
     */
    <emphasis role="bold">private static final String CLASS_NAME = "my.company.project.CustomCache"</emphasis>; 
    
    /**
     * Returns the short alias for this factory instance.
     * @return The short alias name. 
     */
    <emphasis role="bold">public String getName()</emphasis> {
        return NAME;
    }
    
    /**
     * Returns the full class name of the underlying cache implementation.
     * @return The full cache class name. 
     */
    <emphasis role="bold">public String getCacheClassName()</emphasis> {
        return CLASS_NAME;   
    }
    
 }</programlisting> 
        </section>

        <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.custom-provider.configuration">
            <title>Configuration</title>
    
            <para>
               The file <filename>castor.properties</filename> holds a property
               <literal>org.castor.cache.Factories</literal> that enlists the available
               cache types through their related CacheFactory instances.
            </para>    

            <programlisting>
# 
# Cache implementations
# 
org.castor.cache.Factories=\
  org.castor.cache.simple.NoCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.TimeLimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.CountLimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.UnlimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.FKCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.JcsCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.JCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.CoherenceCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.OsCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.hashbelt.FIFOHashbeltFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.hashbelt.LRUHashbeltFactory</programlisting>

            <para>
               To add your custom cache implementation, please append the 
               fully-qualified class name to this list as shown below:
            </para>
       
            <programlisting>
# 
# Cache implementations
# 
org.castor.cache.Factories=\
  org.castor.cache.simple.NoCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.TimeLimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.CountLimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.simple.UnlimitedFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.FKCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.JcsCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.JCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.CoherenceCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.distributed.OsCacheFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.hashbelt.FIFOHashbeltFactory,\
  org.castor.cache.hashbelt.LRUHashbeltFactory,\
  <emphasis role="bold">org.whatever.somewhere.nevermind.CustomCache</emphasis></programlisting>
        </section>
    </section>
        
    <section id="advanced-jdo.caching.cachemanager">
      <title>CacheManager - monitoring and clearing caches</title>
   
	  <para>
	     Sometimes it is necessary to interact with Castor's (performance) caches to 
         e.g.  (selectively) clear a Castor cache of its content, or inquire about 
         whether a particular object instance (as identified by its identity) is 
         cached already.
      </para>
	     
	  <para>
	     For this purpose a 
         <classname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager</classname> can 
	     be obtained from a <classname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.Database</classname> 
         instance by issuing the following code:
      </para>
	  
	  <programlisting language="java">
	  
JDO jdo = ....;
Database db = jdo.getDatabase();
CacheManager manager = db.getCacheManager();
	  </programlisting>
	
	  <para>
	     This instance can subsequently be used to selectively clear the 
         Castor performance cache using one of the following methods:
      </para>
	     
	  <para>
	     <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
		        <methodname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager.expireCache()</methodname>
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
		        <methodname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager.expireCache(Class,Object)</methodname>
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
		        <methodname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager.expireCache(Class,Object[])</methodname>
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
		        <methodname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager.expireCache(Class[])</methodname>
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	     </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	     
	  <para>
	     To inquire whether an object has already been cached, please use the 
         following method:
      </para>

	  <para>
	     <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
	            <methodname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.CacheManager.isCached (Class, Object);</methodname>
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	     </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	     
	  <para>
	     Please note that once you have closed the Database instance from which you 
         have obtained the CacheManager, the CacheManager cannot be used anymore and 
         will throw a 
	     <exceptionname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.PersistenceException</exceptionname>.
	  </para>
   
   </section>    
  </section>
