<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.codehaus.org/jdo-other-features.xml">
  <properties>
    <title>Castor JDO - Advanced features</title>
    <author email="werner DOT guttmann AT gmx DOT net">Werner Guttmann</author>
    <abstract>
       Castor JDO - Advanced features
    </abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <title>Castor JDO - Advanced features</title>

    <header>
      <p>Reference: <api package="org.exolab.castor.jdo">The Java Data Objects API</api></p>
    </header>

    <section title="Introduction">
        
        <p>As explained at <a href="jdo-introduction.html">the introduction to Castor JDO</a>,
           Castor has support for many advanced features such as caching, depend relations, 
           inheritance, polymorphism, etc. The below sections detail these features, as their
           understanding is required to use Castor JDO in a performant and secure way.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Caching">
    
        <p>Castor maintains and properly locks one copy of the dirty checking cache for each 
           object it loads from or creates into persistence storage. Until all transactions 
           involving the object are completed (See 
           <a href="design-persist.html#Persistence">Design: Persistence</a>), the cache is released. 
           Starting from Castor 0.8.6, performance cache is implemented and developer can specify the 
           mechanism and capacity of performance cache for each persistence capable type. Options includes 
           'none', 'count-limited', 'time-limited' and 'unlimited'. Starting from Castor 0.9.9, the cache 
           types 'coherence', 'jcs', 'jcache' and 'fkcache' have been added as explaind below. Performance 
           cache is write-through, because all changes to objects of a transaction should be persisted 
           at commit time without delay.</p>

        <p>Performance caches enhance the application performance by reducing the number of read 
           operations against the persistence storage, by storing and reusing the last read or 
           committed values of the object. Performance caches do not affect the behavior of 
           short transactions or locking. It only affects persistence objects that have been released 
           from any transactional context. </p>

        <p>With the current release, performance caches also serve a dual purpose as dirty checking 
           caches for <a href="long-transact.html">long-transactions</a>. This limitation implies that 
           the object's duration in the performance cache determines the allowed time span of a long 
           transaction. This might become an issue when performance caches of type 'count-limited' or 
           'time-limited' are being used, as objects will eventually be disposed. If an application 
           tries to update an object that has been disposed from the dirty checking cache, 
           an ObjectModifedException will be thrown.</p>

        <p>The DTD declaration is as follows:
           <code-panel><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT cache-type  ( param* )>
<!ATTLIST cache-type
    type           ( none | count-limited | time-limited | unlimited |
                     coherence | fkcache | jcache | jcs | oscache |
                     fifo | lru ) "count-limited"
    debug          (true|false) "false"
    capacity       NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED>

<!ELEMENT param EMPTY>
<!ATTLIST param
          name   NMTOKEN  #REQUIRED
          value  NMTOKEN  #REQUIRED>]]></code-panel></p>
          
        <p>With release 1.0 of Castor the DTD has changed but it is backward compatible
           to the old one and allows to enable debugging of cache access for a specific
           class as well as passing individual configuration parameters to each cache
           instance. Only <b>count-limited</b> and <b>time-limited</b> of the current
           cache types support parameters. Parameter names are case sensitive and are
           silently ignored if they are unknown to a cache type.</p>
                   
        <p>It need to be noted that there are 3 parameter names that are reserved for
           internal use. If you specify a parameter with one of the names: <b>type</b>,
           <b>name</b> or <b>debug</b> their value will silently be overwritten with
           another one used internally.</p>
                
        <p>A <b>count-limited</b> least-recently-used cache (LRU) for 500 objects can be
           specified by:
           <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="count-limited" capacity="500"/>]]></code-panel>
           or
           <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="count-limited"/>
    <param name="capacity" value="500"/>
</cache-type>]]></code-panel>
           If both, the capacity attribute and parameter with name="capacity" is
           specified, the parameter value takes precedence over the attribute value.</p>
                
        <p>A <b>time-limited</b> first-in-first-out cache (FIFO) that expires objects
           after 15 minutes can be specified by:
           <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="time-limited" capacity="900"/>]]></code-panel>
           or
           <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="time-limited"/>
    <param name="ttl" value="900"/>
</cache-type>]]></code-panel>
           If both, the capacity attribute and parameter with name="ttl" is specified,
           the parameter value takes precedence over the attribute value.</p>
                   
        <p>The <b>debug</b> attribute can be used to enable debugging for objects
           of a single class. In addition to setting this attribut to <b>true</b> you
           also need to set logging level of <b>org.castor.cache.Cache</b> to debug.</p>

        <p><b>NOTE:</b> The default cache-type is <tt>count-limited</tt> with a capacity of 30. This will 
           be used when no cache-type is specified in the mapping for a class.</p>
        
        <p><b>NOTE:</b> As of release 0.9.6, Castor allows for the addition of user-defined cache 
           implementations. Instructions can be found <a href="jdo-caching.html">here</a></p>

        <p><b>NOTE:</b> As of release 0.9.9, three new cache types have been added to Castor, three
            of them open source and one commercial.</p>
            
        <ctable>
            <cheader>
                <th>name</th>
                <th>Vendor</th>
                <th>Version</th>
            </cheader>
            <crow>
                <td>coherence</td>
                <td><url href="http://www.tangosol.com/coherence.jsp">Tangosol Coherence</url></td>
                <td>2.5</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jcs</td>
                <td><url href="http://jakarta.apache.org/jcs">JCS</url></td>
                <td>1.2.5</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>fkcache</td>
                <td><url href="http://jcache.sourceforge.net/">FKCache</url></td>
                <td>1.0-beta6</td>
            </crow>
        </ctable>
        
        <p>As some of these cache providers allow for allow you to use it in a <b>distributed</b> 
           mode, this allows Castor JDO to be used in a clustered (multi-JVM) environment. Please see
           the section below for short summayr fo this feature.</p>
        
        <p>For problems related to the use of performance caches, please consult with the relevant 
           entries in the <a href="jdo-faq.html#Castor and performance caches">JDO F.A.Q.</a>.</p>
        
        <p><b>NOTE:</b> As of release 1.0, another three new cache types have been added to Castor,
            one being a distributed open source cache and two new internal cache implementations
            intended for high volunm and high performance.</p>
            
        <ctable>
            <cheader>
                <th>name</th>
                <th>Vendor</th>
                <th>Version</th>
            </cheader>
            <crow>
                <td>oscache</td>
                <td><url href="http://www.opensymphony.com/oscache/">OSCache</url></td>
                <td>2.5</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>fifo</td>
                <td>Castor</td>
                <td></td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>lru</td>
                <td>Castor</td>
                <td></td>
            </crow>
        </ctable>
        
        <section title="fifo and lru cache providers">

                <p>The cache types <b>fifo</b> and <b>lru</b> are based on a set of articles in the
                   O'Reilly Network by William Grosso, to implement a simplified and 1.3-compatible
                   implementation of a Hashbelt algorithm.</p>

                <p>Hashbelts are simple, in principle. Instead of walking all objects and finding out
                   when they're supposed to expire, use a "conveyor belt" approach. At any particular
                   point in time, objects going into the cache go into the front of the conveyor belt.
                   After a certain amount of time or when the size limit of a container has been
                   reached, move the conveyor belt - put a new, empty container at the front of the
                   conveyor belt to catch new objects, and the one that drops off of the end of the
                   conveyor belt is, by definition, ready for garbage collection.</p>

                <p>As seen in his system, you can use a set of pluggable strategies to implement the
                   actual hashbelt bits. A container strategy allows you to change out the
                   implementation of the container itself - from simple hashtable-based
                   implementations, up through more complex uses of soft referenced or hashset-based
                   implementations, depending on what you need and what you want it to be used for.
                   A pluggable "expire behavior" handler allows you to determine what action is taken
                   on something which drops off of the bottom of the conveyor belt.</p>

				<p>In difference to all other cache types the <b>fifo</b> and <b>lru</b> cache
                   types offer various configuration options. Both of them have 6 parameters to
                   configure their behaviour.</p>

                <ctable>
                    <cheader>
                        <th align="left">parameter</th>
                        <th align="left">description</th>
                    </cheader>
                    <crow>
                        <td>containers</td>
                        <td>The number of containers in the conveyor belt. For example: If a box
                            will drop off of the conveyor belt every 30 seconds, and you want a cache
                            that lasts for 5 minutes, you want 5 / 30 = 6 containers on the belt. Every
                            30 seconds, another, clean container goes on the front of the conveyor belt,
                            and everything in the last belt gets discarded. If not specified 10 containers
                            are used by default.
                            <br/>
                            For systems with fine granularity, you are free to use a large number of
                            containers; but the system is most efficient when the user decides on a
                            "sweet spot" determining both the number of containers to be managed on the
                            whole and the optimal number of buckets in those containers for managing. This
                            is ultimately a performance/accuracy tradeoff with the actual discard-from-cache
                            time being further from the mark as the rotation time goes up. Also the number
                            of objects discarded at once when capacity limit is reached depends upon the
                            number of containers.
                        </td>
                    </crow>
                    <crow>
                        <td>capacity</td>
                        <td>Maximum capacity of the whole cache. If there are, for example, ten
                            containers on the belt and the capacity has been set to 1000, each container
                            will hold a maximum of 1000/10 objects. Therefore if the capacity limit is
                            reached and the last container gets droped from the belt there are up to 100
                            objects discarted at once. By default the capacity is set to 0 which causes
                            capacity limit to be ignored so the cache can hold an undefined number of
                            objects.
                        </td>
                    </crow>
                    <crow>
                        <td>ttl</td>
                        <td>The maximum time an object lifes in cache. If the are, for example, ten
                            containers and ttl is set to 300 seconds (5 minutes), a new container will be
                            put in front of the belt every 300/10 = 30 seconds while another is dropped at
                            the end at the same time. Due to the granularity of 30 seconds, everything just
                            until 5 minutes 30 seconds will also end up in this box. The default value for
                            ttl is 60 seconds. If ttl is set to 0 which means that objects life in cache
                            for unlimited time and may only discarded by a capacity limit.
                        </td>
                    </crow>
                    <crow>
                        <td>monitor</td>
                        <td>The monitor intervall in minutes when hashbelt cache rports the current
                            number of containers used and objects cached. If set to 0 (default) monitoring
                            is disabled.
                        </td>
                    </crow>
                    <crow>
                        <td>container-class</td>
                        <td>The implementation of <b>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.Container</b>
                            interface to be used for all containers of the cache. Castor provides the following
                            3 implementations of the Container interface.
                            <ul>
                                <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.FastIteratingContainer</li>
                                <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.MapContainer</li>
                                <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.WeakReferenceContainer</li>
                            </ul>
                            If not specified the MapContainer will be used as default.
                        </td>
                    </crow>
                    <crow>
                        <td>reaper-class</td>
                        <td>Specific reapers yield different behaviors. The GC reaper, the default,
                            just dumps the contents to the garbage collector. However, custom
                            implementations may want to actually do something when a bucket drops off the
                            end; see the javadocs on other available reapers to find a reaper strategy
                            that meets your behavior requirements. Apart of the default
                            <b>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NullReaper</b> we provide 3 abstract
                            implementations of <b>org.castor.cahe.hashbelt.reaper.Reaper</b> interface:
                            <ul>
                                <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NotifyingReaper</li>
                                <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.RefreshingReaper</li>
                                <li>org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.ReinsertingReaper</li>
                            </ul>
                            to be extended by your custom implementation.
                        </td>
                    </crow>
                </ctable>

                <p>A <b>fifo</b> cache with default values explained above is specified by:
                   <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="fifo"/>]]></code-panel></p>

                <p>A <b>lru</b> cache with capacity=300 and ttl=300 is defined by:
                   <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="lru" capacity="300"/>]]></code-panel>
                   or better by:
                   <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="lru"/>
    <param name="capacity" value="300"/>
    <param name="ttl" value="300"/>
</cache-type>]]></code-panel></p>

                <p>An example of a customized configuration of a <b>fifo</b> cache is:
                   <code-panel><![CDATA[
<cache-type type="fifo"/>
    <param name="container" value="10"/>
    <param name="capacity" value="1000"/>
    <param name="ttl" value="600"/>
    <param name="monitor" value="5"/>
    <param name="container-class" value="org.castor.cache.hashbelt.container.WeakReferenceContainer"/>
    <param name="reaper-class" value="org.castor.cache.hashbelt.reaper.NullReaper"/>
</cache-type>]]></code-panel></p>

        </section>

        <section title="Caching and clustered environments">
    
            <p>All of the cache providers added with release 0.9.9 are distributed caches per se or can be 
            configured to operate in such a mode. This effectively allows Castor JDO to be used in a 
            clustered J2EE (multi-JVM) environment, where Castor JDO runs on each of the cluster instances,
            and where cache state is automatically snychronized between these instances.</p>
            
            <p>In such an environment, Castor JDO wil make use of the underlying cache provider 
            to replicate/distribute the content of a specific cache between the various 
            JDOManager instances. Through the distribution mechanism of the cache provider, a client
            of a Castor JDO instance on one JVM will see any updates made to domain objects performed 
            against any other JVM/JDO instance.</p>
    
            <p>The following class mapping, for example, ... </p>
            
                <code-panel><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xyz.MyOtherObject">
        <cache-type type="coherence" />
        <field name= ... >
               ...
        </field>
    </class>
</mapping>]]></code-panel>
    
            <p>defines that for all objects of type <tt>com.xyz.MyOtherObject</tt> Tangosol's 
            <i>Coherence</i> cache provider should be used.</p>
            
        </section>
    
        <section title="Custom cache provider">
     
           <p>Castor provides a set of pre-built cache providers, offering a variety
              of different cache algorithms. Nevertheless, special needs might
              require the application developer to implement a custom cache 
              algorithm. Castor facilitates such need by making available standardized
              interfaces and an easy to understand recipe for integrating a custom 
              cache provider with Castor.</p>
            
           <p>The main component of Castor's cache system is the interface 
              <api class="org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.Cache"><tt>Cache</tt></api>, 
              which declares required functionality of a performance cache provider. 
              Existing (and future) cache implementations have to implement this 
              interface, which is closely modelled after <tt>java.util.Map</tt>.</p>
              
           <p>Below are defined the steps to build a custom cache provider and register
              it with Castor JDO.</p>
    
           <p><ol>
                <li>Create a class that implements 
                    <api class="org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.Cache"><tt>Cache</tt></api>
                   (we have provided an abstract base class that you can use at your
                   convenience).</li>
                <li>Create a class that implements 
                    <api class="org.exolab.castor.persist.cache.CacheFactory">CacheFactory</api>
                   (we have provided an abstract base class that you can use at your
                   convenience).</li>
                <li>Register your custom cache implementation with Castor JDO in the
                    <tt>castor.properties</tt> file.</li>
            </ol></p>
    
            <p>Detailed instructions can be found in one of the 
               <a href="jdo-howto.html">Castor JDO HOW-TO</a> documents.</p>
            
        </section>
        
    </section>
    
    <section title="Dependent and related relationships">
        
        <p>Castor distinguishes the relationship of two objects as dependent or related, and 
           maintains the life cycle independently for the two types of relationships. Starting 
           from Castor 0.9, the developer can explicitly define a dependent relationship in 
           the mapping file.</p>

        <p>When using independent relations, related objects’ life cycle is independent of each 
           other, meaning that they have to be created, removed and updated (for long 
           transaction) independently.</p>

        <p>When using dependent relations, one data object class must be declared as 
           <b>depends</b> on one other data object class in the mapping file, and such an object 
           is called a dependent data object class. A data object class without 
           <i>depends</i> declared in the mapping is called a master object. A master object can 
           be depended upon by zero or more dependent data object class.</p>

        <p>As of Castor 0.9, a dependent object class can be related to other master data 
           object classes including extended classes, but cannot depend on more than one 
           master class.</p>

        <p>If an object class declared as <i>depends</i> on another class, it may not be 
           created, removed or updated separately. Attempting to create, remove or update a 
           dependent object will result in ObjectNotPersistcapableException. Note that Castor 
           doesn'’t allow a dependent object instance to change its master object instance during 
           a transaction. Each dependent object can have only one master object. Both dependent and 
           master objects must have identities, and may or may not make use of key-generators.</p>

        <p>
            Here is the DTD for declaring dependent object:
            
             <code-panel><![CDATA[
<!ATTLIST class     name ID  #REQUIRED
          extends   IDREF    #IMPLIED
          depends   IDREF    #IMPLIED
          identity  CDATA   #IMPLIED
          access    ( read-only | shared | exclusive | db-locked )  "shared"
          key-generator   IDREF #IMPLIED]]></code-panel></p>

        <p>
            For example,
            
                <code-panel><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xyz.MyDependentObject"
        depends="com.xyz.MyObject">
        ...
    </class>
</mapping>]]></code-panel>
                declares the data object class <tt>com.xyz.MyDependentObject</tt> as a dependent 
                upon class <tt>com.xyz.MyObject</tt>.</p>
    </section>

    <section title="Different cardinalities of relationship">
        
         <p>Castor supports different cardinalities of relationship, namely one-to-one, 
            one-to-many, and many-to-many. Many-to-many relationship must be related rather than 
            dependent, because each dependent object can have only one master object. </p>

        <p>Many-to-many requires a separate table for storing the relations between two types of 
           objects. Many-to-many introduces two attributes, namely many-key and many-table that reside 
           in the <tt>&lt;sql&gt;</tt> element which is a sub-element of the <tt>&lt;field&gt;</tt>
           element. For all many-to-many relations, a many-table must be specified. If the column 
           name of the primary key of the class is different from the foreign keys columns of the 
           class in the relation tables, then the relation table columns can be specified using the 
           many-key attributes. Similarly, if the column name of the primary key of the related class 
           is different from the foreign key columns of the related class, then the relation table 
           columns can be specified using the name attribute. </p>

        <p>The many-table is used to store relations in a separate table
            
                <code-panel><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class>
        <field>
            <sql many-key="#OPTIONAL" name="#OPTIONAL"
                 many-table="#REQURIED">
        </field>
    </class>
</mapping>]]></code-panel>
        </p>

        <p>
            So, for example, if the SQL table is the following,
            <center>
                <b>employee_table</b></center>

            <center><table BORDER="true" COLS="3" WIDTH="60%" >
                <tr ALIGN="CENTER">
                    <td><b>id</b></td>   <td><b>name</b></td>      <td><b>salary</b></td>
                </tr>

                <tr>
                    <td>1482</td>        <td>Smith, Bob</td>       <td>$123,456</td>
                </tr>

                <tr>
                    <td>628</td>         <td>Lee, John</td>        <td>$43,210</td>
                </tr>

                <tr>
                    <td>1926</td>        <td>Arnold, Pascal</td>   <td>$24,680</td>
                </tr></table></center>

                <center>
                <b>department_table</b></center>

                <center><table BORDER="true" COLS="3" WIDTH="60%" >
                    <tr ALIGN="CENTER">
                        <td><b>id</b></td>   <td><b>name</b></td>      <td><b>comment</b></td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                         <td>3</td>          <td>Accounting</td>       <td></td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                         <td>7</td>          <td>Engineering</td>      <td>The very important department. :-)</td>
                    </tr>
                </table></center>

                <center>
                <b>employee_department</b></center>

                <center><table BORDER="true" COLS="2" WIDTH="40%" >
                    <tr ALIGN="CENTER">
                         <td><b>e_id</b></td>  <td><b>d_id</b></td>
                    </tr>

                    <tr>
                         <td>....</td>         <td>....</td>
                    </tr>
                </table></center></p>

        <p>
            Then, the mapping for employee data object would look like this
                <code-panel><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xyz.Employee" identity="id">
        <map-to table="employee_table"/>
            <field name="id" type="integer">
                <sql name="id"/>
            </field>
            <field>
                <sql many-table="employee_department"
                     many-key="e_id" name="d_id"/>
            </field>
            <field name="salary">
                <sql name="salary" type="integer">
            </field>
    </class>
</mapping>]]></code-panel></p>

    </section>

    <section title="Lazy Loading">

		<p>As of release 0.9.6, Castor has full support for lazy loading object instances referenced
		   as part of all relation types currently supported:</p>
		   
		<ul>
			<li>1:1 relations</li>
			<li>1:m relations</li>
			<li>M:N relations.</li>
		</ul>
		   
        <section title="1:1 relations">
        
        	<p>As of release 0.9.6, Castor supports lazy-loading of 1:1 relations. Imagine the 
        	   following class mapping:</p>

			<code-panel><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xzy.Department">
       ...
       <field "employee" type="com.xyz.Employee" lazy="true" />
       ...
    </class>
</mapping>]]></code-panel>
        	   
			<p>Per definition, when an instance of Department is loaded through e.g. Database.load(),
			   Castor will not (pre-)load the Employee instance referenced (as such reducing the size
			   pf the initial query as well as the size of the result set returned). Only when the 
			   Emplyoee instance is accessed through Department.getEmployee(), Castor will load 
			   the actual object into memory from the persistence store.</p>
			   
			<p>This means that if the Employee instance is not accessed at all, not only will 
			   the initial query to load the Department object have had its complexity reduced, 
			   but no performance penalty will be incurred for the additional access to the 
			   persistence store either.</p>
			   
        </section>
    
        <section title="1:M and M:N relations">
    
           <p>The elements in the collection are only loaded when the application asks for 
              the object from the collection, using, for example, iterator.next(). The 
              iterator in Castor’s lazy collection is optimized to return a loaded object 
              first.</p>
  
           <p>In the mapping file, lazy loading is specified in the element of the collection’s 
              <tt>&lt;field></tt>, for example,</p>
           
            <code-panel><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xzy.Department">
       ...
        <field name="employee" type="com.xyz.Employee" lazy="true"
               collection="collection"/>
    </class>
</mapping>]]></code-panel>

            <p>declares that the collection of type Employee in a Department is lazy loaded.</p>

           <p>If lazy loading is specified for a field of a class, Castor will set the field with a 
              special collection which contains only the identities of the objects. Because of 
              that, it requires the data object to have the method setDepartment( Collection 
              department) in the data object class which was not required in previous 
              versions.</p>

           <p><b>Note:</b> Please note that currently <b>only</b> the <tt><b>java.util.Collection</b></tt> 
              type is supported. <!--The following collection types are supported:
              java.util.Array, java.util.Vector, java.util.Hashtable, java.util.Collection, 
              java.util.Set and java.util.Map. --></p>
              
           </section>
           
     </section>

     <section title="Multiple columns primary keys">
        <p>
            The support of multiple column primary keys (also called compound primary keys) was another major enhancement added into Castor 0.9. Specifying multiple column primary keys is simple and straightforward, in the mapping file, 
            <code-panel><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xyz.MyObject" identity="firstName lastName">
        <field name="firstName" type="string">
           <sql name="fname"/>
        </field>
        <field name="lastName" type="string">
           <sql name="lname"/>
        </field>
           ...
    </class>
</mapping>]]></code-panel></p>

        <p>Multiple column primary keys work with both master and dependent objects, all 
           cardinalities of relationship, including one-to-one, one-to-many and many-to-many, 
           as well as lazy loading. </p>

        <p>However, multiple column primary keys should only be used to adhere to an existing 
           database design, not when designing a new database. In general, it is not a good 
           idea to use an identity or identities which can be modified by the user, or which 
           contain application-visible data. For example, if the system allows the user name to 
           be changed, using user name as identity is highly discouraged, as this practice can require 
           a major data migration to a new schema to update all foreign keys to adhere to a 
           new primary key structure, should the user name no longer be adequate as a primary key. It should 
           be noted that Castor doesn’t support identity change, as specified in the ODMG 3.0 
           specification. So, primary keys changes are almost certainly a large trade off between 
           data integrity and performance. Well chosen primary keys are usually single (not 
           multiple) column numeric or character fields for the reasons outlined above, as well as 
           performance, as joining operations are faster for single column primary keys. </p>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Callback interface for persistent operations">
        
         <p>For the various persistence operations as available through the 
            <api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.Database">Database</api> 
            interface, Castor JDO provides a callback interface that informs the 
            implementing class on events taking place related to selected
            persistence operations.</p>
            
         <p>Once your entity class implements the 
            <api class="org.exolab.castor.jdo.Persistence">Persistence</api> interface, 
            you'll have to provide implementations for the following methods (with their
            respective semantics described next to them):</p>
            
         <ctable>
            <cheader>
                <th>Method</th>
                <th>Description</th>
            </cheader>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoAfterCreate()</td>
                <td>Indicates that an object has been created in persistent storage.</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoAfterRemove()</td>
                <td>Indicates that an object has been removed from persistent storage.</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoBeforeCreate()</td>
                <td>Indicates that an object is to be created in persistent storage.</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoBeforeRemove()</td>
                <td>Indicates that an object is to be removed from persistent storage.</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoLoad()</td>
                <td>Indicates that the object has been loaded from persistent storage.</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoPersistent(Database)</td>
                <td>Sets the database to which this object belongs when this object becomes persistent.</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoStore()</td>
                <td>Indicates that an object is to be stored in persistent storage.</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoTransient()</td>
                <td>Indicates the object is now transient.</td>
            </crow>
            <crow>
                <td>jdoUpdate()</td>
                <td>Indicates that an object has been included to the current transaction by 
                    means of db.update() method (in other words, at the end of a 
                    "long" transaction).</td>
            </crow>
         </ctable>
        
      </section>

   </body>
</document>
