<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="jpa" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Castor JDO - Support for the JPA specification</title>

    <section id="jpa.why">
        <title>JPA annotations - Motivation</title>
    
        <para>
            It has always been a goal of the Castor JDO project to 
            eventually fully support the JPA specification and become a 
            first class JPA provider that can e.g. be easily integrated
            with Spring ORM. Whilst full compliance is still work 
            in progress, there are several small areas where sufficient 
            progress has been made, and where partial support 
            will be made available to the user community.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            One such area is (partial) support for JPA annotations. This chapter 
            highlights how JPA-annotated Java classes can be used with 
            Castor JDO to persist such classes through the existing persistence 
            framework part of Castor, without little additional requirements.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The following sections describe ...
        </para>
        
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The prerequisites.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The current limitations.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The supported JPA annotations.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>How to use Castor JDO to persist JPA-annotated classes.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>How to use Castor JDO as Spring ORM provider to persist JPA-annotated classes.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>   
    
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Prerequisites and outline</title>
        
        <para>
            The following sections assume that you have a (set of) JPA-annotated
            domain classes which you would like to persist using
            Castor JDO.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            As such, we explain how to enlist those classes with
            Castor JDO (through the <classname>JDOClassDescriptorResolver</classname>
            interface, so that Castor JDO will be able to find and work with your
            JPA-annotated classes. In addition, we explain how to achieve the same
            with Spring ORM and the Spring ORM provider for Castor JDO.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            By the end of this chapter is should become obvious that 
            Castor JDO is well-prepared to integrate with the annotation part of the
            JPA specification, although support for JPA annotations is 
            currently limited.
        </para>
        
    </section>
  
    <section id="jpa.annotations.limitations">
        <title>Limitations and Basic Information</title>
    
        <section>
            <title>persistence.xml</title>
            <para>
                 In Castor JPA there is no use or support for a JPA
                 <filename>persistence.xml</filename> configuration file for 
                 now. All required configuration needs to be supplied by one 
                 of the following means:
            </para>
                
            <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para>Castor JDO configuration file.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><classname>JDOClassDescriptorResolver</classname> configuration.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para>Spring configuration file for the Spring ORM provider for Castor JDO.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
        </section>
    
        <section>
            <title>JPA access type and the placing of JPA annotations</title>
            
            <para>
                Because Castor does not support direct field access, this 
                feature is not supported by Castor JPA. Thus all annotations have 
                to be defined on the getter methods of the fields. If JPA related 
                annotations are found on fields, Castor will throw an 
                exception.
            </para>
            
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Primary Keys</title>
            
            <para>		
                Primary keys made of single fields are supported by Castor as defined 
                in the JPA specification (through the use of the <literal>@Id</literal> annotation). If 
                you need to define composite primary keys, please note that that 
                Castor does <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> support relations 
                with composite primary keys.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                If you still want to persist single classes with the use of 
                composite primary keys, none of the available JPA annotations 
                (<literal>@EmbeddedId</literal> or <literal>@IdClass</literal>) is supported as such. Instead Castor 
                uses a kind of ad-hoc <literal>IdClass</literal> mechanism. Simply 
                define multiple <literal>@Id</literal> annotations on the fields that make up your 
                composite primary key, and Castor JDO will internally create the 
                relevant constructs.
            </para>
            
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Inheritance, mapped superclasses, etc.</title>
            
            <para>
                These JPA annotations are currently <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis>
                supported by Castor JDO. For now, you can only define entities.
            </para>
            
        </section>
    
        <section>
            <title>Relations</title>
            
            <para>
                Besides the fact, that Castor does not support composite primary keys 
                in relations, there are some limitations on the different kinds of 
                relations between entities. For detailed information, please read the 
                documentation about the different relations types further below.
            </para>
            
        </section>
    
  </section>
  
  <xi:include href="jpa/annotations.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="jpa/configuration.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="jpa/configuration-spring.xml"/>

</chapter>
