<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.org/tutorial/how-to-sumit-a-bug/main.xml">
  <properties>
    <title>How to submit a patch at Jira</title>
    <abstract>
       General information about submitting a patch at Jira
    </abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <title>How to submit a patch at Jira</title>
    <header>
    </header>
    
	<section title="Overview">

        <p>A "Patch" is the set of differences between two versions of the same file. Patches are used to 
           send someone the exact changes that you have made to your version of a program or a 
           document. They can then apply that patch to their version to merge the changes and bring 
           their version up-to-date with your version.</p>

        <p>As our example we use the contribution of a simple documentation patch for the 
        Castor project. The principles apply to any project and to any type of file, e.g. 
        *.xml, *.java, *.xsd, etc.</p>
        
    </section>
    
    <section title="Intended Audience">

        <p>Anyone who wants to contribute to a project. This document addresses the basics, 
        so as to get new people started.</p>

        <p>Our example describes the use of command-line tools for a UNIX system. Other 
        tools can be used, as long as they produce a "unified diff".</p>
        
    </section>
    
    <section title="Prerequisites">

        <p>Contributers should have:</p>

        <ul>
            <li>The source code of the documents as a local working copy of the CVS 
                repository. If you are working with the current CVS HEAD then you will 
                have already done a 'cvs checkout castor' (see CVS Usage Precis). However, see 
                below for other ways of obtaining source for diff comparison.</li>
            <li>The tools with which to prepare a patch. On UNIX the "cvs" program has the 
                <tt>cvs diff -u</tt> command.</li>
        </ul>
            
    </section>

    <section title="Steps">

        <p>Here is how to proceed.</p>

        <section title="Understand what a patch is">

            <p>A "Patch" is the set of differences between two versions of the same file. A 
            patch comprises one or more "diff" files. These diffs are produced by the program 
            of the same name: diff.</p>

            <p>Here is an example of a single diff for one of the Castor How-to pages,
            where we are suggesting a minor text change. Do not get frightened. These are 
            just human-readable instructions to the "patch" program.</p>

<code-panel>
Index: contrib.xml
===================================================================
RCS file: /home/projects/castor/src/doc/jdo-howto.xml,v
retrieving revision 1.7
diff -u -r1.7 contrib.xml
--- jdo-howto.xml 30 Apr 2002 07:44:52 -0000      1.7
+++ jdo-howto.xml 26 May 2002 04:08:23 -0000
@@ -208,7 +208,7 @@
    to create a patch. (The commands are for Linux.)
   &lt;/p&gt;

- &lt;s2 title="How to Establish your Local Repository"&gt;
+ &lt;s2 title="How to Establish your Local Working Copy"&gt;

   &lt;p&gt;
    This will checkout the current copy of the master cvs repository and
</code-panel>

            <p>That is a "unified diff" ... there a some lines of context on each side of the 
            changes. This patch is basically saying "Change the text on line 208".</p>

            <ul>
                <li>lines to be deleted are preceded with -</li>
                <li>lines to be added are preceded with +</li>
                <li>contextual lines with no leader remain the same</li>
            </ul>

        </section>

        <section title="Modify your document and ensure consistency">

            <p>Let us now go though the process of preparing that patch. Go ahead and 
            edit your local copy of the document at 
            $CASTOR_HOME/src/doc/jdo-howto.xml.</p>

            <p>Ensure that it is valid XML using your favourite XML editor or an external 
            validating parser. Please do not leave it up to the poor committer to fix 
            broken XML.</p>

            <p>Run the 'build doc' target to be sure that links are not broken and that the new 
            document is presented as you intend it to be.</p>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Get ready">
            
            <p>If you are using the HEAD of CVS then ensure that your working copy is 
            up-to-date. Of course, if you are using a previous public release version 
            of Cocoon, then it is already up-to-date.</p>
            
        </section>

        <section title="Generate the differences">
            
            <p>Prepare the diff file. CVS will contact the remote repository, ensure that 
            your working copy is up-to-date, then compare your local copy with the 
            master repository.</p>

<code-panel>
    cd src/doc
    cvs diff -u jdo-howto.xml > $TEMP/castor/patch/jdo-howto.xml.diff
</code-panel>
            
        </section>

        <section title="Describe the patch">
            
            <p>Prepare a brief explanation of what your patch does. Get this ready in a 
            text file before you go to Jira. See further hints about this in 
            the "Description" section of the How-to Jira.</p>

            <p>What version of CVS did you patch against? Was it HEAD branch? Was 
            it a nightly build? Was it a public release?</p>
            
        </section>

        <section title="Submit via Jira">
            
            <p>To contribute your patch to a specific project, use Jira - The Codehaus Issue Database. The 
            procedure is explained in How to Contribute a Patch via Jira.</p>
            
        </section>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Real World Extension">
        
        <section title="Multiple diffs in a single patch">

            <p>A patchfile can contain the differences to various individual documents. For example,
            the following command does that ...</p>

<code-panel>
cd src
cvs diff -u > $WORK/castor/patch/src.dir.diff
</code-panel>

            <p>However, be careful not to go overboard with this technique. When producing 
            multiple diffs in one patchfile, try to limit it to one particular topic, i.e 
            when fixing the same broken external link in various pages, then it would be fine 
            to produce a single diff. Consider the committer - they will find it hard to apply 
            your patch if it also attempts to fix other things.</p>
            
        </section>        


        <section title="Other ways of obtaining source for diff comparison">
            
            <p>Ideally you will prepare your patches against a CVS repository. There are other 
            ways to do this. They do create more work for the committers, however it may 
            be the only way that you can do it. We would certainly rather receive your 
            patch however it comes. As a mtter of fact, we would politeky ask you 
            first to send us a unified patch.</p>

            <p>You could get the source document via the web interface to CVS. Here are the steps ...</p>

            <ul>
                <li>get the relevant XML file via ViewCVS</li>
                <li>save the file to your local disk: ./jdo-howto.xml.orig</li>
                <li>create a copy of the file: ./jdo-howto.xml</li>
                <li>make your modifications and validate the XML</li>
                <li>use the "diff" command (i.e. not 'cvs diff') as follows</li>
                <li><tt>diff -u jdo-howto.xml.orig jdo-howto.xml > $WORK/castor/patch/jdo-howto.xml.diff</tt></li>
                <li>proceed as for Step 5.</li>
            </ul>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Tips">

        <ul>
            <li>Please review your diffs before you submit your patch to Bugzilla</li>
        </ul>    
        
    </section>


    <section title="References">

        <ul>
            <li>The UNIX manual pages 'man diff' and 'man patch'.</li>
            <li>CVS usage information is at www.cvshome.org and your local 'info cvs' 
                pages or 'man cvs' pages or user documentation. This includes guidance 
                about using cvs diff -u</li>
        </ul>
    
        
    </section>


    </body>
</document>