<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://castor.org/tutorial/how-to-run-do-ctf-suite.xml">
  <properties>
    <title>How to run Castor JDO's CTF suite</title>
    <abstract>
       General information about running Castor JDO's CTF suite
    </abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <title>How to run Castor JDO's CTF suite</title>
    <header>
    </header>
    
	<section title="Overview">

        <p>Castor JDO has a JUnit test suite that is used to test various functional 
           areas, and to give developers/committers some reassurance when changing the 
           codebase.</p>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Intended Audience">

        <p>Anyone who wants to run the CTF test suite. This document outlines the basic 
           steps to get people unfamiliar with this area started.</p>

        <p>Our example describes the use of command-line tools for a UNIX system.</p>
        
    </section>
    
    <section title="Prerequisites">

        <p>Anybody wishing to run the CTF test suite should have access to the 
           source code of Castor. This can be obtained in one of the following 
           ways:</p>

        <ul>
            <li>Download the sources distribution from the 
                <a href="download.html">download page</a></li>
            
            <li>download the latest snapshot from CVS from (see links on the bottom 
                left corner): <a href="http://cvs.castor.codehaus.org/viewrep/castor/castor">here</a></li>
            <li>Check out the latest code from CVS into your prefered developement 
                environment. For instructions on this task, take a look
                <a href="cvs.html">here</a></li>
        </ul>
        
        
    </section>

    <section title="Steps">

        <p>Once you have obtained the Castor sources in one of the ways highlighted above,
           here is how to proceed. In general, more information about how to 
           execute the CTF test suite can be found <a href="test-framework.html">here</a>.</p>


        <p>From a command line (e.g a shell), please execute the following
           commands to run the test suite against <i>mySQL</i> (where
           &lt;castor-root&gt; points to the directory where you installed
           the Castor sources:</p>
           
        <code-panel>
cd &lt;castor-root&gt;/bin
build clean
build tests
test castor.mysql</code-panel>
        
        <p>To execute just one of the many tests of of the complete test suite, 
           please change this to:</p>
           

        <code-panel>
cd &lt;castor-root&gt;/bin
build clean
build tests
test castor.mysql.TC01</code-panel>
           
    </section>
    
    <section title="References">

        <ul>
            <li><a href="test-framework.html">The testing framework</a></li>
            <li><a href="cvs.html">Access to CVS</a></li>
        </ul>
    
        
    </section>


    </body>
</document>