<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="jdo.introduction">
    <sectioninfo>
      <authorgroup>
	     <author>
	        <firstname>Werner</firstname>
	        <surname>Guttmann</surname>  
	        <email>werner DOT guttmann AT gmx DOT net</email>
	     </author>
	  </authorgroup>
    </sectioninfo>
    
<!-- 
    Status: Final
-->    
    
  <title>Castor JDO - An introduction</title>

  <section id="jdo.introduction.what">
     <title>What is Castor JDO</title>
        
     <para>
       Castor JDO is an Object-Relational Mapping and Data-Binding Framework, which is 
       written in 100% pure Java[tm]. Castor can map relational database data into 
       Java Data Object based on user-defined mapping schema. In the other point-of-view, 
       it provides java data objects a persistence layer.
     </para>

     <para>
       It frees programmer from dealing with database directly and replacing the entire 
       burden of composing updating the database. Proper SQL statements are automatically 
       generated for loading, updating, creating and deleting. Changes to objects in transaction 
       are automatically done to data source at commit time. Thus programmer can stay in pure-Java
       without remember all the details in the backing database, after the creation of 
       database tables and the mapping schema. The separation of persistence and programming 
       logic also enable much clearer object-oriented design, which is important in larger 
       projects.
     </para>
  </section>
 
  <section id="jdo.introduction.features">
     <title>Features</title>
         
     <para>
       JDO is <emphasis role="bold">transactional</emphasis>. Data objects loaded in Castor 
       are properly locked and isolated from other transactions. Castor supports full 
       2-phase commit via xa.Synchronzation. Castor supports several locking modes, 
       including "shared", "exclusive", "database locked", and "read-only".
     </para>
            
     <para>
       <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             <emphasis role="bold">Shared access</emphasis>, the default, is useful for 
             situations in which it is common for two or more transactions to read the 
             same objects, and/or update different objects.
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             <emphasis role="bold">Exclusive access</emphasis> uses in-memory locks 
             implemented by Castor to force competing transactions to serialize access 
             to an object. This is useful for applications in which it is common for more 
             than one transaction to attempt to update the same object, and for which most, 
             if not all access to the database is performed through Castor.
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             <emphasis role="bold">Database-Locked access</emphasis> is often used for 
             applications in which exclusive locking is required, but in which the database 
             is frequently accessed from applications outside of Castor, bypassing Castor's 
             memory-based locking mechanism used by "exclusive access" locking.
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             <emphasis role="bold">Read-Only access</emphasis> performs no locking at all. 
             Objects read using this access mode are not locked, and those objects do not 
             participate in transaction commit/rollback.
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
     </para>

     <para>
       In addition, Castor supports <emphasis role="bold">"long transactions"</emphasis>, 
       whichs allow objects to be read in one transaction, modified, and then committed 
       in a second transaction, with built-in dirty-checking to prevent data that has been 
       changed since the initial transaction from being overwritten.
     </para>
            
     <para>
       Through <emphasis role="bold">automatic dirty-checking</emphasis> 
       and <emphasis role="bold">deadlock detection</emphasis>, Castor can be 
       used to ensure data integrity and reduce unnecessary database updates.
     </para>
            
     <para>
       A subset of OQL, defined in the Object Management Group (OMG) 3.0 
       <emphasis role="bold">Object Query Language</emphasis> Specification, 
       is supported for interacting with the database. OQL is 
       similar to SQL, though operations are performed directly on Java objects instead 
       of database tables, making the language more appropriate for use within a 
       Java-based application.
     </para>
            
     <para>
       Castor implements a <emphasis role="bold">data cache</emphasis> to reduce database 
       accesses, providing several alternative LRU-based caching strategies.
     </para>

     <para>
       Castor supports different cardinalities of <emphasis role="bold">relationship</emphasis>, 
       including <emphasis role="bold">one-to-one</emphasis>, 
       <emphasis role="bold">one-to-many</emphasis> 
       and <emphasis role="bold">many-to-many</emphasis>. It also supports both object 
        and database record <emphasis role="bold">inheritance</emphasis>. It distinguishes 
       between <emphasis role="bold">related</emphasis> (i.e. association) 
       and <emphasis role="bold">dependent</emphasis> 
       (i.e. aggregation) relationships during an object's life cycle, automatically creating 
       and deleting dependent objects at appropriate times in the independent object's 
       life cycle.
     </para>
           
     <para>
       Multiple-column primary keys, and a variety of key generators are supported.
     </para>

     <para>
       Castor automatically manages persistence for objects that contain Java collection 
       types, including Vector, Hashtable, Collection, Set, and Map. 
       <emphasis role="bold">Lazy loading</emphasis> 
       (of collections as well as simple 1:1 relations) is implemented to reduce unnecessary 
       database loading. Lazy loading can be turned on or off for each individual field (of 
       any supported collection type for 1-to-many and many-to-many relations).
     </para>

     <para>
       Other features include a type converter for all Java primitive types (see the 
       info on supported <ulink url="#jdo.types">types</ulink>).
     </para>

     <para>
       No pre-processor (aka pre-compiler), class enhancer (bytecodes modification) is needed 
       or used for data-binding and object persistence.
     </para>

     <para>
       Castor JDO works in an application that uses multiple ClassLoaders, making it possible to 
       use in an EJB container or servlet, for example. A Castor-defined callback interface, 
       "Persistent", can be implemented if the objects wants to be notified on Castor 
       events: jdoLoad(), jdoCreate(), jdoRemove() and jdoTransient(). This makes it possible 
       to create user-defined actions to take at various times in an object's life cycle.
     </para>

      <para>
        The Java-XML Data-Binding Framework (Castor XML) has been merged with Castor JDO for 
        users who need both O/R Mapping and Java-XML Data-Binding together.
      </para>

      <para>
        The following relational databases are supported: 
            
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>DB2</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Derby</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Generic DBMS</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Hypersonic SQL</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Informix</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>InstantDB</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Interbase</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>MySQL</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Oracle</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>PostgreSQL</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Progress</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>SAP DB / MaxDB</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>SQLServer</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Sybase</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
            
      <para>
        Database support includes Oracle 8.1.x and different versions of Sybase Enterprise and 
        Anywhere. Users can implement the Driver interface to adapt Castor to the differences in 
        SQL syntax supported by different relational DBMS's, as long as the DBMS supports JDBC 
        2.0, multiple ResultSet, and transactions. Thanks to many individual open source 
        contributors, drivers for different database are available.
      </para>
  </section>
</section>