<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
     "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

  <section id="jdo.advanced-features">
    <sectioninfo>
	    <authorgroup>
	      <author>
	        <firstname>Werner</firstname>
	        <surname>Guttmann</surname>  
	        <email>werner DOT guttmann AT gmx DOT net</email>
	      </author>
	    </authorgroup>
    </sectioninfo>
    
<!-- 
    Status: final
-->    
    
    <title>Castor JDO - Advanced features</title>

    <section id="jdo.advanced-features.introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        
        <para>
           As explained at 
           <link linkend="jdo.introduction">the introduction to Castor JDO</link>,
           Castor has support for many advanced features such as caching, depend 
           relations, inheritance, polymorphism, etc. The below sections detail these 
           features, as their understanding is required to use Castor JDO in a 
           performant and secure way.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="jdo.advanced-features.caching">
        <title>Caching</title>
        
        <para>
           All information related to caching and related concepts supported 
           by Castor has been consolidated into one place, and is available 
           <!-- TODO change link when Advanced JDO chapter is finished -->
           <ulink url="../../jdo-caching-detail.html">here</ulink>.
        </para>
           
    </section>

    <section id="jdo.advanced-features.dependent-and-related">
        <title>Dependent and related relationships</title>
        
        <para>
           Castor distinguishes the relationship of two objects as dependent or related, 
           and maintains the life cycle independently for the two types of relationships. 
           Starting from Castor 0.9, the developer can explicitly define a dependent 
           relationship in the mapping file.
        </para>

        <para>
           When using independent relations, related objects' life cycle is independent 
           of each other, meaning that they have to be created, removed and updated 
           (for long transaction) independently.
        </para>

        <para>
           When using dependent relations, one data object class must be declared as 
           <emphasis role="bold">depends</emphasis> on one other data object class in 
           the mapping file, and such an object is called a dependent data object class. 
           A data object class without <literal>depends</literal> 
           declared in the mapping is called a master object. A master object can be 
           depended upon by zero or more dependent data object class.
        </para>

        <para>
           As of Castor 0.9, a dependent object class can be related to other master data 
           object classes including extended classes, but cannot depend on more than one 
           master class.
        </para>

        <para>
           If an object class declared as <literal>depends</literal> 
           on another class, it may not be created, removed or updated separately. 
           Attempting to create, remove or update a dependent object will result in 
           ObjectNotPersistcapableException. Note that Castor doesn't allow a 
           dependent object instance to change its master object instance during a 
           transaction. Each dependent object can have only one master object. 
           Both dependent and master objects must have identities, and may or may 
           not make use of key-generators.
        </para>

        <para>
            Here is the DTD for declaring dependent object:
            
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<!ATTLIST class     name ID  #REQUIRED
          extends   IDREF    #IMPLIED
          depends   IDREF    #IMPLIED
          identity  CDATA   #IMPLIED
          access    ( read-only | shared | exclusive | db-locked )  "shared"
          key-generator   IDREF #IMPLIED]]>
            </programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>
            For example,
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xyz.MyDependentObject"
        depends="com.xyz.MyObject">
        ...
    </class>
</mapping>]]>
            </programlisting>
            declares the data object class 
            <classname>com.xyz.MyDependentObject</classname> as a dependent 
            upon class <classname>com.xyz.MyObject</classname>.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="jdo.advanced-features.different-cardinalities">
        <title>Different cardinalities of relationship</title>
        
        <para>
           Castor supports different cardinalities of relationship, namely one-to-one, 
           one-to-many, and many-to-many. Many-to-many relationship must be related 
           rather than dependent, because each dependent object can have only one 
           master object.
        </para>

        <para>
           Many-to-many requires a separate table for storing the relations between 
           two types of objects. Many-to-many introduces two attributes, namely 
           many-key and many-table that reside in the <literal>&lt;sql&gt;</literal> 
           element which is a sub-element of the <literal>&lt;field&gt;</literal>
           element. For all many-to-many relations, a many-table must be specified. 
           If the column name of the primary key of the class is different from the 
           foreign keys columns of the class in the relation tables, then the relation 
           table columns can be specified using the many-key attributes. Similarly, 
           if the column name of the primary key of the related class is different 
           from the foreign key columns of the related class, then the relation table 
           columns can be specified using the name attribute.
        </para>

        <para>
            The many-table is used to store relations in a separate table
            
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class>
        <field>
            <sql many-key="#OPTIONAL" name="#OPTIONAL"
                 many-table="#REQURIED">
        </field>
    </class>
</mapping>]]></programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>
            So, for example, if the SQL table is the following,

            <table frame="all" width="60%" >
              <title>employee_table</title>
            
              <tgroup cols="3">
                <thead>
	                <row>
	                    <entry style="text-align:center">id</entry>
	                    <entry style="text-align:center">name</entry>
	                    <entry style="text-align:center">salary</entry>
	                </row>
                </thead>
                
                <tbody>
	                <row>
	                    <entry>1482</entry><entry>Smith, Bob</entry><entry>$123,456</entry>
	                </row>
	
	                <row>
	                    <entry>628</entry><entry>Lee, John</entry><entry>$43,210</entry>
	                </row>
	
	                <row>
	                    <entry>1926</entry><entry>Arnold, Pascal</entry><entry>$24,680</entry>
	                </row>
	             </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>


            <table border="true" width="60%">
              <title>department_table</title>
            
              <tgroup cols="3">
                 <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry style="text-align:center">id</entry>
                        <entry style="text-align:center">name</entry>
                        <entry style="text-align:center">comment</entry>
                    </row>
                 </thead>
                 
                 <tbody>
                    <row>
                         <entry>3</entry>
                         <entry>Accounting</entry>
                         <entry></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                         <entry>7</entry>
                         <entry>Engineering</entry>
                         <entry>The very important department. :-)</entry>
                    </row>
                 </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>


            <table border="true" width="40%">
               <title>employee_department</title>
            
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <thead>
                    <row>
                         <entry style="text-align:center">e_id</entry>
                         <entry style="text-align:center">d_id</entry>
                    </row>
                  </thead>
                  
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                         <entry>....</entry><entry>....</entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
        </para>

        <para>
            Then, the mapping for employee data object would look like this
                <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xyz.Employee" identity="id">
        <map-to table="employee_table"/>
            <field name="id" type="integer">
                <sql name="id"/>
            </field>
            <field>
                <sql many-table="employee_department"
                     many-key="e_id" name="d_id"/>
            </field>
            <field name="salary">
                <sql name="salary" type="integer">
            </field>
    </class>
</mapping>]]></programlisting></para>

    </section>

    <section id="jdo.advanced-features.lazy-loading">
        <title>Lazy Loading</title>

		<para>
		   As of release 0.9.6, Castor has full support for lazy loading object 
		   instances referenced as part of all relation types currently supported:
		</para>
		   
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			   <para>1:1 relations</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			   <para>1:m relations</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			   <para>M:N relations.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		   
        <section id="jdo.advanced-features.1-to-1-relations">
            <title>1:1 relations</title>
        
        	<para>
        	   As of release 0.9.6, Castor supports lazy-loading of 1:1 relations. 
        	   Imagine the following class mapping:
        	</para>

			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xzy.Department">
       ...
       <field "employee" type="com.xyz.Employee" lazy="true" />
       ...
    </class>
</mapping>]]>
            </programlisting>
        	   
			<para>
			   Per definition, when an instance of Department is loaded through e.g. 
			   Database.load(), Castor will not (pre-)load the Employee instance 
			   referenced (as such reducing the size of the initial query as well 
			   as the size of the result set returned). Only when the Emplyoee 
			   instance is accessed through Department.getEmployee(), Castor will load 
			   the actual object into memory from the persistence store.
			</para>
			   
			<para>
			   This means that if the Employee instance is not accessed at all, not 
			   only will the initial query to load the Department object have had its 
			   complexity reduced, but no performance penalty will be incurred for the 
			   additional access to the persistence store either.
			</para>
        </section>
    
        <section id="jdo.advanced-features.m-to-n-relations">
           <title>1:M and M:N relations</title>
    
           <para>
              The elements in the collection are only loaded when the application asks 
              for the object from the collection, using, for example, iterator.next(). 
              The iterator in Castor's lazy collection is optimized to return a loaded 
              object first.
           </para>
  
           <para>
              In the mapping file, lazy loading is specified in the element of the 
              collection's <literal>&lt;field></literal>, for example,
           </para>
           
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xzy.Department">
       ...
        <field name="employee" type="com.xyz.Employee" lazy="true"
               collection="collection"/>
    </class>
</mapping>]]></programlisting>

           <para>
              declares that the collection of type Employee in a Department is lazy loaded.
           </para>

           <para>
              If lazy loading is specified for a field of a class, Castor will set the 
              field with a special collection which contains only the identities of the 
              objects. Because of that, it requires the data object to have the method 
              setDepartment( Collection department) in the data object class which was 
              not required in previous versions.
           </para>

           <note>
              <para>
                 Please note that currently <emphasis role="bold">only</emphasis> the 
                 <emphasis role="bold"><type>java.util.Collection</type></emphasis> 
	             type is supported. <!--The following collection types are supported:
	             java.util.Array, java.util.Vector, java.util.Hashtable, 
	             java.util.Collection, java.util.Set and java.util.Map. -->
              </para>
           </note>
           </section>
     </section>

     <section id="jdo.advanced-features.multiple-cols-primary-keys">
        <title>Multiple columns primary keys</title>
        
        <para>
            The support of multiple column primary keys (also called compound primary 
            keys) was another major enhancement added into Castor 0.9. 
            Specifying multiple column primary keys is simple and straightforward, 
            in the mapping file, 
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<mapping>
    <class name="com.xyz.MyObject" identity="firstName lastName">
        <field name="firstName" type="string">
           <sql name="fname"/>
        </field>
        <field name="lastName" type="string">
           <sql name="lname"/>
        </field>
           ...
    </class>
</mapping>]]></programlisting></para>

        <para>
           Multiple column primary keys work with both master and dependent objects, 
           all cardinalities of relationship, including one-to-one, one-to-many and 
           many-to-many, as well as lazy loading. 
        </para>

        <para>
           However, multiple column primary keys should only be used to adhere to an 
           existing database design, not when designing a new database. In general, 
           it is not a good idea to use an identity or identities which can be modified 
           by the user, or which contain application-visible data. For example, if the 
           system allows the user name to be changed, using user name as identity is 
           highly discouraged, as this practice can require a major data migration to 
           a new schema to update all foreign keys to adhere to a new primary key 
           structure, should the user name no longer be adequate as a primary key. 
           It should be noted that Castor doesn't support identity change, as specified 
           in the ODMG 3.0 specification. So, primary keys changes are almost certainly 
           a large trade off between data integrity and performance. Well chosen 
           primary keys are usually single (not multiple) column numeric or character 
           fields for the reasons outlined above, as well as performance, as joining 
           operations are faster for single column primary keys.
        </para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="jdo.advanced-features.callback-interface">
         <title>Callback interface for persistent operations</title>
        
         <para>
            For the various persistence operations as available through the 
            <interface>org.exolab.castor.jdo.Database</interface> interface, 
            Castor JDO provides a callback interface that informs the implementing 
            class on events taking place related to selected persistence operations.
         </para>
            
         <para>
            Once your entity class implements the 
            <interface>org.exolab.castor.jdo.Persistence</interface> interface, 
            you'll have to provide implementations for the following methods (with 
            their respective semantics described next to them):
         </para>
            
         <table>
            <title>Interface methods</title>
         
            <tgroup cols="2">
	            <thead>
	              <row>
	                <entry>Method</entry>
	                <entry>Description</entry>
	              </row>
	            </thead>
	            
	            <tbody>
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoAfterCreate()</entry>
	                <entry>
	                    Indicates that an object has been created in persistent storage.
	                </entry>
	              </row>
	              
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoAfterRemove()</entry>
	                <entry>
	                     Indicates that an object has been removed from persistent storage.
	                </entry>
	              </row>
	              
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoBeforeCreate()</entry>
	                <entry>
	                    Indicates that an object is to be created in persistent storage.
	                </entry>
	              </row>
	              
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoBeforeRemove()</entry>
	                <entry>
	                    Indicates that an object is to be removed from persistent storage.
	                </entry>
	              </row>
	              
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoLoad()</entry>
	                <entry>
	                    Indicates that the object has been loaded from persistent storage.
	                </entry>
	              </row>
	              
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoPersistent(Database)</entry>
	                <entry>
	                    Sets the database to which this object belongs when this object 
	                    becomes persistent.
	                </entry>
	              </row>
	              
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoStore()</entry>
	                <entry>Indicates that an object is to be stored in persistent storage.
	                </entry>
	              </row>
	              
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoTransient()</entry>
	                <entry>Indicates the object is now transient.</entry>
	              </row>
	              
	              <row>
	                <entry>jdoUpdate()</entry>
	                <entry>
	                    Indicates that an object has been included to the current 
	                    transaction by means of db.update() method (in other words, 
	                    at the end of a "long" transaction).
	                </entry>
	              </row>
	            </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
      </section>
   </section>
