<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
     "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

  <section id="jdo.faq">
    <title>Castor JDO FAQ</title>

    <section id="jdo.faq.other-specifications">
        <title>Castor's relation to other specifications</title>

        <section id="jdo.faq.other-specifications.sun-jsr-000012">
            <title>Does Castor JDO comply with the SUN JSR-000012 specification?</title>
            
            <para>
	            No, Castor JDO doesn't comply with the SUN's JDO specification.
            </para>

            <para>
	            Although Castor JDO carries very similar goals as SUN's JDO, it has 
	            been developed independently from the JSR.
            </para>

            <para>
	            Although it is not impossible to shape (perhaps "hammer" is a more 
	            descriptive verb) Castor JDO into the SUN's JDO specification, there 
	            are several major technical differences which make it unfavorable to 
	            do so. Castor is RDBMS centric. Each persistence object loaded by 
	            Castor is locked. Locks in Castor are observable, meaning that locks 
	            may not be granted because of timeout or deadlock. On the other 
	            hand, the SUN's JDO hides details about locks.
            </para>

            <para>
	            Internally, Castor JDO maintains a single copy of lock (and cache) 
	            for each active persistence object for all transaction. SUN's JDO 
	            specification implicitly requires a copy of cache per object per 
	            transaction. SUN's JDO also implicitly requires a bytecode modifier 
	            which Castor doesn't require.
            </para>

            <para>
	            Castor also provides other features, such as key generators, long 
	            transaction support and OQL query which cannot be found in SUN's JSR.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.other-specifications.ejb-cmp">
            <title>Is Castor JDO better than EJB CMP?</title>
            
            <para>
	            The relation between JDO and EJB Container-Managed
	            Persistence is more complicated than simply saying, "one
	            is better than the other".
            </para>

            <para>
	            An Entity Bean may manage persistence itself - the EJB
	            specification calls this Bean Managed Persistence
	            (BMP). Alternatively, the Entity Bean may rely on an EJB
	            container to manage all peersistence automatically - the
	            EJB specification calls this Container Managed Persistence
	            (CMP). When implementing BMP, an Entity Bean may use
	            Castor JDO as its persistence mechanism, or it may use
	            others methods, such as dealing with JDBC directly.
	            During CMP, an EJB Container vendor may implement their
	            CMP on top of Castor JDO.  In such an implementation,
	            Castor JDO will be used to persist the Entity Bean.
            </para>

            <para>
	            If a developer would like to take advantage of an EJB's
	            life-cycle management, security, the "write once deploy
	            anywhere" promise and other distributed business
	            application facilities, then EJB will be the right
	            choice. Otherwise, the fact that Castor is simple, is Open
	            Source (you can always include Castor in your application
	            or product), has much less overhead, provides more design
	            freedom, and is integrated with Castor XML may be enough
	            of a reason to choose Castor JDO.
            </para>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section id="jdo.faq.xml">
        <title>XML related questions</title>

        <section id="jdo.faq.xml.marsgalling-transactional">
            <title>Is it possible to make XML marshalling transactionally using Castor?</title>
            
            <para>
	            No. The decision of putting XML and JDO together is NOT intended to 
	            make XML marshalling transactional. Instead, the integration is done 
	            to help developers of a typical client-server situation whereby an 
	            application server receives incoming XML messages, process the 
	            messages and replies to the client.
            </para>

            <para>
	            With Castor, incoming XML messages can be unmarshaled into data 
	            objects. Required information can be obtained from a database using 
	            JDO in form of data objects. With this approach, all data 
	            manipulation can be done in an object-oriented way. Changes to JDO 
	            data objects can be committed transactionally, and result data 
	            objects can be marshaled into XML and returned to the client. 
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.xml.xml-file-queries">
            <title>Is it possible to do queries on a XML file using Castor?</title>
            
            <para>
	            No, Castor does not provide an OQL query facility on a XML file. If 
	            querying is important for you, you should consider using a DBMS to store 
	            your data instead of using XML files, especially if querying performance 
	            is a concern.
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            Another alternative is parse an XML Document directly and use XPath to
	            retrieve Nodes and/or NodeSets from an XML Document.  Other open source
	            tools which provide this functionality are:
	            <itemizedlist>
	              <listitem>
	                <para>
	                  <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/saxpath/">SAXPath</ulink>
	                </para>
	              </listitem>
	              <listitem>
	                <para>
	                  <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/jxpath/index.html"><!-- 
	               -->Jakarta Commons JXPath</ulink>
	                </para>
	              </listitem>
	            </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section id="jdo.faq.technical">
        <title>Technical questions</title>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.examples">
            <title>Where can I find some examples to start with?</title>
            
            <para>
	            Download the full SVN snapshot and look into the src/tests/jdo 
	            directory.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.sub-jdbc-odbc">
            <title>I have encountered problems using Sun JDBC-ODBC bridge with Castor...</title>
            
            <para>
	            It cannot be used with Castor, because it doesn't allow more than one
	            open <literal>ResultSet</literal> at the same time. 
	            Either use JDBC driver of type &gt; 1, or use some other JDBC-ODBC 
	            bridge without such a restriction
	            (for example, from <ulink url="http://www.easysoft.com">Easysoft</ulink>).
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.collection-get-method">
            <title>
              My get-method for the Collection of dependent objects returns null. 
              Why?
            </title>

            <para>You should initialize the Collection yourself:
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
private Collection _children = new ArrayList();

public Collection getChildren() {
    return _children;
}
            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.implement-interfaces">
            <title>Should my JDO classes implement some special interface?</title>
            
            <para>
	            In general, no. If you need some behavior that is not directly 
	            supported by Castor, you can implement interface 
	            <interface>org.exolab.castor.jdo.Persistent</interface>. 
	            In order to use dirty checking for long transaction you should 
	            implement interface 
	            <interface>org.exolab.castor.jdo.TimeStampable</interface>. 
	            If you need an example of use of these interfaces, see Persistent.java 
	            and TestPersistent.java among Castor JDO tests.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.create-or-remove">
            <title>Can Castor automatically create/remove related objects?</title>
            
            <para>
	            First of all, let's agree upon terminology. We distinguish dependent 
	            and independent objects:
	
	            <itemizedlist>
	                <listitem>
	                   <para>
	                     <emphasis role="bold">dependent</emphasis> objects are bounded 
	                     to the parent object's lifecycle
	                   </para>
	                </listitem>
	                <listitem>
	                   <para>
	                     <emphasis role="bold">independent</emphasis> objects have 
	                     independent lifecycle
	                   </para>
	                </listitem>
	            </itemizedlist>
	
	            Thus, dependent objects are created/removed automatically, when 
	            their parent object is created/removed, while all operations on 
	            independent objects should be performed explicitly.
            </para>

            <para>
	            However, with Castor 0.8.x you cannot describe explicitly the kind 
	            of object. Instead, the following rule applies: if you have 
	            one-to-many relation, and each side of the relation refers to 
	            another (Collection attribute on "one" side, simple attribute on 
	            "many" side), then "many" side is a dependent object. All other 
	            objects are independent. In particular, related objects via 
	            one-to-one relation are not created/removed automatically.
            </para>

            <para>
	            With Castor 0.9 dependent objects should be described via "depends" 
	            attribute of "class" element in mapping configuration file.
            </para>

            <para>
	            If you wish some independent object was created and/or removed 
	            automatically on operations on other independent object, you may 
	            use interface <interface>Persistent</interface> to code the desired 
	            behavior.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.connection-pooling">
            <title>
	            Is Castor JDO using any connection pooling mechanism to improve 
	            the overall performance?
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            No, Castor JDO doesn't have any built-in JDBC resource pooling. 
	            However the framework can transparently use any resource pooling 
	            facilities provided through DataSource implementation or 
	            -even better- through JDNI. In fact we even recommend people to use 
	            some Connection and PreparedStatement pool with Castor as this can
	            increase Castor's performance 3-5 fold.
            </para>

            <para>
	            For example the following set of statements:
	            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
db.begin();
db.execute(...)
db.commit()
	            ]]></programlisting>
	            will be executed in much less time with the resource pooling because it 
	            will avoid creating a new physical JDBC connection at every execution.
            </para>

            <para>
	            With Oracle, instead of specifying the usual JDBC driver you can use a
	            DataSource that specifically provides some Connection caching/pooling.
            </para>

	        <para>
		        Thus if your jdo config file looks like :
		        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
        <database name="..." engine="oracle" >
            <driver class-name="oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleDriver"
                    URL="jdbc:oracle:thin:@localhost:1521:TEST" >
                <param name="user" value="SYSTEM"/>
                <param name="password" value="manager"/>
            </driver>
            ...
        </database>
		        ]]></programlisting>
		        then it can be changed into (for example):
		        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
        <database name="..." engine="oracle" >
            <data-source class-name="oracle.jdbc.pool.OracleConnectionCacheImpl">
                <params URL="jdbc:oracle:thin:@localhost:1521:TEST"
                        user="scott" 
                        password="tiger"
                />
            </data-source>
            ...
        </database>
		        ]]></programlisting>
	        </para>

	        <para>
	            When Castor is used inside a Container such as an EJB container 
	            (within BMP or Session Bean), then the Container usually provides 
	            the JDBC resource through the JNDI ENC, which implicitely includes 
	            pooling facilities.
	        </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.classnotfoundexception">
            <title>
               I am getting ClassNotFoundException for my JDO class, 
               but it is in the class path. Why?
            </title>
            <para>
	            Probably castor.jar file is in jre/lib/ext directory. In this case 
	            you should call:
	            <programlisting language="java">
      jdo.setClassLoader(getClass().getClassLoader());
	            </programlisting>
	           before jdo.getDatabase().
           </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.notpersistencecapable">
            <title>
              I am getting exception 
              'the class ... is not persistence capable...'. Why?
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            In this case as well as in many others you can get more information 
	            with the help of logging. Call:
            </para>
	        <programlisting language="java">
  jdo.setLogWriter(Logger.getSystemLogger());
	        </programlisting>
            <para>and seek in the output for warnings and errors.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.db-remove">
            <title>
	            I call db.remove() on the dependent object and commit, 
	            but this doesn't work...
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            You should not add/remove dependent objects directly. In order to 
	            add/remove the dependent object you should just add/remove it from the 
	            collection in the master object and call db.commit()
            </para>

            <para>
	            Dependent objects cannot be created/removed explicitly. It's created 
	            automatically when it is added to a master object, and removed 
	            automatically when it de-linked/dereferenced from a master object.
            </para>

            <para>
	            Otherwise, we will be encounter into problem where a dependent object 
	            created explicitly but removed implicitly (delinked from a master object), 
	            or vice versa. It can also lead to other problems that are harder to 
	            detect.
            </para> 
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.string-date-boolean-literals">
            <title>
	            How should I represent string/date/boolean literals in OQL query?
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            It is recommended to replace literals with parameters and to set them 
	            via <methodname>OQLQuery.bind()</methodname>, for example:
            </para>
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
OQLQuery query = db.getOQLQuery(
        "SELECT p FROM Person p "
      + "WHERE name LIKE $1 AND dob>$2 AND married=$3");
query.bind("John %");
query.bind((new SimpleDateFormat("yyyy-MM-dd"))
       .parse("1960-01-01"));
query.bind(false);
         ]]></programlisting>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.abstractmethoderror">
            <title>
	            I get 'java.lang.AbstractMethodError: getBigDecimal' 
	            for numeric fields. Why?
             </title>
             
            <para>
	            Your JDBC driver is not JDBC 2.0 compliant, upgrade it or find another one.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.bi-directional">
            <title>Does Castor support both one-way and two-way relationships?</title>
            
            <anchor id="bi-directional" />
            
            <para>
	            Typcially a relationship between two objects is either one-way 
	            (aka uni-directional) or two-way (aka bi-directional). 
	            Officially, Castor currently only supports bi-directional relationships. 
	            For example, if an <classname>Order</classname> object contains a 
	            reference to a <classname>LineItem</classname> object, the 
	            <classname>LineItem</classname> object must contain a reference to the 
	            Order object. However, this requirement is not enforced in all 
	            situations. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            This is a very complex problem to solve. So until Castor is expanded 
	            the support uni-directional relationships, the best policy is to 
	            implement the bi-directionalality for all relationships. This will 
	            ensure proper functionality.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.self-relation">
            <title>
	            I have an object that holds a relation to itself. 
	            Does Castor support this?
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            This is a very common occurrence in an object model and is known as 
	            a self-referenential relationship. Unfortunately, Castor does not 
	            currently support self-referential relationships. An example of such 
	            a relationship occurs when a <literal>Folder</literal> object contains
	            a reference to another <literal>Folder</literal> object. 
	            Castor does not currently support this. However, there are ways 
	            around this limitation. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            One way is to manage this type of relationship manually. For example, 
	            let's say that a parent object <literal>FolderA</literal> needs to hold 
	            references to child objects <literal>FolderB</literal>, 
	            <literal>FolderC</literal> and <literal>FolderD</literal>. 
	            The <literal>Folder</literal> object contains not only a property 
	            to hold its own id, but also a property to hold its parent id 
	            (we'll call this <literal>parentId</literal>). 
	            The <literal>parentId</literal> property is used to determine 
	            if there is a relationship to another <literal>Folder</literal> object. 
	            If <literal>parentId</literal> is null, there is no relationship. 
	            If <literal>parentId</literal> is populated, there is a relationship 
	            and the object tree can be walked by comparing the object id to the 
	            <literal>parentId</literal>. When the two properties are equal, 
	            you're at the top of the tree. 
            </para>

            <para>
	            Another say to solve this problem is to make use of an intermediary 
	            object. For example, a <literal>Folder</literal> object contains a 
	            <literal>Reference</literal> object in lieu of the actual 
	            <literal>Folder</literal> object. The <literal>Reference</literal> 
	            object is somewhat of a proxy object whereby it only contains enough 
	            information to identify the object to which the 
	            <literal>Reference</literal> object refers. Then the 
	            <literal>Folder</literal> object can be easily instantiated via the 
	            information contained in the <literal>Reference</literal> object. 
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.objectmodifiedexception">
            <title>
	            Why do I get an ObjectModifiedException when trying to commit 
	            a transaction?
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            The dirty checking engine will throw an 
	            <literal>ObjectModifiedException</literal> when the values in the
	            cache and in the database are different. This can happen when 
	            someone else changed the database content, but also when type 
	            mapping is not reversible.
            </para>

            <para>
	            For example, if a java timestamp (<literal>java.util.Date</literal>) 
	            is stored as a DATE, the time part is lost and the dirty checking 
	            will fail. Oracle cannot tell the difference between an empty String
	            and a null value: if an attribute value is an empty String, dirty 
	            checking will also fail. Some precision loss sometimes occur with 
	            floating point numbers.
            </para>

            <para>
	            To avoid this, always use reversible mapping conversions. If this 
	            is not possible, mark the fields with <literal>dirty="ignore"</literal> 
	            in the mapping file.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.technical.ora-01461">
            <title>I'm receiving a java.sql.SQLException: ORA-01461</title>
            
            <para>
	            When using Weblogic Portal 4.0 with Oracle I am receiving the following 
	            error:
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[
java.sql.SQLException: ORA-01461: can bind a LONG value only for insert into a LONG column
	            ]]></programlisting>
	            According to Weblogic Release Notes, this error can remedied by setting 
	            a Weblogic environment variable. 
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="jdo.faq.performance-caches">
        <title>Castor and performance caches</title>
    
        <section id="jdo.faq.performance-caches.objectmodifiedexception">
            <title>
	            Sometimes long transaction fails: on update() it is thrown 
	            ObjectModifiedException. Why?
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            Most probably the object that is being updated has more than 100 related 
	            objects of one class and the cache size for this class is not enough. 
	            You should either increase the size of the cache or change the cache type 
	            to time-limited (the default cache type is count-limited, the default 
	            size is 100), for example:
		        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<class ...>
  <cache-type type="count-limited" capacity="1000"/>
  ...
</class>
		        ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.performance-caches.cache-type-none">
            <title>Can I use the cache-type='none' with long transactions?</title>
            
            <para>
	            As of release 0.9.5.3, you cannot. When using a cache of type 'none' 
	            with your 'Timestampable' objects, a MappingException is thrown when 
	            performing long transactions. Currently, Castor requires a (performance) 
	            cache of type other than 'none' to be used with classes  that implement 
	            the <interface>TimeStampable</interface> interface. In other words, 
	            if you want to use long transactions, please make sure that you use one 
	            of these cache types: 'unlimited', 'count-limited' or 'time-limited'. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            The next entry has some more information about a potential cause of 
	            confusion in the context of long transactions and a cache type other 
	            than 'unlimited'.
            </para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="jdo.faq.performance-caches.persistenceexception">
            <title>
	            What is causing a PersistenceException with long transactions and 
	            how do I fix it?
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            With long transactions, sometimes update() throws a PersistenceException. 
	            As of release 0.9.5.3, Castor requires a (performance) cache (of type 
	            other than 'none') to be used with classes that implement the 
	            <interface>TimeStampable</interface> interface. 
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            Please note that if you are using a cache type other than 'unlimited', 
	            it is possible that objects expire from the cache. This case will be 
	            highlighted to you by a PersistenceException being thrown.
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            In this cases, please consider switching to cache type 'unlimited' 
	            (if possible) or increase the size of the cache according to your 
	            needs when using 'count-limited' (which has a default capacity of 100). 
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="jdo.faq.oql">
        <title>OQL</title>

        <section id="jdo.faq.oql.document">
            <title>Is there any document available for Castor OQL?</title>

            <para>
	            Yes. It is available from the Castor website: 
                <link linkend="advanced-jdo.oql-to-sql-translator">Advanced JDO &mdash;&gt; OQL</link>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.oql.phase">
            <title>
	            The OQL document describes several phases of development. 
	            Which is the current phase?
            </title>
            
            <para>We are currently working on Phase 3.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.oql.sub-queries">
            <title>Does Castor OQL support sub-queries?</title>
            
            <para>Not yet</para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.oql.join">
            <title>
	            I cannot get Castor OQL to join two objects for me. Is it supported?
            </title>

            <para>
	            Yes or no. Castor OQL supports implicit joins. And, in most case, 
	            you simply don't need explicit join.
            </para>

            <para>
	            Consider the following example, 
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[
SELECT o FROM Order o, LineItem i WHERE o.id = i.id AND i.price > 100
	            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            It is simply equivalent to the following OQL
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[
SELECT o FROM Order o WHERE o.lineItem.price > 100
	            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.oql.pass-thru">
            <title>Can I write a pass-thru OQL?</title>
            
            <para>
	            Yes. Just put "CALL SQL" keywords in front of your SQL statement. For example,
	            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
OQLQuery oql = castorDb.getOQLQuery(
    "CALL SQL SELECT id, name, date "
   +"FROM user WHERE upper(name) like $1 AS myapp.Product");
	            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            <emphasis role="bold">
	            But remember that the order of the fields listed must match what is 
	            defined in the mapping file.
	            </emphasis>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.oql.struct">
            <title>Does Castor OQL support struct?</title>
            
            <para>
	            No, Castor OQL doesn't support struct. For example, the following 
	            query CANNOT be done:
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[
select c.name, c.age from Client c
	            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.oql.like">
            <title>How do I structure a query using the 'LIKE' expression?</title>
            
            <para>
	            A query using the 'LIKE' expression includes the use of the SQL 
	            wildcard '%'. The wildcard must be included in the 
	            <code language="java">bind()</code> statement:
	            <programlisting language="java">
        OQLQuery oql = castorDb.getOQLQuery(
                "SELECT p FROM Product p WHERE p.name LIKE $1" );
        oql.bind( "%widget%" );
	            </programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.oql.in">
            <title>Does Castor support the SQL 'IN' expression?</title>
            
            <para>
	            Yes. However, the full expression is a bit different using the LIST 
	            keyword. The following example provides a demonstration:
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[
SELECT p FROM Product p WHERE p.id IN LIST ( 123, 456, 789 )
	            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            If identifiers other than numbers are used, those identifiers must be 
	            quoted:
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[
SELECT p FROM Product p WHERE p.name IN LIST ( "abc", "jkl", "xyz" )
	            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            
			<para>
	            To include NULL values in the 'IN' list, use the 'nil' keyword:
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[
SELECT p FROM Product p WHERE p.name IN LIST( "ABC", nil )
	            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            
			<para>
	            It is even possible to include bind values in the 'IN' lists 
	            using the following syntax:
	            <programlisting><![CDATA[
SELECT p FROM Product p WHERE p.id IN LIST( $(int)1, $2, $3 )
	            ]]></programlisting>
			</para>
        </section>
        
    </section>

    <section id="jdo.faq.feature-requests">
        <title>Features requests</title>

        <section id="jdo.faq.feature-requests.foreign-key-multiple">
            <title>Can a foreign key be part of multiple primary keys?</title>
            
            <para>
	            Unfortunately, the answer is no. We're aware that many users need 
	            this feature so it is a very high priority in our todo list.
            </para>

            <para>
	            If foreign key is the primary key, as a workaround you may consider 
	            using the 'extends' relationship.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.feature-requests.polymorphic-collection">
            <title>Is polymorphic collection supported?</title>
            
            <para>Unfortunately, the answer is no.</para>
        
            <para>
	            In version 0.8.11, we tried to enable polymorphic collection by 
	            introducing the notation of Object Reloading. Object Reloading 
	            delegates the determination of the class to a data object. However, 
	            it is proved that reloading can only be done before any instance of 
	            the target object is returned to user, and we have no way to determine 
	            that. As a result, we removed the support in version 0.9.x.
            </para>
        
            <para>
	            In the near future, we are going to use a new mechanism to provide 
	            extends. The new mechanism loads a table with an SQL statement that 
	            outer-joins all of the extending tables with the base. The existence 
	            of an extended table row can be used to determine the class of a data 
	            object. Notice that all extended table rows of the same entity should 
	            always be stored in the same data-store.
            </para>

            <para>
	            In the further future, we also want to let users to define a 
	            discriminator column (or determinance field). Basing on the value of 
	            discriminator columns in the base table, the bridge layer fetches the 
	            additional information and returns the combined entity with the 
	            appropriate list of entity classes.
            </para>
        </section>

     </section>

     <section id="jdo.faq.data-model">
        <title>Data model issues</title>

        <section id="jdo.faq.data-model.map-to-multiple-tables">
            <title>Is it possible to map an object to more than one tables?</title>
            
            <para>
	            Yes, if the two tables share the same identity, you can specify one 
	            data object to "extends" the other. When the extended data object is 
	            loaded, its table (specified in <![CDATA[<map-to/>]]> will be joined 
	            with all the tables of its super classes'.
            </para>

            <para>
	            Another solution (in my opinion more flexible) is having two set 
	            of methods in the main object. One for Castor JDO and another for 
	            application.
            </para>

            <para>
	            Consider the following example:
	            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
class Employee {
   private int _employeeNumber;
   private Address _address;
   private Collection _workGroup;

   public int getEmployeeNumber() {
        return _employeeNumber;
   }
   public void setEmployeeNumber( int id ) {
        _employeeNumber = id;
   }

   // methods for Castor JDO
   public Address getAddress() {
       return _address;
   }
   public void setAddress( Address address ) {
        _address = address;
   }
   public Collection getWorkGroup() {
        return _workGroup;
   }
   public Collection setWorkGroup( Collection workGroup ) {
        _workGroup = workGroup;
   }

   // methods for application
   public String getAddressCity() {
       return _address.getCity();
   }
   public String getAddressZip() {
       return _address.getZip();
   }
   // ...
}
	            ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.data-model.remove-recreate">
            <title>
	            Can an object with the same identity be re-created after being removed 
	            in the same transaction?
            </title>
            
            <para>
	            Yes, as long as the deleted object is the same instance as the one 
	            being recreated.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.data-model.dependent-object">
            <title>What is a dependent object?</title>
            
            <para>
	            Dependent object is actually a concept from the object-oriented 
	            database world.  A dependent object's lifetime depends on its master 
	            object. So, create/delete/update of the master object will trigger 
	            the proper actions, newly linked dependent object will be 
	            automatically created and de-referenced dependent object will be 
	            removed.
            </para>

            <para>
	            The concept was also used in the earlier CMP 2.0 draft, although 
	            it is later removed.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.data-model.dependent-many-to-many">
            <title>
	            Can a data object involved in many-to-many relationship be dependent?
	        </title>
            
            <para>No</para>
        </section>

     </section>

     <section id="jdo.faq.design">
        <title>Castor JDO design</title>

        <section id="jdo.faq.design.functionality">
            <title>How does Castor JDO work anyway?</title>
            
            <para>Let's use object loading as an example.</para>

            <para>
	            When an application invoke db.load, the underneath 
	            <literal>TransactionContext</literal> is invoked. 
	            If the object with the requested identity exists in the 
	            <literal>TransactionContext</literal>, previously loaded object in the 
	            <literal>TransactionContext</literal> is returned. Otherwise, 
	            <literal>TransactionContext</literal> creates a new instance 
	            of the interested type and invokes LockEngine to "fill" the object.
            </para>

            <para>
	            <literal>LockEngine</literal> acquires a lock of the object, 
	            and it makes sure <literal>ClassMolder</literal> has a thread-safe 
	            environment when it invokes <literal>ClassMolder</literal>. 
	            In <literal>ClassMolder</literal>, if the interested set of fields 
	            representing the object is not existed in the cache yet, 
	            <literal>SQLEngine</literal> will be invoked and the set of fields 
	            from the underneath data store will be returned. 
	            <literal>ClassMolder</literal> binds the loaded or cached fields into 
	            the new instance. <literal>ClassMolder</literal> requests the 
	            <literal>TransactionContext</literal> to load the related and the 
	            dependent objects. Eventually, the object is returned after all of 
	            the relationships are resolved.
            </para>

            <para>
	            The process of commit has several states. The first state is 
	            preStore. In preStore state, objects existing in the 
	            <literal>TransactionContext</literal> are checked for modification 
	            one by one, including dependent and related objects. 
	            De-referenced dependent objects are marked as delete-able, 
	            and reachable dependent objects are added into 
	            <literal>TransactionContext</literal>. An object is marked 
	            "dirty" if it is modified. Also, if any modification should cause 
	            any related or dependent to be dirty, the related or dependent object 
	            is marked as dirty as well.
            </para>

            <para>
	            After the preStore state, all dirty object is properly stored. And, 
	            all marked delete object will be removed. Then, the connection is 
	            committed. If succeed, all cache with be updated. Finally, all lock 
	            is released.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.design.two-phase-commits">
            <title>
	            Does Castor support two-phase commits? How is this implemented?
	        </title>
            
            <para>
	            Yes, via <interface>javax.transaction.Synchronization</interface> interface.
            </para>
            
            <para>
	            For Castor to work with global transactions, Castor must be configured
	            to use global transaction demarcation in its main configuration file:
            </para>

            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<jdo-conf>
   ...
   <transaction-demarcation mode="global" >
      <transaction-manager name="jndi" />
   </transaction-demarcation>
</jdo-conf>
            ]]></programlisting>

            <para>When retrieving a Database instance via</para>

            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
...
JDOManager.loadConfiguration("jdo-conf.xml");
JDOManager jdo = JDOManager.createInstance("mydb");
...
Database db = jdo.getDatabase();
            ]]></programlisting>
            
            <para>
	            the <literal>Database</literal> implementation will authomatically 
	            be registered with the transaction manager, as it implements 
	            <interface>javax.jta.Synchronization</interface> interface. 
	            Subsequently, the transaction manager communicates with Castor 
	            via the beforeCompletion() and afterCompletion() calls.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.design.nested-transaction">
            <title>Does Castor support nested transaction?</title>
            
            <para>No</para>
        </section>

     </section>

     <section id="jdo.faq.open-source-databases">
        <title>Working with open source databases</title>

        <section id="jdo.faq.open-source-databases.postgresql">
            <title>Does Castor support PosgreSQL?</title>
            
            <para>
	            Yes, starting from PostgreSQL 7.1, where outer joins support has 
	            been added.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.open-source-databases.mysql">
            <title>Does Castor support MySQL?</title>
            
            <para>
	            Yes, starting from MySQL version 3.23, where transaction support has 
	            been added. Note: if you use Mark Matthews MySQL JDBC driver, then 
	            you need version 2.0.3 or higher.
            </para>
         </section>

        <section id="jdo.faq.open-source-databases.which">
            <title>Which Open Source database is supported better?</title>
            
            <para>
	            For now only with 
	            <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL 7.1</ulink> 
	            and <ulink url="http://www.sapdb.org">SAP DB</ulink> you get a full 
	            set of Castor features. Other Open Source databases don't support 
	            select with write lock, so db-locked locking mode doesn't work 
	            properly (it works in the same way as exclusive locking mode).
            </para>

            <para>
	            All other Castor features are supported with 
	            <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com">MySQL</ulink>, 
	            <ulink url="http://www.interbase2000.org">Interbase</ulink>, 
	            <ulink url="http://instantdb.enhydra.org">InstantDB</ulink> and 
	            <ulink url="http://www.hypersonicsql.com">Hypersonic SQL</ulink>.
            </para>
        </section>

    </section>
    
    <section id="jdo.faq.rdbms-specific">
        <title>RDBMS-specific issues</title>
    
    	<section id="jdo.faq.rdbms-specific.mysql">
    	    <title>MySQL</title>

    		<section id="jdo.faq.rdbms-specific.mysql.datetime">
    		    <title>Use of DATETIME fields in general</title>
    	
    			<para>
    			   MySQL in it's current releases (4.0.x and 4.1.x) does not store fractions of a 
    			   second in fields of type DATETIME that are mapped to java.sql.TimeStamp fields.
    			   As a result, Castor will throw ObjectModifiedExceptions during commits as Castor 
    			   internally maintains fractions of a seconds. 
    			</para> 
    			<para>
    			   Instead, Please use a column type that can be mapped to a long value, as Castor 
                   internally handles conversion between java.util.Date and long values with 
                   the required precision.
                </para>
    		</section>
    		
    		<section id="jdo.faq.rdbms-specific.mysql.timestamp-null">
    		    <title>Use of TIMESTAMP fields &amp; NULLs in long transactions</title>
    		
    			<para>
    			   In MySQL, fields of type 'Timestamp' exhibit special behaviour wih 
    			   regards to NULLs. When inserting a "NULL" into such a field, it 
    			   actually inserts the current date and time. This causes problems 
    			   for Castor's caching mechanism since Castor internally believes the 
    			   field is still NULL. If you subsequently perform an update on the 
    			   entry whilst it is still in the cache, an ObjectModifiedException 
    			   will be thrown, because Castor believes that the database record 
    			   has changed in the meantime.
    			</para>

                <para>The workaround is to use a DATETIME field instead of TIMESTAMP.</para>
                
    		</section>

    		<section id="jdo.faq.rdbms-specific.mysql.upgrade-issues">
    		    <title>MySQL 4.1.x and upgrade issues</title>
    		
 				<para>
 				   As with many other open source products, MySQL seems to be changing 
 				   slightly from version to version. There seems to be a problem with 
 				   concurrency in MySQL 4.1.5 that can be resolved by upgrading to 
 				   4.1.7 or higher.
				</para>
				   
				<para>
				   At Castor we frequently use Connector/J 3.0.16, 3.1.13 and nowadays 5.1.6 to
				   execute our test farmework. If you use one of this versions of Connector/J 
				   you should be on the safe side. If you are hit by any problems using one of 
				   these versions, please let us know.
				</para>
			
			</section>
    		

    	</section>

    	<section id="jdo.faq.rdbms-specific.oracle">
    	    <title>Oracle</title>

    		<section id="jdo.faq.rdbms-specific.oracle.clob-blob-lob-fields">
    		    <title>Oracle &amp; (C|B)LOB fields</title>
    		    
    			<para>
    			   As of Oracle release 10g, the problem of Castor to handle BLOBs 
    			   with a size greater than 2kB and CLOBs with a size greater than 
    			   4 kB correctly has been resolved. With the 10 release of Oracle's 
    			   JDBC driver, both driver types (type 2 and type 4) can be used. 
    			   With earlier releases, only the OCI driver (type 2) seems to work.
    			</para>
    			   
    			<para>
    			   The 10g release of the Oracle JDBC Driver can be downloaded
    			   <ulink url="http://www.oracle.com/technology/software/tech/java/sqlj_jdbc/index.html"><!-- 
    		    -->here</ulink>.
    			</para>
    			
    		</section>
    		
    	</section>
    </section>

    <section id="jdo.faq.logging">
        <title>Castor &amp; Logging</title>
			
        <section id="jdo.faq.logging.log4j">
            <title>
	            How can I integrate Castor's logging with a logging infrastructure 
	            using Log4J?
	        </title>
            
            <para>
	            Please see 
	            <ulink url="http://www.mail-archive.com/castor-dev@exolab.org/msg02710.html">
	            this message</ulink> from the mailing list. It includes an adapter class 
	            that will provide this functionality. (Thanks John!)
            </para>
        </section>

		<section id="jdo.faq.logging.sql-statement">
		    <title>
			    Can I see what SQL statement Castor issues to the database as a result 
			    of an operation?
			</title>
			
			<para>
			   Yes, you can. By default, Castor uses JDBC proxy classes (wrapping
			   <literal>java.sql.Connection</literal> and 
			   <literal>java.sql.PreparedStatement</literal>) that capture the 
			   core SQL statements as generated by Castor and the user-supplied 
			   parameters at execution timeof the various persistence operations, 
			   and outputs them to the standard logger used by Castor. 
			   By default, these output statements are not visible, 
			   as the log level is set to level 'info'. To see these SQL statements, 
			   please increase the log level to level 'debug' in 
			   <literal>log4j.xml</literal>.
			</para>
			   
		</section>
	
		<section id="jdo.faq.logging.disable-jdbc-proxy-classes">
		    <title>How can I disable the use of JDBC proxy classes?</title>
			
			<para>
			   As of <emphasis role="bold">release 0.9.7</emphasis>, a new property
			   <programlisting>org.exolab.castor.persist.useProxies</programlisting>
			   has been added to <literal>castor.properties</literal> to allow 
			   configuration of the JDBC proxy classes mentioned above. 
			   If enabled, JDBC proxy classes will be used for logging SQL statements. 
			   When turned off, no logging statements will be generated at all.
			</para>
			   
		</section>
		
	</section>
   
   <section id="jdo.faq.lazy-loading">
       <title>Lazy Loading related questions</title>
   
       <section id="jdo.faq.lazy-loading.1-to-1">
           <title>
	           How do I configure the JDO mapping to use the lazy loading feature 
	           for 1:1 relations?
           </title>

           <para>
              Let us convert one of the classes from the 
              <!-- TODO change link when More doc is finished -->
              <ulink url="http://castor.org/examples.html">JDO examples</ulink> to use 
              lazy-loading.
           </para>

           <para>
              In the example model, every Product belongs to one ProductGroup. 
              This is reflected in the conventional mapping as below. 
              Here's the mapping for Product:
           </para>

           <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<!--  Mapping for Product  -->
<class name="myapp.Product"
       identity="id">
   <description>Product definition</description>
   <map-to table="prod" xml="product" />
   <field name="id" type="integer">
       <sql name="id" type="integer" />
       <xml name="id" node="attribute"/>
   </field>
 
   <!-- more fields ... -->

    <!--  Product has reference to ProductGroup,
          many products may reference same group  -->
    <field name="group" type="myapp.ProductGroup">
      <sql name="group_id" />
      <bind-xml name="group" node="element" />
    </field>
    
</class>
]]></programlisting>

           <para>
              Let us now make the relationship between Product and ProductGroup use 
              lazy loading. The relevant field in Product can be re-written like so:
           </para>

           <programlisting language="xml">
    &lt;field name="group" type="myapp.ProductGroup" lazy="true"&gt;
      &lt;sql name="group_id" /&gt;
      &lt;bind-xml name="group" node="element" /&gt;
    &lt;/field&gt;
           </programlisting>

           <para>
              There have been one change only. We have placed the attribute lazy="true" in 
              the field element. Note that no change is required in the ProductDetail 
              mapping.
           </para>

       </section>

       <section id="jdo.faq.lazy-loading.1-to-1-serialization">
           <title>Lazy loading for 1:1 relations and serialization</title>
       
       	   <para>
       	      Please note that Castor does not support full serialization of lazy-loaded 
       	      objects at this time. Rather than serializing just the information 
       	      required to re-build the underlying proxy implementation during 
       	      deserialization, Castor will materialize (read: load from the persistence 
       	      store) all objects before serialization. As this can lead to a lot of 
       	      database accesses, please use this feature carefully. A full working 
       	      solution will be provided with the next release.
       	   </para>
       	      
       </section>
       
       <section id="jdo.faq.lazy-loading.1-to-m-m-to-n">
           <title>
	           How do I configure the JDO mapping to use the lazy loading feature for 
	           1:m and M:N relations?
	       </title>
           
           <para>
	           Let us convert one of the classes from the 
	           <ulink urd="http://castor.org/examples.html"> JDO examples</ulink> 
	           to use lazy-loading.
           </para>

           <para>
	           In the example model, one Product can contain many ProductDetails. 
	           This is reflected in the conventional mapping as below. 
	           First, the mapping for Product:
	           <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<!--  Mapping for Product  -->
<class name="myapp.Product"
       identity="id">
   <description>Product definition</description>
   <map-to table="prod" xml="product" />
   <field name="id" type="integer">
       <sql name="id" type="integer" />
       <xml name="id" node="attribute"/>
   </field>
 
   <!-- more fields ... -->

   <!-- Product has reference to ProductDetail
            many details per product  -->
   <field name="details" type="myapp.ProductDetail" required="true"
           collection="vector">
       <sql many-key="prod_id"/>
       <xml name="detail" node="element" />
   </field>
</class>
	            ]]></programlisting>
           </para>
           
           <para>
	           Now let us examine ProductDetail. Note, the relationship is mapped 
	           <link linkend="jdo.faq.technical.bi-directional">bi-directionally</link> as must be 
	           all relationships when using Castor JDO.
	           <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<!--  Mapping for Product Detail -->
<class name="myapp.ProductDetail" identity="id" depends="myapp.Product" >
   <description>Product detail</description>
    <map-to table="prod_detail" xml="detail" />
   <field name="id" type="integer">
       <sql name="id" type="integer"/>
       <xml node="attribute"/>
    </field>
    <field name="product" type="myapp.Product">
       <sql name="prod_id" />
       <xml name="product" node="element" />
    </field>
   
       <!-- more fields ... -->
   
</class>
	           ]]>
	           </programlisting>
           </para>
           
           <para>
	           Let us now make the relationship between Product and ProductDetail use 
	           lazy loading. We need only change the way that the relationship to 
	           ProductDetail is specified in the mapping of Product. The relevant 
	           field in Product can be re-written like so: 
	           <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<field name="details" type="myapp.ProductDetail" required="true" lazy="true"
            collection="collection">
   <sql many-key="prod_id"/>
   <xml name="detail" node="element" />
</field>
           ]]>
           </programlisting>
           </para>
           
           <para>
	           There have been two changes.
	           <itemizedlist>
	               <listitem>
	                 <para>
		               We have placed the attribute lazy="true" in the field element
		             </para>
		           </listitem>
	               <listitem>
	                 <para>
		               We have changed the type of the underlying collection type to be 
		               a <literal>java.util.Collection</literal> by changing the field 
		               element attribute to collection="collection".
		             </para>
	               </listitem>
	           </itemizedlist>   
           </para>
           <para> 
           Note that no change is required in the ProductDetail mapping.
           </para>
       </section>

       
       <section id="jdo.faq.lazy-loading.no-method-error">
           <title>
               I have modified my mapping to use lazy loading. Now I get the error 
               'no method to set value for field: com.xyz.ClassB in class: 
               ClassMolder com.xyz.ClassA' or 
               'org.exolab.castor.jdo.DataObjectAccessException: no method to set 
               value for field: com.xyz.ClassB in class: ClassMolder com.xyz.ClassA'. 
               What am I doing wrong?
           </title>
           
           <para>
	           To use lazy loading you must also change the persistent class that 
	           will hold the related objects. At the very highest level, you need 
	           to provide a set method that accepts a java.util.Collection for the 
	           field in question. This is demonstrated by changing the 
	           <!-- TODO change link when More chapter is finished -->
	           <ulink url="http://castor.org/examples.html">JDO examples</ulink> below.
           </para>

           <para>
	           In the original Product class we have the following code:
	           <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
import java.util.Vector;
...
private Vector _details = new Vector();
...
public Vector getDetails()
{
   return _details;
}


public void addDetail( ProductDetail detail )
{
   _details.add( detail );
   detail.setProduct( this );
}
	           ]]></programlisting>
           </para>

           <para>
	           Let us now make the necessary changes to set up lazy loading. 
	           As stated above we now require a special set method for the related 
	           ProductDetails (stored originally as a 
	           <literal>java.util.Vector</literal>) that accepts a 
	           <literal>java.util.Collection</literal> as an argument. This mandates 
	           that we must also use a <literal>java.util.Collection</literal> to 
	           hold our ProductDetails. If this is not added, you will receive the 
	           errors above.
	           <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
import java.util.Collection;
...
private Collection _details;
...
public Collection getDetails()
{
   return _details;
}


public void setDetails( Collection details )
{
   _details = details;
}

	           ]]></programlisting>
           </para>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section id="jdo.faq.lob-tuning">
        <title>Tuning for LOBs</title>
        
        <para>
	        Castor JDO provides a property in <literal>castor.properties</literal> 
	        for adjusting the size of the JDBC driver's buffer for reading LOBs 
	        (BLOBs and CLOBs) from the database. The propery is named 
	        <literal>org.exolab.castor.jdo.lobBufferSize</literal> and its default 
	        is 5120 bytes (5k). The size of this buffer can be tuned for larger LOBs, 
	        but is dependent upon the JDBC driver implementation being used and what 
	        it supports. 
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="jdo.faq.database-specific">
        <title>Database-specific issues</title>
    
        <section id="jdo.faq.database-specific.hsql-identity-key-generators">
            <title>HSQL and identity key generators</title>
            
            <para>
               Due to a product limitation, AUTO_INCREMENT sequences in HSQL begin 
               with 0 rather 1, as is the case with most other RDBMS. As a result 
               of this, long transactions will not work for the object with the 
               identity 0, and a ObjectModifiedException will be thrown.
            </para>
               
            <para>
               To avoid this issue, we recommend inserting a temp object into the 
               database in question, and removing thereafter so that no object with 
               identity 0 is stored.
            </para>
	    </section>
	    
    </section>
    
    <section id="jdo.faq.change-configurations">
        <title>Changing database configurations</title>

        <para>
           Some applications need to change the database connection or switch 
           between different mapping files on the fly. Because Castor caches 
           database configurations per name, you would have to register a new 
           JDO configuration using a distinct name for any of the different 
           configurations.
        </para> 

		<para>
		   Instead you can call 
		   <methodname>org.exolab.castor.jdo.engine.DatabaseRegistry.clear()</methodname>
		   to reset the database registry before registering the new configuration as 
		   follows:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="java">
// Reset database registry
org.exolab.castor.jdo.engine.DatabaseRegistry.clear();
		</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>