<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document url="http://castor.org/srcgen-anttask.xml">

  <properties>
    <title>The Ant Tak for the Castor XML Code Generator</title>
    <author email="keith AT kvisco DOT com">Keith Visco</author>
    <author email="blandin@intalio.com">Arnaud Blandin</author>
    <abstract>
       Describes how to use Ant task for the Castor XML Code Generator, and what
       is currently supported.
    </abstract>
    <status>Final</status>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <title>Using the Ant task for the Castor XML Code Generator</title>
    <header>
      <p>API Reference: <api package="org.exolab.castor.builder">The Source Builder API</api></p>
    </header>

    <section title="Castor source generator Ant task">

        <p>An alternative to using the command line as shown in the previous section,
           the Castor Source Generator Ant Task can be used to call the source
           generator for class generation. The only requirement is that the 
           castor-&lt;version&gt;-srcgen-ant-task.jar must be on the CLASSPATH.</p>
           
        <section title="Configuration">
            
            <p>Please find below the complete list of parameters that can be set on the Castor 
               source generator.</p>
            
            <ctable>
                <cheader>
                    <th>Attribute</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                    <th>Required</th>
                </cheader>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>file</b></td>
                    <td>The XML schema, to be used as input for the source code generator.</td>
                    <td>Yes, unless a nested &lt;fileset&gt; element is used.</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>package</b></td>
                    <td>The default package to be used during source code generation.</td>
                    <td>No; if not given, all classes will be placed in the root package.</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>todir</b></td>
                    <td>The destination directory to be used during source code generation. In
                        this directory all generated Java classes will be placed.</td>
                    <td>No</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>bindingfile</b></td>
                    <td>A Castor source generator binding file, as detailed <a href="">here</a>.</td>
                    <td>No</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>lineseparator</b></td>
                    <td>Defines whether to use Unix- or Windows- or Mac-style line separators during source code generation. Possible values are: 'unix', 'win' or 'mac'.</td>
                    <td>No; if not set, system property 'line.separator' is used instead.</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>types</b></td>
                    <td>Defines what collection types to use (Java 1 vs. Java 2). Possible values: 'vector', 'arraylist' (aka 'j2') or 'odmg'.</td>
                    <td>No; if not set, the default collection used will be Java 1 type</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>verbose</b></td>
                    <td>Whether to output any logging messages as emitted by the source generator</td>
                    <td>No</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>warnings</b></td>
                    <td>Whether to suppress any warnings as otherwise emitted by the source generator</td>
                    <td>No</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>nodesc</b></td>
                    <td>If used, instructs the source generator not to generate *Descriptor classes.</td>
                    <td>No</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>nomarshal</b></td>
                    <td>If specified, instructs the source generator not to create (un)marshalling 
                        methods within the Java classes generated.</td>
                    <td>No</td>
                </crow>
                <crow>
                    <td><b>properties</b></td>
                    <td>Location of file defining a set of properties to be used during source code 
                        generation. This overrides the default mechanisms of configuring the source 
                        generator through a <tt>castorbuilder.properties</tt> (that has to be 
                        placed on the CLASSPATH)</td>
                    <td>No</td>
                </crow>
                
            </ctable>
            
        </section>
        
        <section title="Example">
            
            <p>Below is an example of how to use this task from within an Ant target 
               definition named 'castor:gen:src':</p>

            <code-panel>
  &lt;target name="castor:gen:src" depends="init"
             description="Generate Java source files from XSD."&gt;

    &lt;taskdef name="castor-srcgen"
                classname="org.exolab.castor.tools.ant.taskdefs.CastorSourceGenTask"
                classpathref="castor.class.path" /&gt;
    &lt;mkdir dir="generated" /&gt;
    &lt;castor-srcgen file="src/schema/sample.xsd"
                      todir="generated-source"
                      package="org.castor.example.schema"
                      types="j2"
                      warnings="true" /&gt;
  &lt;/target&gt;
            </code-panel>
        
        </section>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>

